[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "What is the other name for Flood Irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow Irrigation",
            "b) Lift Irrigation",
            "c) Surface Irrigation",
            "d) Uncontrolled irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is category which comes under Subsurface irrigation as sometimes, water from leakage of pipes, channels goes underground and causes rise in water table and this helps in irrigation of crops nearby. Irrigation by natural processes is called natural sub irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "In which of the following types of irrigation water is supplied to the crops throughout their crop period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perennial Irrigation",
            "b) Flood Irrigation",
            "c) Direct Irrigation",
            "d) Storage Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Normally this of irrigation is practiced in alluvial and deltaic regions where river water level is available in hot seasons, with this the soil is kept submerged and thoroughly flooded with water to thorough saturation of land. The water can be supplied to the land by flow, or partly by flow and partly by lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of irrigation system is practised on small scale in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Natural sub-irrigation",
            "b) Artificial sub-irrigation",
            "c) Flood Irrigation",
            "d) Lift Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In perennial irrigation, system water is supplied at a constant and continuous rate from perennial water sources, which get their supplies from melting snow, in accordance with the requirements of crop. Water is supplied by canal distribution system using a weir or reservoir."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "What is the other name of perennial irrigation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct Irrigation",
            "b) Storage Irrigation",
            "c) Controlled Irrigation",
            "d) Flood Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a system in which open joint drains is artificially laid below the soil, to supply water to the soil by capillarity. So, therefore it is very costly and can only be practiced in special cases, like favorable soil conditions and for cash crops of good return."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "In India most irrigation schemes fall under which category of irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) River Canal Irrigation",
            "b) Tank Irrigation",
            "c) Combined System",
            "d) Lift Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As perennial irrigation system works on perennial water sources, the flow of water in those sources can be controlled by the construction of canals, weirs, check dams, dams etc. So in this way there is no sudden rush of water during irrigation unlike in uncontrolled irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What type of irrigation scheme uses pick-up weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combined System",
            "b) Storage Irrigation",
            "c) Direct Irrigation",
            "d) Perennial Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this system solid barrier, such as a dam or a storage weir is constructed across the river and water is stored. Volume of storage required depends upon requirements of crops, or hydroelectric power generation and flow of water in the river, unlike the other type of irrigation systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Diversion scheme, comes under which type of irrigation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct Irrigation",
            "b) Storage Irrigation",
            "c) Flow Irrigation",
            "d) Inundation Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this system water is first stored at upstream side of the dam for power generation and then discharged back into the river at the downstream side of the dam. Thus, sufficient quantity of flow is again available in the river. At a suitable place in downstream pick-up weir is constructed to divert water to canals."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "In what type of irrigation system land property gets submerged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combined System",
            "b) Storage Irrigation",
            "c) Perennial Irrigation",
            "d) Flow Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In direct irrigation system water is directly diverted to the canal without storing water. For this system low diversion weir or diversion barrage is constructed across the river. So, this gives the diversion scheme for direct irrigation system over the other systems of irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Irrigation from wells is what type of irrigation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lift Irrigation",
            "b) Tank Irrigation",
            "c) Direct Irrigation",
            "d) Flow Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In storage irrigation system a solid structure such as dam, it forms a reservoir at the upstream side of the dam. Due to this, some land property gets submerged."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "What type of irrigation system needs mechanical means to supply water for irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combined System",
            "b) Storage Irrigation",
            "c) Lift Irrigation",
            "d) Perennial Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lift irrigation system mechanical means are used to supply water to the crops for irrigation. This is quite the case of wells where by mechanical means water is supplied for irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "In which of the following types of irrigation systems hydroelectric power can be generated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage Irrigation",
            "b) Perennial Irrigation",
            "c) Flood Irrigation",
            "d) Lift Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unlike any other irrigation systems lift irrigation system is used in when water supply is at too low level to run by gravitation on to the land. So, in such cases water is needed to be lifted by mechanical means for irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "What type of irrigation system is based merely on gravitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow Irrigation",
            "b) Direct Irrigation",
            "c) Lift Irrigation",
            "d) Storage Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dams are constructed in this type of irrigation system, which leads to formation of reservoir on the upstream side of the dam. The hydroelectric power is generated when water is released through the dam for irrigation, or any other multipurpose, or when reservoir is full."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "What type of irrigation method is also called as trickle irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sprinkler Irrigation Method",
            "b) Furrow Irrigation Method",
            "c) Drip Irrigation Method",
            "d) Check Flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this type of method, it involves laying a system of head, mains, sub-mains, laterals, and drip nozzles. From these nozzles, water oozes or trickles out at a small rate into the plant roots area. Hence the name trickle irrigation method."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What is the quality of a good irrigation method from the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil Erosion",
            "b) Drainage Troubles",
            "c) Leached Fertilizers",
            "d) Increased Yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This method of irrigation contains a pump to lift water so as to maintain a desired pressure, for ensuring proper flow of water through the system.so, as it contains a mechanical means to supply water, it comes under lift irrigation system."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "In which type of irrigation method wasteful use of water happens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wild Flooding",
            "b) Check Flooding",
            "c) Furrow Method",
            "d) Free Flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because good irrigation has uniform water distribution for both light irrigation and heavy irrigation. It also reduces conveyance and labor losses. It also facilitates mechanized farming. So, these advantages lead to increased yield."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which type of irrigation method can be used for both flat lands and relatively steep lands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free Flooding",
            "b) Basin Flooding",
            "c) Furrow Method",
            "d) Drip Irrigation Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This type of method is used in an inundation irrigation system in which water is forced to spread or flooded on a flat land, without much control or prior preparation. This leads to wasteful use of water."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which type of irrigation method uses supply ditch, borders, ridges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Border Flooding",
            "b) Check Flooding",
            "c) Basin Flooding",
            "d) Drip Irrigation Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Irrigation by this type of method is done, by dividing the entire land to be irrigated into a number strips called laterals. These laterals may be perpendicular to the sides of the field or perpendicular to the contour lines. So, as this method uses contour lines of field it is suitable for both flat lands and steep lands."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What kind of irrigation method uses artificial rain to irrigate the land?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sprinkler Irrigation Method",
            "b) Drip Irrigation Method",
            "c) Furrow Method",
            "d) Border Irrigation Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This type of method uses borders to divide the land into strips of with 10 to 20 meters, 100 to 400 meters in length each. Ridges are provided between borders so as to prevent overtopping during irrigation. Supply ditches run perpendicular to borders either on one side of the field to provide water for irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "What type of irrigation method is considered as the most advantageous method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drip Irrigation Method",
            "b) Sprinkler Irrigation Method",
            "c) Furrow Irrigation Method",
            "d) Border flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By looking at the diagram we can see the basins provided for the trees, main ditch, subsidiary ditches in a particular field. These are essential parts of basin flooding, whereas other methods do not contain basins, and trees in their irrigation procedure."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "With what type of mounting does a sprinkler irrigation network give the best results?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Revolving Sprinkler Heads",
            "b) Nozzles",
            "c) Open Pipes",
            "d) Pipes with holes near the crop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, water is applied to the field through a network of pipes connected to sprinklers of different types, and through these sprinklers, water comes out as artificial rain and waters the crops in the field."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Furrows of 150 m long and 2 m apart, have longitudinal slope of 0.5 percent are initially irrigated by non-erosive stream for 100 minutes. The stream size is reduced to 50% and continued for another 40 minutes. Determine the average depth of irrigation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50.34 mm",
            "b) 43.56 mm",
            "c) 47.58 mm",
            "d) 43.84 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This type of method can be used for any kind of crops, for all kinds of soils, and for widely different topographies and slopes. It can also be used in places of low or scarce availability of water, and also where water table is high. So, therefore it is the most advantageous method."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "In which type of irrigation method the entire land is not wetted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Furrow Method",
            "b) Free Flooding",
            "c) Contour Farming",
            "d) Basin Flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally in sprinkler irrigation system water flows with pressure in the pipes. So, sometimes the pressure may be low or high depending upon the water availability, and crop requirement. So, revolving sprinkler heads are mounted upon these rising pipes because these sprinklers can work under both high and low pressures."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "In which irrigation method levees are provided along the contours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Check Flooding",
            "b) Free Flooding",
            "c) Contour Farming",
            "d) Basin Flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a type of surface irrigation method. This method is mainly used in hilly areas having steep slopes with quickly falling contours. The area is divided into longitudinal curved plots called terrace with a dividing between them, contour bunds. The water flows between the bunds from higher ground to terrace, thus irrigating the crops."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "In which method of flooding, does the water take circuitous route to irrigate the land?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Check Flooding",
            "b) Zigzag Flooding",
            "c) Free Flooding",
            "d) Basin Flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Given L = 150 m and W = 2 m and s = 0.5%\nNow we have qm = 0.6/s = 0.6/0.5 = 1.2 lps\nNow q = 0.4qm = 0.4×1.2 = 0.48 lps\nAverage depth of water applied\n= (2 x 100 x 60 + 0.48 x 40 x 60) / 1000 x (1 / 300) x 1000\n= (12+1.152) / 300 x 1000\n= 43.84 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "What is the time interval between the sowing and harvesting of crops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base period",
            "b) Kor period",
            "c) Crop period",
            "d) Season period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Crop period is the time period that is elapsed from the instant of sowing to that of harvesting. Kor period is the time elapsed for kor watering. The base period is the time elapsed from first watering to the last watering."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What is the first step in soil preparation before sowing of seeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Levelling",
            "b) Ploughing",
            "c) Manuring",
            "d) Pre-watering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The watering stops before harvesting and base period is the time elapsed between first watering and the last watering till the crop matures. The total water requirement for the maturing process of the crop is non-uniform in the entire span which is also the crop period. Hence, both are assumed to be the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "The first watering before sowing the crop is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) paleo",
            "b) kor",
            "c) delta",
            "d) flooding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tillage is the technical term used for soil preparation to ensure ideal conditions for seed germination and growth of crops. It involves ploughing or dig-up, mix and overturning of the soil, followed by breaking the soil into small mass and then levelling the field."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What is called as the percentage of C.C.A irrigated at a time in one crop season?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross Command Area",
            "b) Culturable cultivated area",
            "c) Culturable uncultivated area",
            "d) Intensity of irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Kor period depends upon the climate. It is generally less for humid climates and more for dry climates. Crop type, length of the base period, the water requirement of plants at different stages, soil conditions, etc are all factors influencing the number of waterings."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Superfluous water is also called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) capillary water",
            "b) gravitational water",
            "c) hydroscopic water",
            "d) saturation capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Before sowing a crop first watering has to be done on the land to add sufficient water to the unsaturated zone of a soil which is required for the initial growth of the crop. This watering is known as Paleo."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The useful soil moisture for plant growth is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) capillary water",
            "b) gravitational water",
            "c) hydroscopic water",
            "d) permanent wilting point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Intensity of irrigation can be defined as “a ratio of irrigated land at a time one crop season to C.C.A”. Mathematically, Area to be irrigated = C.C.A x intensity of irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "What is the time interval between two consecutive watering called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crop Period",
            "b) Period",
            "c) Base Period",
            "d) Rotation Period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Every type of crop requires different amount of water for its complete growth in certain fixed intervals of time. The time interval between two consecutive intervals is called a rotation period."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "What is total depth of water, for complete growth of crop called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangle",
            "b) Delta",
            "c) Duty of Water",
            "d) Rotation Period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total quantity of water required by the crop for its complete growth can be expressed in terms of depth of water standing on the field. This total depth expressed in cm is called delta."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "What is the name of duty called as in direct irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow Duty",
            "b) Quantity Duty",
            "c) Duty",
            "d) Delta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duty of water gives a relation volume of water required and the area of irrigated crop. So, in this way if we know the area of crop irrigated we can know discharge required for the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which type of period is slightly more than its counterpart period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crop Period",
            "b) Period",
            "c) Base Period",
            "d) Rotation Period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When direct irrigation is used, then the units of duty, always expressed in hectares/cumec. Then duty is called flow duty."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which type of units is used to define high and low duty?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hectare-meters",
            "b) Hectares/cumec",
            "c) Meters",
            "d) Centimeters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crop period is time period between the instant of sowing to its harvesting. Base period is the time period between the first watering of crop to its final watering before harvesting."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which type of area is large in quantity compared to others?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross Commanded Area (G.C.A)",
            "b) Culturable Commanded Area (C.C.A)",
            "c) Culturable Cultivated Area",
            "d) Culturable Uncultivated Area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lift irrigation system due to the commanded area of each well near to it, gives a high value of duty when compared to flow irrigation system."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "In what type of area crop is not sown for a particular season?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross Commanded Area (G.C.A)",
            "b) Culturable Commanded Area (C.C.A)",
            "c) Culturable Cultivated Area",
            "d) Culturable Uncultivated Area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the number of hectares/cumec, if the irrigated area is large or small then it is called high or low duty respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Given that, a particular irrigation field has C.C.A as 200 hectares, out which 150 hectares of land is cultivated for rabi season and 100 hectares of land is cultivated for kharif season. What is the intensity of irrigation for each season?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%, 100%",
            "b) 120%, 60%",
            "c) 75%, 50%",
            "d) 150%, 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gross Commanded Area (G.C.A) is the sum of Culturable Commanded Area (C.C.A) and unculturable area. Again Culturable Commanded Area (C.C.A) is divided into the sum of culturable cultivated and culturable uncultivated areas. Therefore, Gross Commanded Area (G.C.A) is a large quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Given that a particular crop requires about 20 cm depth of water at an interval of 40 days, and the base period is 400 days. Find the delta for the crop? Now using this delta find the duty of water for the crop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 cm, 1150 hectares/cumec",
            "b) 180 cm, 1825 hectares/cumec",
            "c) 200 cm, 1728 hectares/cumec",
            "d) 195 cm, 1920 hectares/cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This type of area is not kept under cultivation because, to restore the fertility of the soil, to provide pasture land for animals, to prevent water logging in the land."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "It is said that a particular type of crop requires a depth of 6 cm of water every 24 days and the crop period is 168 days. Find the delta of the crop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 cm",
            "b) 42 cm",
            "c) 20 cm",
            "d) 95 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For rabi season:\nIntensity of irrigation = (150/200) x 100\n= 15 x 5\n= 75%\nFor kharif season:\nIntensity of irrigation = (100/200) x 100\n= 0.5 x 100\n= 50%. "
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "How can we improve the duty of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lining of Canals",
            "b) Construction of Weir",
            "c) Construction of Dam",
            "d) Check Dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given that base period is 400 days at an interval of 40 days. This number of waterings as = 400/40 = 10\nNow delta = 10 x 20 = 200 cm.\nNow we have relation between delta and duty as –\nDelta = (864B)/D\nB = base period, D = duty\n200 = (864 x 400)/D\nD = 864 x 2 = 1728 hectares/cumec."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which factor directly affects the duty of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of Crop",
            "b) Useful Rainfall",
            "c) Type of Soil",
            "d) Canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Assume that crop period is equal to base period. So, given base period is 168 days, and it requires watering for every 24 days. Therefore number of waterings for entire cultivation = (168/24) = 7\nEach watering needs 6 cm depth of water. So, therefore total depth of water required in 168 days = 7 x 6 = 42 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "At which point in the entire canal system the duty of water will be more?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head of the Water-course",
            "b) Head of the Minor",
            "c) Head of the Distributary",
            "d) Head of the Branch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By lining of canals, carrying irrigation supplies we can reduce seepage and evaporation losses. Therefore reducing the field requirement of water increases the duty."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a top Cotton growing state in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gujarat",
            "b) Maharashtra",
            "c) Andhra Pradesh",
            "d) Bihar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cotton is generally grown in black soil. Major cotton-producing states are Gujarat, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Karnataka, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which one below is an example of the overlapping crop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tobacco",
            "b) Wheat",
            "c) Millets",
            "d) Sugarcane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  When a crop of one season extends into another season, the overlapping condition exists; crops of both the season require water simultaneously. The extra amount of water required for this purpose is called over-lap allowance. Sugarcane is an example of this kind."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Heavy retentive soil is favorable for which type of crop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sugarcane and Rice",
            "b) Maize",
            "c) Gram and fodder crops",
            "d) Cotton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heavy retentive soils contain 40% clay and tend to be more fertile is suitable for raising crops like sugarcane and rice requiring more water. Gram and fodder crops require less water, suitable in light sandy soil (2-8% clay). Cotton and maize require a normal amount of water."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "What is the crop ratio of Kharif to rabi crops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2",
            "b) 1:4",
            "c) 1:3",
            "d) 2:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crop ratio can be defined as the ratio of areas under the crops of two main seasons. The Kharif area is one-half of the rabi area as this value is generally 1:2."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which one the following combination is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kharif crops – Rice, maize",
            "b) Rabi crops – Wheat, mustard",
            "c) Zaid crops – cotton, sugarcane",
            "d) Cash crops – jute, tobacco"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The zaid crops are the short term crops grown during the period between Rabi and Kharif crops i.e from March to June. They are best grown in summers and some common examples are cucumber, pumpkin, watermelon, and muskmelon."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Who is the ‘Father of Indian Green Revolution’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dr. William Gaude",
            "b) Dr. M.S Swaminathan",
            "c) Norman Borlaug",
            "d) Dr. Varghese Kurien"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Groundnut is generally grown as a Kharif crop and relies much on rainfall, but the productivity is low. To increase productivity paleo and irrigation is considered as basic input and rainfall as a supplement."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which Indian state is Worlds first organic state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Punjab",
            "b) Assam",
            "c) Arunachal Pradesh",
            "d) Sikkim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Swaminathan is known for his leadership and success for developing the production level of food grains. He stressed on adopting the best scientific techniques and promoting organic farming."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which state leads to the consumption of fertilizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Haryana",
            "b) Punjab",
            "c) Andhra Pradesh",
            "d) UP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In January 2016, Sikkim became India’s first “100 percent organic state” and has been awarded UN Future Policy Gold Award 2018 for best policies. All the farming in Sikkim is carried out without the use of fertilizers and pesticides making agriculture more eco-friendly activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "In crop-rotation, a cash crop may be followed by a fodder crop, which is then followed by soil renovating crop like ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rice",
            "b) Maize",
            "c) Oats",
            "d) Grams and pulses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Punjab is ranked first with 184 Kg/hectare fertilizer consumption followed by Haryana, Andhra Pradesh, and UP. The Overall average consumption in India is 90 Kg/hectare."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "What are the climatic conditions required for growing rice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fertile clay soil, 70-200 cm rainfall, temperature 20°C-27°C",
            "b) Fertile soil, 50-75 cm rainfall, temperature 20°C-25°C",
            "c) Nitrogen-rich soil, 50-80 cm rainfall, temperature 25°C-30°C",
            "d) Sulfur-rich soil, 150-200 cm rainfall, temperature 15°C-20°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Grams and pulses are leguminous plants which increase the fertility of the soil by fixing environmental nitrogen with the help of Rhizobium bacteria. This helps reducing crop diseases and wastage due to insects and hence increases overall crop yield."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The O.M.C is the water content at which the yield is maximum",
            "b) Below O.M.C, the yield increases with water content to a certain value",
            "c) After O.M.C, the yield decreases with the water content",
            "d) After O.M.C, the yield increases with the water content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: OMC is the moisture content at which the yield of the crop is maximum. Below OMC, sufficient water is not available so, the yield of the crop is less. After OMC, the sufficient amount of air is not available so, the productivity decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The optimum utilisation of irrigation water means _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Getting maximum yield with the maximum amount of water available",
            "b) Getting maximum yield with any amount of water",
            "c) Getting less yield with maximum water content",
            "d) Getting less yield with the least water content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It generally means getting maximum yield with any amount of water. The water to be supplied should be such that so as to get optimum benefit ratio. It is done not only for the efficient use of water and maximum yield but, also to prevent waterlogging."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which factor doesn’t influence the root zone depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of soil",
            "b) Type of crops grown",
            "c) Sub-soil formation",
            "d) The yield of the crop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The yield increases with water, reaches a certain maximum value and then, falls down. The quantity of water at this maximum value is called optimum water depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Which efficiency is also called on-farm efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water conveyance efficiency",
            "b) Water application efficiency",
            "c) Water storage efficiency",
            "d) Water use efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water application efficiency is the ratio of water stored in the root zone to the water actually delivered to the field. It takes into consideration the water lost in the farm hence, it is also known as on-farm efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What is water conveyance efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ratio of the quantity of water delivered to the field and quantity of water pumped into the canal",
            "b) The ratio of water stored in the root zone and the water delivered to the field",
            "c) The ratio of water used beneficially and the water delivered to the field",
            "d) The ratio of water stored in the root zone and the water needed before irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the ratio of water delivered into the fields to the water entering into the channel. This efficiency accounts for the conveyance or transit losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "The mean depth of water is 1.5 cm and the mean deviation from the mean is 0.1 cm. Determine its distribution efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 85%",
            "c) 66.66%",
            "d) 93%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The beneficially used water accounts for the water required for leaching and by the crop as well. This is required in calculating water use efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The presence of excess salts in the soil requires _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high water storage efficiency",
            "b) low water storage efficiency",
            "c) high water application efficiency",
            "d) high water use efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formula for distribution efficiency is:\nNd = (1- d/D) x 100; where d = mean deviation and D = mean depth of water\nGiven, d=0.1 cm and D = 1.5 cm\nHence, Nd = 93%."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong about consumptive use efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the ratio of normal consumptive use of water to the net amount of water depleted from the root zone",
            "b) It accounts for the loss of water by deep percolation",
            "c) Evaporation losses are considered",
            "d) The losses due to percolation and evaporation are not considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Leaching is the supply of additional water to wash away the salts in a saline prone area. The presence of excess salts in water requires high water storage efficiency in order to keep the salts washed out of the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "The quantity of water that is pumped into a farm distribution system is 2 cumec. 1.6 cumec is delivered to a turn-out, 1km from the well. Compute the conveyance efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 60%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  It is the ratio of normal consumptive use of water to the net amount of water depleted from the root zone. It accounts for the loss of water by deep percolation and evaporation following irrigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Determine the distribution efficiency, if the depths of water in the field are 1.1 cm and 1.8 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80%",
            "b) 90%",
            "c) 85%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  By definition, Conveyance efficiency Nc = (output/input) x 100\nGiven, Output = 1.6 cumec and Input = 2 cumec\nSo, Nc = 80%."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Uniformity coefficient is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) water conveyance efficiency",
            "b) consumptive use efficiency",
            "c) water distribution efficiency",
            "d) water storage efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Efficiency is inversely proportional to the losses. If losses are more, the output is less and therefore, efficiency is less."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "The water distribution efficiency is 1.0 if _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the deviation from the mean depth is 1",
            "b) the deviation from the mean depth is 0",
            "c) the deviation from the mean depth is less than 1",
            "d) the deviation from the mean depth is greater than 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mean depth (D) = (1.1 + 1.80) / 2 = 1.45\nDeviation from mean depth (d) = 1.80 – 1.45 = 1.1 – 1.45 = 0.35 (neglecting negative sign)\nNd = (1 – d/D) x 100 = 75%."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "What is the correct formula for uniformity coefficient efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nd = 1 – d/D",
            "b) Nd = 1 + d/D",
            "c) Nd = 1 – D/d",
            "d) Nd = 1 + D/d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water distribution efficiency is also known as the uniformity coefficient. It is the measure of how uniformly water is applied to the area being irrigated. The effectiveness of irrigation is measured by its uniformity coefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "What is the process of a plant called, through which it leaves water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photosynthesis",
            "b) Transpiration",
            "c) Evapotranspiration",
            "d) Chlorosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Consumptive use is defined as the total amount of water used by the plants in transpiration and evaporation from soils, in specific time. So, therefore the values of consumptive use vary for different crops, and vary for same crops at different places or times."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which protein in the leaf of the plant utilize carbon dioxide and produce carbohydrates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chloroplasts",
            "b) Stomata",
            "c) Xylene",
            "d) Leaf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transpiration is the process of the plant through which water leaves the plant, through its leaves as water vapor and enters the atmosphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "On which factor does the transpiration loss also depends on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Available Moisture",
            "b) Type of Soil",
            "c) Type of Irrigation",
            "d) Method of Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yes, photosynthesis is an important process of the plant through which the plant produces carbohydrates for its growth, and it is during this process transpiration occurs as an integral process in the whole photosynthesis process."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "On what factor does transpiration ratio depends on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Soil",
            "c) Air",
            "d) Moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Water enters the leaves of the plant through the roots, where photosynthesis happens. During this, air enters the stomata of the leaves. The protein chloroplasts present here takes the carbon dioxide in air and uses it to produce carbohydrates."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "In transpiration ratio what type of crop is considered to be weighed, for mass of dry matter produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Marketed Crop",
            "b) Cash Crop",
            "c) Horticulture Crop",
            "d) Plantation Crop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Preparation of food, i.e carbohydrates is done during daylight alone, as photosynthesis process occurs only during sunlight. Therefore most of the transpiration occurs during the day alone."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Given information is that total mass of water required for the growth of a plant is 285 kgs, and mass of the marketed crop is 19 kgs. Find the transpiration ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Availability of moisture also affects the transpiration losses because plants transpire moisture according to its availability. That is plants transpire less moisture when moisture is scarce, and transpire more moisture when it is more available."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "A crop is being tested in the lab to its loss due to transpiration. Given that initial weight of instrument is 100 kgs, and final mass of instrument is 150 kgs. The amount of water added during full growth of plant is 70 kgs. Find the loss due transpiration when the method used is phytometer method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 kgs",
            "b) 15 kgs",
            "c) 25 kgs",
            "d) 10 kgs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transpiration ratio is directly proportional to water requirement of the plant. So, therefore if amount of water increases the ratio increases, and if amount of water decreases the ratio decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "By what number should the value from the phytometer method be multiplied when it comes to obtain possible field results?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 9",
            "d) A Constant Number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mass of dry matter is taken as the weight of the entire plant including its roots. And also sometimes only marketed crop like wheat, gram etc is weighed."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which type of soil has less ratio of AET/PET than the other?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clayey Soil",
            "b) Sandy Soil",
            "c) Alluvial Soil",
            "d) Black Soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We have transpiration ratio (TR) = (total mass of water transpired by the plant during its growth / mass of dry matter produced)\n= (285/19)\n= 15."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "On what factors Potential Evapotranspiration critically depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climatological Factors",
            "b) Types of Crop",
            "c) Types of Soils",
            "d) Vegetation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When phytometer method is used the formula for transpiration loss (T)\n= (M1 + M) – (M2)\nM1 = initial mass of instrument\nM = mass of water added during full growth of plant\nM2 = final mass of instrument\nTherefore (T) = (100 + 70) – 150 = 170 – 150 = 20 kgs."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "On what factors Actual Evapotranspiration depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climatological Factors",
            "b) Types of Crop",
            "c) Types of Soils",
            "d) Characteristics of Soil and Vegetation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the phytometer method is tested in lab in artificial conditions, the obtained result is only relevant to the lab due different soil conditions in the open field. So, therefore in order to get or obtain exact field results we need to multiply the value of transpiration loss obtained from the method with a constant number."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which type of method is adopted for research studies on crops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phytometer Method",
            "b) Lysimeter Method",
            "c) Furrow Irrigation Method",
            "d) Drip Irrigation Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio AET/PET is directly proportional to available moisture. Sandy soil has less availability of moisture than the other type of soils like clayey soil, alluvial soil, and black soil. So, this gives that sandy soil has less AET/PET ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about Effective rainfall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It doesn’t take into consideration precipitation lost through deep percolation",
            "b) It satisfies evapotranspiration needs of the crop",
            "c) It includes surface runoff loss",
            "d) It doesn’t include surface runoff water loss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Effective rainfall is that portion of precipitation that remains in the soil and is available for consumptive use. It is available to meet the evapotranspiration needs of the crop and does not include percolation losses and surface runoff losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "What is the field irrigation requirement (FIR)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The water required to meet the evaporation needs of a crop",
            "b) Amount of water required to delivered at the field to meet evapotranspiration and leaching needs",
            "c) Amount of water required to meet the net irrigation requirements plus water lost due to surface runoff and percolation",
            "d) Amount of water required to meet the field irrigation requirements plus water lost in conveyance through the canal system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FIR can be defined as the water required meeting the net irrigation requirements plus the amount of water lost as surface runoff and through deep percolation.\nMathematically, FIR = NIR / Na where Na = application efficiency and NIR = Net irrigation requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "What is the correct representation for the calculation of NIR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cu – Re",
            "b) CIR + leaching losses",
            "c) FIR + conveyance losses",
            "d) FIR + leaching losses + conveyance losses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Net irrigation requirement (NIR) can be defined as the amount of irrigation water required to be delivered at the field to meet the evapotranspiration and leaching losses.\nNIR = (Cu – Re) + amount of water required for leaching = CIR + leaching losses requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Determine the Gross irrigation requirement for an irrigation system if consumptive use of crop is 200 cm in terms of depth and the rainfall excess is 30 cm. assume water application efficiency = 50% and conveyance efficiency = 90%.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 370 cm",
            "b) 380.79 cm",
            "c) 355.56 cm",
            "d) 377.77 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Given, Cu = 200 cm, Re = 30 cm, Na = 50%, Nc = 90%\nNIR = CIR + losses = (200-300) + 0 = 170 cm\nFIR = NIR / Na = 170/0.5 = 340 cm\nGIR = FIR / Nc = 340/0.9 = 377.77 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "An outlet irrigates an area of 40 ha. The discharge required at this outlet to meet the evapotranspiration requirement of 40 mm occurring uniformly in 40 days neglecting other field losses is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.52 litres / sec",
            "b) 2.31 litres / sec",
            "c) 4.01 litres / sec",
            "d) 1.52 litres / sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Volume of water required for evapo-transpiration = 40 x 104 x 40 x 10-3 x 103 = 16 x 106 litres\nHence, the discharge required at outlet\n= (16 x 106) / (40 x 86400)\n= 4.52 litres / sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "The moisture holding capacity of the soil in a 100-hectare farm is 20 cm/m. The root zone depth of the crop is 1.0 m and peak rate to moisture use is 5 mm/day. The field is to be irrigated when 40% of the available moisture in the root zone is depleted. Calculate the frequency of irrigation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 days",
            "b) 18 days",
            "c) 20 days",
            "d) 25 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moisture holding capacity is 20 cm/m and the root zone depth = 1 m\nMoisture holding capacity of soil for crop = 20 x 1 = 20 cm\nAllowable depletion of moisture = 40% of 20 cm = 8 cm\n Consumptive use of water= 5 mm/day = 0.5 cm/day\nThe frequency of irrigation = 8 / 0.5 = 16 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "What is the correct formula for Gross irrigation requirement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cu – Re",
            "b) CIR + leaching losses",
            "c) NIR/Na",
            "d) FIR/Nc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is defined as the amount of water required to meet the field irrigation requirements plus the amount of irrigation water lost in conveyance through the canal system by evaporation and seepage.\nMathematically, GIR = FIR/Nc."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Options": [
            "a) 41.60 cm",
            "b) 41.60 mm",
            "c) 44 cm",
            "d) 44 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NIR = consumptive use – effective rainfall.\n\n\nDates\nCu (in mm)\nRe (in mm)\nNIR = Cu – Re\n\n\n16-31 October\n37\n30.8\n6.2\n\n\n1-30 November\n84.2\n20.4\n63.8\n\n\n1-31 December\n154.9\n6.7\n148.2\n\n\n1-31 January\n188.1\n2.4\n185.7\n\n\n1-10 February\n13.3\n1.0\n12.3\n\n\n\n\n\tSummation of all values of NIR = 416.2 mm = 41.62 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which formula is extensively used for estimating seasonal water requirements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blaney-Criddle formula",
            "b) Hargreaves pan evaporation method",
            "c) Penman’s equation",
            "d) Christiansen formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This formula is also used for estimating monthly consumptive use.\nBlaney-Criddle formula is written as Cu = k.f  where, f = p/40[1.8t + 32].\nWhere Cu = monthly/seasonal consumptive use, k = crop factor, p = monthly % of annual daylight hours in that period, and t = mean monthly temperature"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which method is time-consuming and expensive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tanks and Lysimeter",
            "b) Vapour transfer method",
            "c) Field plot method",
            "d) Integration method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the Lysimeter method, the plants are grown in the tank with a sand layer at the bottom and a pan for collecting the surplus water. The consumptive use is measured by the amount of water required for the satisfactory growth of plants within tanks. Other methods are more reliable than this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an empirical method of determining consumptive use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lowry Johnson method",
            "b) Penman’s equation",
            "c) Hargreaves method",
            "d) Inflow-outflow method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inflow-outflow method is a direct method in which field observations are made and physical models are used for the purpose. Lowry Johnson, Penman, and Hargreaves method are all empirical methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "The monthly consumptive use values for paddy are 26.69, 8.76, 14.38, 22.73, 21.29, 25.50 and 15.06 for the duration of month from June to July. What is the average daily consumptive use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.0 mm",
            "b) 8.0 mm",
            "c) 7.5 mm",
            "d) 8.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The production of the rate of absorption of solar energy is high in dark green vegetation hence; its evapotranspiration rate will be higher than that of light green vegetation. The plant diseases causing yellowing of the leaves of the plants greatly reduce evapotranspiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong about consumptive use coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is different for different crops",
            "b) It varies with the crop growth",
            "c) It is different for the same crop at different places",
            "d) It is independent of the crop type and its growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total consumptive use for paddy = 29.69 + 8.76 + 14.38 + 22.73 + 21.29 + 25.50 + 15.06 = 137.41 cm\nAverage daily consumptive use = 137.41 / period of growth in days\n= 137.41 / (30+31+31+30+31+30) = 7.5 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "What is the range of reflection coefficient for close-grained crops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.15-0.25",
            "b) 0.05-0.45",
            "c) 0.05",
            "d) 0.45-0.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Consumptive use coefficient (k) = evapotranspiration (Cu or Et) / pan evaporation (Ep). It is different for different crops, varies with crop growth and is different at different crop stages for the same crop."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which method is widely used in India for the computation of consumptive use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penman’s equation",
            "b) Hargreaves – Christiansen equation",
            "c) Blaney-Criddle equation",
            "d) Tanks and lysimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of reflection coefficient for different surfaces are-\n\n\nClose-grained crops\n0.15-0.25\n\n\nBare lands\n0.05-0.45\n\n\nWater surface\n0.05\n\n\nSnow\n0.45-0.90\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The average value of Et/Ep for citrus crops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.90",
            "b) 0.7-1.10",
            "c) 0.60",
            "d) 0.66-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value obtained from Penman’s equation is almost equal to the values obtained from the actual field observations made in pan evaporation method. The values obtained from the Blaney-Criddle equation were on the much higher side (about 30%) and the values obtained from the Hargreaves method is on the lower side (about 15%-20%). Lysimeter method is time-consuming and expensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The monthly consumptive use is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cu = k.p/40 [1.8t + 32] ",
            "b) Cu = k.p/40 [1.8t – 32] ",
            "c) Cu = k.p/40 [t + 32] ",
            "d) Cu = k.p/40 [t – 32]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Et/Ep ratio is consumptive use coefficient (k). Group F includes citrus fruits like oranges, grapefruit, etc. the Et/Ep ratio is fairly constant throughout the year and average to a value of about 0.60."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which method involves the use of crop factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penman’s equation",
            "b) Hargreaves method",
            "c) Blaney-Criddle Formula",
            "d) Tanks and Lysimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blaney-Criddle Formula is expressed as Cu = k.f\nWhere, f = p/40 [1.8t + 32], Cu = seasonal consumptive use and k = crop factor. Crop factor is determined by experiments under environmental conditions of the particular area for each crop."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "What are the dimensions of the standard class-A pan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diameter-1.2 m, Depth – 25 cm",
            "b) Diameter-2 m, Depth – 25 cm",
            "c) Diameter-2 m, Depth – 30 cm",
            "d) Diameter-1.2 m, Depth – 30 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Class-A pan is used for experimental determination of pan evaporation. This pan has a diameter of 1.2 m, 25 cm deep, and the bottom is raised 15 cm above the ground surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Penman’s equation for the estimation of PET has been derived by using ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) energy balance approach",
            "b) mass transfer approach",
            "c) combination of energy balance approach and mass transfer approach",
            "d) combination of energy balance approach and energy transfer approach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula was developed by Penman in 1948 for determining the consumptive use of different areas of the basin. This formula has sound theoretical reasoning and is derived by combining energy balance and mass transfer approaches for the computation of transpiration and evaporation respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Albedo or reflection coefficient factor is used in which method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blaney- Criddle equation",
            "b) Christiansen equation",
            "c) Penman equation",
            "d) Tank and Lysimeter method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Albedo is a factor used in Penman’s equation which is used for a different type of areas for calculation of consumptive use. The value of albedo varies for water surface, bare lands and snow."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Penman’s equation can also be used to compute evaporation from a water surface like a lake if _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reflection coefficient = 0.05",
            "b) reflection coefficient > 0.05",
            "c) reflection coefficient < 0.05",
            "d) reflection coefficient = 0.45- 0.90"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of reflection factor or albedo varies for water surface, bare lands and snow. When the value is equal to 0.05, it can be used to compute evaporation from a water surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "What is the consumptive use for a crop in the month of April having a consumptive use coefficient equal to 0.80 and pan evaporation is 35 cm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28 cm",
            "b) 43.75 cm",
            "c) 35.80 cm",
            "d) 40.80 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Christiansen formula for pan evaporation is Ep = 0.459 R.Ct.Cw.Ch.Cs.Ce where, R = Extra-terrestrial radiation in cm\nCt = Coefficient of temperature\nCw = Coefficient for wind velocity\nCh = Coefficient for relative humidity\nCs = Coefficient for percent of possible sunshine\nCe = Coefficient of elevation."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Compute the total consumptive use for a drainage basin by Penman’s formula. The slope of saturation vapour pressure V/s chart at 40°C is 2.95 mm of Hg/°C and the net incoming solar radiation is 5.705 mm of evaporative water/day. Assume, Ea = 18.07 mm/day and Psychrometric constant = 0.49 mm of Hg/°C.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17.01 mm/day",
            "b) 18 mm/day",
            "c) 11.07 mm/day",
            "d) 20.45 mm/day"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula is Et = k. Ep\nEt = 0.8 x 35 = 28 cm\nHence, the required value of consumptive use = 28 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression of parameter Ea in Penman’s equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ea = 0.35 (1 + V2/160) (es – ea)",
            "b) Ea = 0.35 (1 + V2/160) (es + ea)",
            "c) Ea = 0.35 (1 – V2/160) (es – ea)",
            "d) Ea = 0.35 (1 – V2/160) (es + ea)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Penman’s formula for Cu is equal to [A.Hn + Ea.Y] / (A + Y)\nCu = [2.95 x 5.705 + 18.07 x 0.49] / (2.95 + 0.49)\nCu = 17.01 mm/day."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which zone is the most important from an irrigation point of view?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil Zone",
            "b) Intermediate Zone",
            "c) Capillary Zone",
            "d) Saturation Zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From this soil zone plants take their water requirements which are needed during their growth. As in this zone roots of the plants are present."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is the name of water which flows under gravity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hygroscopic Water",
            "b) Gravity Water",
            "c) Capillary Water",
            "d) Residue Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When water flows over the land, some water is absorbed in the root zone and remaining water flows underground due to the action of gravity, hence the name gravity water."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "How many days are generally taken to obtain field capacity after free gravity drainage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 to 7 days",
            "b) 4 to 8 days",
            "c) 5 to 9 days",
            "d) 2 to 5 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Immediately after application of irrigation water or sudden rain the gravity water drains down to the water table. But certain amount of water gets retained on the surfaces of soil grains and this water cannot be easily drained under action of gravity. This water is called field capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "By what type of forces the soil grains retain water on their surfaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capillary Forces",
            "b) Cohesive Forces",
            "c) Molecular Attraction and by Loose Chemical Bonds",
            "d) Compressive Forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Generally field capacity is defined as the water content of soil that is left after free gravity drainage for certain period of time. This period of free gravity drainage is generally taken as 2 to 5 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Based on surface tension, what is the name of the part of field capacity water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hygroscopic Water",
            "b) Gravity Water",
            "c) Capillary Water",
            "d) Residue Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to these forces like molecular attraction between adjacent soil grains and by their loose chemical bonds, i.e adsorption, the soil grains are able to retain water against the action of gravity on their surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Based on loose chemical bonds, what is the name of the part of field capacity water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hygroscopic Water",
            "b) Gravity Water",
            "c) Capillary Water",
            "d) Residue Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Capillary water is that part of field capacity water, which is attached to the soil molecules by surface tension against the gravitational forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Determine the field capacity, when the unit weight of water is 9.8 KN/m3, and volume of water stored in unit area of soil is 28 m3, the dry unit weight of soil is 18 KN/m3, and the depth of root zone of the plant is 7 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.178 m2",
            "b) 2.135 m2",
            "c) 2.125 m2",
            "d) 2.25 m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water which is attached to the soil molecules due to the influence of their loose chemical bonds is called hygroscopic water. This is a part of field capacity water."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Determine the volume of water stored in unit area if unit weight of water is 9.8 KN/m3, dry unit of soil is 17 KN/m3, field capacity (F) is 2.35 m2, and depth of root zone of the plant is 9 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36.69 m3",
            "b) 36 m3",
            "c) 36.12 m3",
            "d) 36.25m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The capillary water can be extracted by the plants by capillary action or capillarity. But, hygroscopic water cannot be extracted by the capillarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Up to which point plants can extract water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturation Point",
            "b) Permanent Wilting Point",
            "c) Hydration Point",
            "d) Dissolution Point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We have, field capacity (F) = (weight of water retained in unit area of soil / weight of same volume of dry soil)\nWeight of water retained in unit area of soil = γw x volume of water stored in unit area\n= 9.8 x 28\n= 274.4 KN\nWeight of same volume of dry soil = γd x d (where, γw = unit weight of water, γd = dry unit weight of soil)\n= 18 x 7\n= 126 KN/m2\nNow field capacity (F) = (274.4 / 126)\n= 2.178 m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "What is the name of actual available water to the plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Available Moisture",
            "b) Moisture",
            "c) Capillary Water",
            "d) Hygroscopic Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We have field capacity (F) = (γw x volume of stored in unit area of soil / γd x d)\nTherefore volume of stored water = (γd. d. F / γw)\n= (17 x 9 x 2.35 / 9.8) (where, γw = unit weight of water, γd = dry unit weight of soil)\n= 359.55 / 9.8\n= 36.69 m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "By what percentage of available moisture is easily extracted by plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80 to 90%",
            "b) 75 to 80%",
            "c) 70 to 80%",
            "d) 65 to 70%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At permanent wilting point plants can no longer extract sufficient water for its growth and wilts up. Plants are able to extract water from the soil till this point is reached. This is the point at which permanent wilting of plants take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which type of moisture is slightly less or most equal to field capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equivalent Moisture",
            "b) Soil Moisture Deficiency",
            "c) Available Moisture",
            "d) Readily Available Moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amount water available to the plants is the difference between field capacity water and permanent wilting point water. This amount of water is known as Available moisture or maximum storage capacity of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which type of moisture acts as a bridge between soil moisture content and field capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equivalent Moisture",
            "b) Soil Moisture Deficiency",
            "c) Available Moisture",
            "d) Readily Available Moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Readily available moisture is that part of available moisture which can be easily extracted by plants and of 75 to 80% of available moisture."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about alluvial soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is formed by sediment deposition of silt from the flowing water",
            "b) The area of alluvial soil is even",
            "c) It has a flat surface slope",
            "d) Hard foundations are generally available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The process of silt deposition over a long period of time resulting in the formation of soil is called alluvial soil. It has a flat surface slope and even area. Hard foundations are generally not available in this kind of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Canal irrigation is generally preferred in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) alluvial canal",
            "b) non-alluvial canal",
            "c) non-perennial canal",
            "d) feeder canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disintegration of mountainous rocks over a period of time resulting in the formation of a rocky plain area called non-alluvial soils. It has uneven topography and hard foundations are available in this soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which of the following combination is not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feeder canal – no direct irrigation is carried out",
            "b) Protective canal – constructed as a relief work during the famine",
            "c) Lined canal – provided with a lining of impervious material on its bed",
            "d) Contour canal – provision of cross drainage works is not required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Direct irrigation using a weir or barrage (canal irrigation) is generally preferred in alluvial soil as compared to storage irrigation. Alluvial soil is a fine-grained fertile soil and due to its porosity and texture provides good drainage making it highly productive and suitable for agriculture."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which canal is not provided with any headworks for diversion of river water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permanent canal",
            "b) Feeder canal",
            "c) Perennial canals",
            "d) Inundation canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A feeder canal is used to feed another canal and no direct irrigation is carried out from it. A protective canal is constructed to provide employment in the famine-affected area. A lined canal is provided with a lining of impervious material to prevent the seepage of water. A contour canal has to cross the drainage and hence, cross drainage works are required."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "The velocity of the flowing water in a navigation canal should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high",
            "b) very high",
            "c) small",
            "d) medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An inundation canal is a canal which gets its supplies only when the water level in the river from which it takes off rises during floods. They obtain their supplies through open cuts in the banks of the river."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which one is well traded and is provided with permanent regulation and distribution works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inundation canals",
            "b) Permanent canals",
            "c) Alluvial canal",
            "d) Navigation canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A navigation canal is constructed to provide various navigation facilities. The velocity of flowing water should be small for easy movement of small ships and barges in the direction of flow of water as well as in the opposite direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which canal acts as an irrigation canal as well as a feeder canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feeder canal",
            "b) Carrier canal",
            "c) Inundation canal",
            "d) Permanent canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A permanent canal is the one that is fed by a permanent source of supply. The provision of permanent regulation and distribution works is made in the permanent canal. It is further classified as Perennial canals and non-perennial canals."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": " A canal which when fully developed yields enough revenue to cover up its running cost is known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) protective canal",
            "b) productive canal",
            "c) permanent canal",
            "d) inundation canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A carrier canal is a canal used for both direct irrigation and for feeding water to another canal. Thus, it acts as an irrigation canal as well as a feeder canal. Upper Chenab Canal is an example of this type of canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which type of canal does not need cross drainage structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope Canal",
            "b) Contour Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Side slope canal is that type of canal which runs perpendicular to the ground contours, i.e they run parallel to natural drainage flow and do not intercept the drainage channels and therefore avoiding the construction of cross drainage structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "What is the name given to the junction of two streams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ridge",
            "b) Area of Mixture",
            "c) Merging",
            "d) Area of Mingling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dividing line between the catchment areas of two streams is called ridge or watershed. The main watershed between two streams divides the drainage area of the two streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "On flatlands what type of canal alignment is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope Canal",
            "b) Contour Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For flat lands, the slopes are relatively flat and uniform and it is very easy, and advantageous to align canals along watershed. Therefore the name of the alignment is watershed canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which type of canal is most useful in hilly areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope Canal",
            "b) Contour Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By aligning a canal on the ridge, helps to irrigate the land on both sides of the canal. Moreover, the drainage flows away from the ridge, this gives an advantage in a way that the drainage does not cross a canal aligned on the ridge. Therefore the cost of construction of cross drainage works is reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "What type of canal necessitates construction of cross drainage works more than any other types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope Canal",
            "b) Contour Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The idea of watershed canal in hilly areas is does not work because it is highly uneconomical, since the river flows in valley below the ridge. And the watershed may be hundreds of meters above the river."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which type of canal is the farmer’s responsibility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contour Canal",
            "b) Side Slope Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this canal the river slope is much steeper than the canal bed slope so therefore the canal encloses more and more area between itself and the river. It should be noted that more fertile lands are located at the lower levels. In other words we can say contour canal irrigates only on one side as the other side is higher."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which type of canal need syphons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope Canal",
            "b) Contour Canal",
            "c) Watershed Canal",
            "d) Field Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this contour canal the drainage of the river flow is always perpendicular to the ground contours, and this would certainly require crossing of natural drains and streams, which necessitates the construction of cross drainage structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "If a looping is present in the ridge line they how can that area be irrigated with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distributary",
            "b) Tributary",
            "c) Weir",
            "d) Canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The image indicates an alignment of canal perpendicular to the ground contours. So, therefore the fitting example of this type of alignment is alignment of side slope canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "A curve in channel results in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) silting on inside (convex side) and scouring on outside (concave side)",
            "b) scouring on inside (convex side) and scouring on outside (concave side)",
            "c) both silting and scouring on inside",
            "d) both silting and scouring on outside"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a channel is aligned the proposed curve should be as gentle as possible. It leads to silting on the convex side and scouring on the concave side due to the disturbance of flow caused by curves. Stone pitching is sometimes proposed to avoid erosion and scouring."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "If the discharging capacity of the channel is less than 0.5 cumecs then, the minimum recommended value for curve radius is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 m",
            "b) 100 m",
            "c) 300 m",
            "d) 600 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the discharge is more, the curve should be gentler and should have more radius. When the capacity is less than 0.5 cumecs, the minimum recommended curve radius is 100m. If the discharge lies in the range 0.5-3 cumecs, the value is 150m."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "What is the Annual Intensity of irrigation (AII)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross Irrigated Area/Cultivable Command Area",
            "b) Cultivable Command Area/Gross Irrigated Area",
            "c) Net Irrigated Area/Cultivable Command Area",
            "d) Cultivable Command Area/Net Irrigated Area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The G.C.A includes the cultivated as well as an uncultivated area like ponds, residential areas, roads, etc. An irrigation canal lies in the area between the two drainages and can economically irrigate it. Thus, the drainages fix the boundary of the gross command of a canal system and it becomes uneconomical to use the system across the two drainages i.e boundaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "What is Gross Cropped Area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Net irrigated area + Area irrigated more than once during the same year",
            "b) Net cropped area + Area sown more than once during the same year",
            "c) Net irrigated area + Net cropped area",
            "d) Total area irrigated once a year + area irrigated more than once in that year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The AII is the sum total of intensities of irrigation of all the seasons of the year. IT can also be defined as the percentage of CCA which may be irrigated annually. It is thus obtained by dividing the gross irrigated area by the CCA."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The ratio of the actual operating period of a distributary to the crop period is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) capacity factor",
            "b) time factor",
            "c) full supply coefficient",
            "d) nominal duty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sometimes two crops in two seasons are grown during a particular year on the same area. Hence this area will be sown more than once during that year. When this area is added to the area which is sown only once then the value obtained is Gross Cropped Area."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The number of hectares irrigable per cumec of the canal capacity at its head is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nominal duty",
            "b) duty on capacity",
            "c) design full supply discharge",
            "d) capacity factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: No distributary is allowed to operate on all the days during any crop season to check for the dangers of over-irrigation leading to waterlogging and salinity. This ratio of actual operating period of a distributary to the crop period is called time factor. It is useful in computing the design capacity of a distributary."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "The Gross Command Area for a distributary is 8000 hectares 80% of which is culturable irrigable. The intensity of irrigation for Rabi season is 50% and the average duty at the head of the distributary is 2000 hectares/cumec. Determine the discharge required at the head of the distributary.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.33 cumec",
            "b) 1.60 cumec",
            "c) 1.40 cumec",
            "d) 1.44 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full supply coefficient is also called duty on capacity. It is the design duty at the head of the canal. It is obtained by dividing the area estimated to be irrigated during the base period with the design full supply discharge at the head of the canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The CCA of a water course is 1500 hectares. The intensity of sugarcane and wheat crops is 20% and 40% respectively. The duties for the crops at the head of the watercourse are 730 hectares/cumec and 1600 hectares/cumec respectively. Calculate the design discharge at the outlet assuming a time factor equal to 0.8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.55 cumec",
            "b) 1.0 cumec",
            "c) 0.72 cumec",
            "d) 0.92 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water requirement during Rabi season reduces to about 2/3rd times the full supply, the capacity factor usually varies from 0.60 to 0.70 for rabi season. The cropped area is increased in order to improve this factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The transplantation of rice takes 18 days and the total depth of water required by the crop is 60 cm on the field. During this transplantation period, rain starts falling and about 10 cm of rain is being utilized to fulfill the rice demand. Find the duty of irrigation water required for rice assuming 25% losses of water in watercourses.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 233.28 hectares/cumec",
            "b) 240 hectares/cumec",
            "c) 230 hectares/cumec",
            "d) 244.44 hectares/cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cultivable Command Area CCA = 8000 x 80/100 = 6400 hectares\nThe area to be irrigated = CCA x Intensity of irrigation = 6400 x 50/100 = 3200 hectares\nThe water required at the head of the distributary = 3200/2000 = 1.6 cumec."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Loss of canal discharge occurs mainly due to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seepage and Percolation",
            "b) Percolation and Absorption",
            "c) Seepage and Evaporation",
            "d) Seepage and Absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Seepage and Evaporation are the two main reasons for loss of canal discharge. Out of these, seepage loss is most significant in the initial stages (about 40%). Evaporation loss may range from 2 to 3% of the total canal discharge."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor do not affect seepage loss?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Underground water-table condition",
            "b) The porosity of the soil",
            "c) Physical properties of the canal water",
            "d) Prevailing wind velocity in the region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The loss due to seepage is the most significant so far as irrigation loss from canals is considered. The porosity of the soil, underground water-table condition, condition of the canal system, and physical properties of the canal water are all factors affecting seepage loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "In which of the following phenomenon there is a continuous direct flow between the canal and the underground water table?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorption",
            "b) Seepage",
            "c) Percolation",
            "d) Both Absorption and Percolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the ground water-table is nearer to the natural surface, the water which has entered the subsoil may join the saturation zone or underground reservoir to maintain a continuous direct flow. Due to the difference of level, the water directly flows from the canal to the underground reservoir through the soil pores."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor have no influence on evaporation loss?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The temperature of the region",
            "b) Prevailing wind velocity in the region",
            "c) Area of water surface exposed to the atmosphere",
            "d) The porosity of the soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Evaporation loss is not that significant and may range from 2-3% of the total canal discharge. The rate of loss depends mainly on temperature and humidity of the region, prevailing wind velocity and the area of water surface exposed to the atmosphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "According to Etcheverry and Harding, the range of conveyance loss is highest in which soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandy Loam",
            "b) Loose sandy soil",
            "c) Clay Loam",
            "d) Rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The soil which is in immediate contact with the channel section forms a bulb of saturated soil. The soil layer below the saturated bulb is partially saturated. Thus the extent of saturation goes on decreasing from the ground level and a zone of unsaturation exists between them."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following empirical formula is used in Punjab for calculating channel losses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q’ = 1.9 Q1/6",
            "b) Q’ = 1/200 x (B+D)2/3",
            "c) Q’ = 1.9 Q",
            "d) Q’ = 1/200 x (B-D)2/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of water lost in conveyance for loose sandy soil is 5.18 to 6.10.\nFor Sandy loam = 3.66 to 5.18\nFor Clay loam = 1.83 to 3.66\nFor rocks = about 0.9."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Inflow and Outflow method is generally used to measure ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transpiration loss",
            "b) seepage loss",
            "c) evaporation loss",
            "d) percolation loss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for channel losses used in Punjab and Haryana states is Q’ = 1.9 Q1/6.\nWhere Q’ = Losses in cumecs per million sq.m of the wetted perimeter, Q = Discharge in cumecs.\nThe formula is used in U.P is; Q’ = 1/200 x (B + D)2/3 where B is the bed width of channel and D is the depth of water in the channel in meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The seepage loss is very high in black cotton soils and heavy clay as compared to sandy porous soil",
            "b) The seepage through a new canal is more than from a silted canal",
            "c) The more the silt, the lesser are the losses",
            "d) The more the velocity, the lesser will be the losses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Seepage loss is generally measured by Inflow and Outflow method. Regular and simultaneous discharge measurement is done at the entrance and end of the selected reach. Same gauge and discharge are maintained at the entrance during the period of observations. The difference between the inflow and outflow over the reach gives the quantity of water lost."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which soil has the least range of conveyance loss according to Etcheverry and Harding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandy Loam",
            "b) Clay Loam",
            "c) Loose sandy soil",
            "d) Impervious clay loam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The seepage losses depend upon all these factors. The seepage loss is very high in sandy or porous soil as compared to black cotton soil or clays. The sandy soil has high permeability so the soil structure allows more water to penetrate and hence there is more seepage."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The quantity of water that can be diverted from the river into the main canal has no dependency on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The water available in the river",
            "b) The capacity of the main canal",
            "c) Water demand of the branch canals",
            "d) The capacity of the branch canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This method of distribution of available water into various canals is called canal regulation and the flow from the main canal is followed by the branch canals and then to the distributaries. The flow distribution depends on the demand for water on various canals."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of the following combination is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roster – Indication of allotted supplies to different channels",
            "b) Flexible regulation – Allocation of supplies with anticipated demand",
            "c) Head regulator – Regulation of discharge in the canal",
            "d) Chak – Command area of an inlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This alternative is generally not preferred as it causes siltation, weed growth, seepage, and water-logging. To compensate for these disadvantages and provide time for sufficient inspections and repairs of the channels, distributaries are made to run turn by turn with full supplies."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristics is wrong about extensive irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The irrigation extends to a large area with the lowest available supply",
            "b) Agricultural production and protection against famine will be at optimum levels",
            "c) The crop production will be minimal per unit of available water",
            "d) It creates a perpetual scarcity of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chak is the command area of an outlet. It is a function of operating characteristics of the system, peak design requirement of an outlet and field application rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What are the categories of the entire water conveyance system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The primary distribution system and secondary distribution system",
            "b) The primary distribution system, the secondary distribution system, and Water allowance",
            "c) The primary distribution system, secondary distribution system, and tertiary distribution system",
            "d) The primary distribution system, secondary distribution system, tertiary distribution system, and Water allowance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In spite of the fact that this method requires good control and monitoring on the release of water, it is usually adopted in India. The production would be the maximum per unit of available water, though it may not be optimum of the land covered."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The primary and secondary distribution system is fully controlled by the State Irrigation Department",
            "b) The tertiary system is managed by farmers",
            "c) The distribution of water managed by farmers is done on a seven-day rotation basis",
            "d) Water allowance is not a compromise between the likely demand and the supply for a given project"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An integral management system designed to deliver a constant flow of water among irrigators along a tertiary canal is called Warabandi. This entire water conveyance system is divided into Primary, Secondary and Tertiary distribution system. Water allowance is just a certain rate of flow which is allocated to each unit of C.C.A in this warabandi system."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is the correct formula for Flow Time in an hour for an individual farmer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (FT for the unit area) x (area of farmer’s fields) + (his bharai – his jharai)",
            "b) (FT for the unit area) x (area of farmer’s fields) – (his bharai – his jharai)",
            "c) FT for the unit area + (his bharai – his jharai)",
            "d) FT for the unit area – (his bharai – his jharai)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of water allowance decides the carrying capacities of the water-courses and the distributaries. Hence, it is generally a compromise between the likely demand and the supply for a given project."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the Flow Time for the unit area in hours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 168 – (total Bharai – total Jharai) / Total area to be irrigated by the water-course",
            "b) 168 + (total Bharai – total Jharai) / Total area to be irrigated by the water-course",
            "c) 168 – (total Bharai – total Jharai)",
            "d) 168 + (total Bharai – total Jharai)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula for the flow time an hour for an individual farmer after the allowance of Bharai and Jharai timings is –\n(FT for the unit area) x (area of farmer’s fields) + (his bharai – his jharai)\nBharai is generally zero in case of the tail (i.e. the last farmer) and Jharai is usually zero for all except for the tail."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is the most important point to be considered while fixing the canal capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keenest Demand",
            "b) Average Demand",
            "c) Water Demand",
            "d) Demand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Suppose take wheat crop for example, let us say it requires a 60 cm of water in a total period of about 240 days (for a given area of field) thus giving an average outlet factor of 3456 hectares/cumec. But the kor depth of wheat is 14 cm in about 4 weeks which gives an outlet of 1728 hectares/cumec. Therefore it is clear that for a given area (A) outlet factor of 1728 is very much more than 3456. Hence kor demand should be given importance while designing irrigation canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Let us consider in a given area the plantation of a certain crop takes 20 days, and the total water depth required by this crop is 80 cm on the field. Find the duty of irrigation water required for the crop during this period. (a) Assuming 20% losses of water in the water courses, find duty at the head of the course. (b) Find the duty of the water at the head of the distributary, assuming 10% losses from the distributary head.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 182.9 hectares/cumec, 194.4 hectares/cumec",
            "b) 172.8 hectares/cumec, 185.4 hectares/cumec",
            "c) 172.8 hectares/cumec, 194.4 hectares/cumec",
            "d) 185.6 hectares/cumec, 184.6 hectares/cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While fixing the capacity of a canal the main important that should be kept in mind is the keenest demand, but not the average demand. For instance, let rice require 160 cm of water during 320 days which gives an outlet factor of 1728 hectares/cumec. (i.e D = 864B/∆ = 864 x 320 / 160 = 1728)."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "A pump was installed in a field to supply water to the crops. The duty for this crop is 432 hectares/cumec on the field and the efficiency of pump is 50%. The sown area of the field is 5 hectares. Determine the maximum output required (H.P) of the pump, if the highest water level is 4 meters below the highest portion of the field. Assume negligible field channel losses.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.77H.P",
            "b) 0.85H.P",
            "c) 0.80H.P",
            "d) 0.31H.P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Total depth of water needed = 80 cm\nPeriod for which water is needed = 20 days\nDuty of irrigation water = (864B/d) = (864 x 20 / 80) = 216 hectares/cumec\n(a) Given 20% losses in the watercourse\n= 216 x 0.8 = 172.8 hectares/cumec\n(b) Given 10% losses in the head of the distributary\n= 216 x 0.9 = 194.4 hectares/cumec."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "At a certain place, the transplantation of a crop takes 15 days, and the total depth of water required by the crop is 90 cm on the field. During the plantation rain falls and about 20 cm is utilised to fulfil the demand. Now determine the duty of irrigation water required during the plantation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 185.14hectares/cumec",
            "b) 186.25hectares/cumec",
            "c) 187.45hectares/cumec",
            "d) 184.89hectares/cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Area of field to be irrigated = 5 hectares\nDuty of water for crop = 432 hectares/cumec\nDischarge required for the crop is = (5 / 432) = 1/86.4 cumec\nVolume of water lifted per second = 1 / 86.4 cumec\nTherefore, weight of water lifted per second = (1 / 86.4) x 9.81 = 0.1135 KN/sec\n(unit wt. of water = 9.81 KN/m3)\nMaximum static lift of pump = 4 metres\nWork done by the pump in lifting water = 0.1135 x 4 = 0.454 KWatt\nThe input of the pump = (0.454 / 0.735) = 0.62\n(1 metric H.P = 0.735 KWatt)\nOutput H.P of the pump = (input/η) = (0.62 / 0.5) = 0.31 H.P."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Let us take the gross commanded area of a watercourse is 2000 hectares, 80% of which is culturable irrigable. Intensities of sugarcane and paddy are 30% and 50%. The duties of the crops at the head of the watercourse are 850 hectares/cumec and 1900 hectares/cumec. Find the discharge required at the head of the watercourse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.98 cumec",
            "b) 0.97 cumec",
            "c) 0.9 cumec",
            "d) 0.986 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Total depth of water required = 90 cm\nUseful rainfall = 20 cm\nExtra water depth needed after useful rainfall = 90 – 20 = 70 cm\nPeriod for which water is needed = 15 days\nDuty of irrigated water (∆) = (864B/d) = (864 x 15 / 70) = 185.14 hectares/cumec."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "By how much percentage canal capacity is increased to meet peak demands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 to 35%",
            "b) 20 to 25%",
            "c) 15 to 20%",
            "d) 20 to 30%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Given G.C.A = 2000 hectares\nNow the C.C.A = 2000 x 80 / 100 = 1600 hectares\nIntensity of irrigation for sugarcane = 30%\nArea to be irrigated under sugarcane = 1600 x 30/100 = 480 hectares\nIntensity of irrigation of paddy = 50%\nArea to be irrigated under paddy = 1600 x 50/100 = 800 hectares\nDuty of sugarcane = 850 hectares/cumec\nDuty of paddy = 1900 hectares/cumec\nDischarge for sugarcane = 480 / 850 = 0.565 cumec\nDischarge for paddy = 800 / 1900 = 0.421 cumec\nNow the total canal capacity at the head of watercourse is = 0.565 + 0.421 = 0.986 cumec."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Suppose the culturable commanded for a distributary is 8000 hectares, and the intensity of irrigation for Kharif season is 60% and that of rabi season is 30%. The average duty at the head of a distributary is 4000 hectares/cumec for Kharif season and for Rabi season it is 1800 hectares/cumec, find out discharge required at the head of the distributary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.35 cumec",
            "b) 1.32 cumec",
            "c) 1.33 cumec",
            "d) 1.3 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water depth will be multiplied by crop area which is required in this interval, so as to give the volume of water required in this interval. By dividing the volume by interval, we can find out the discharge needed for each interval. The summation of this will give the discharge required for all the crops in each interval. The canal can then be designed for the maximum of these values."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Determine the discharge required at the head of the distributary in a canal where Kharif area to be irrigated is 2400 hectares and Rabi area to be irrigated is 1800 hectares, for fulfilling maximum crop requirement. Assume suitable values for kor depth and kor period.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.08 cumec",
            "b) 2 cumec",
            "c) 2.1 cumec",
            "d) 2.2 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to be more precise, the intervals are kept as small as possible. Monthly water requirements studies are conducted to provide a sufficient quantity of water for irrigation. So, the canal capacity is increased by 20 to 25% to meet the peak demands in a month."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "What are the types of sediment load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bedload and Suspended load",
            "b) Bedload and Dissolved load",
            "c) Bedload, Dissolved load and Suspended load",
            "d) Suspended load and Dissolved load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bedload is that portion of sediment load that is transported along the bed by sliding, rolling or hopping. The dissolved load is the one that is chemically carried by water in the form of ions. When the material is maintained in suspension due to the turbulence of flowing water, it is called a suspended load."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "On increasing velocity beyond the threshold stage of motion, the bed develops ____________ shape.",
        "Options": [
            "a) dunes with ripples",
            "b) saw-tooth ripples",
            "c) anti-dunes",
            "d) flat surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to unusual high velocity in the flooded streams, there is heavy sediment transportation and deposition downstream. The increased suspended load may be visible giving the stream a muddy color."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ripples do not occur if the size of the bed particles is coarser than 0.6 mm",
            "b) Dunes are much larger in length and height than ripples",
            "c) Crests of both ripples and dunes extend across the entire width of the stream",
            "d) Ripples are less rounded than Dunes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depending upon the discharge or the velocity of the water, the channel bed may be distorted into various shapes by the moving water. Ripples are superimposed on the bed when they first appear. At high velocities, ripples disappear and only dunes are left."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "When the velocity is further increased beyond the stage where sand waves are formed in association with the surface waves, the waves are then called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dunes",
            "b) ripples",
            "c) flat surface",
            "d) antidunes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A channel bed made of fine sand less than 2 mm diameter develops the shape of ripples of saw-tooth type when the velocity is increased beyond the threshold stage of motion. If the velocity is increased further, large periodic irregularities appear that are called dunes."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "On which factor does the movement of bedload depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity of Flow",
            "b) Type of Flow",
            "c) Depth of Flow",
            "d) Width of the River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bedload is a sediment load, and it moves by the actions like rolling, sliding and hopping which in turn depend on the velocity of flow. The bed load remains in the bottom layers of the flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "What type of force is completely responsible for the bedload movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forces of Turbulence",
            "b) Drag Force",
            "c) Capillary Force",
            "d) Gravity Force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes bed load is estimated to be in between 3 to 25% of the total suspended load, depending upon the reflexes of the sediment to forces from the sectors like physical, chemical, and biological. In between this percentage we commonly take bed load is 10% of total suspended load."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which type of force is needed for suspension of suspended load in flowing water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capillary Force",
            "b) Drag Force",
            "c) Forces of Turbulence",
            "d) Gravity Force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally we know that bedload is a type of sediment which moves adjacent to the bed of the channel. Shear stress (τo) is responsible for this movement of bedload along the bed if the channel, which is developed by the flowing water along the channel bed. This shear force is called drag force or tractive force."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Given that the bed slope of a channel is 1 in 2000 and the discharge is 60 cumecs. The depth of the channel is fixed and is given as 2 m. The tractive force needed for the movement of bedload is? Take critical velocity ratio as 1.1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.89 N/m3",
            "b) 8.87 N/m3",
            "c) 8.85 N/m3",
            "d) 8.83 N/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Suspended load is a sediment load, but remains in suspension in the flowing water of the channel. The forces which cause this suspension are the forces of turbulence, which are generated by the flow of the channel itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What cause is prime responsible for the heavy movement of water from main canal to branch canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Existence of Favorable Gradient",
            "b) Velocity of Flow",
            "c) Type of Flow",
            "d) Depth of the Canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to transport the bed load the tractive force (τo) should exceed the critical tractive force (τc), therefore the rate of movement of bedload becomes a function of (τo – τc). But, as soon as the sediment starts moving it is opposed by the ripples generated by the channel bed, and to overcome these ripples a large part of tractive force is lost and cannot be used again. So, this part of the force does not have any part in transporting the bed load."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Water in which condition or state carry a maximum amount of sediment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform State",
            "b) Vapor State",
            "c) Floods",
            "d) Ice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Critical velocity (Vo) = 0.55my0.64\n= 0.55 x 1.1 x (2)0.64\n= 0.943 m/sec\nArea = Q / Vo = 60 / 0.943 = 63.63 m2 (Given Q = 60 cumecs)\nA = y (b + y (1/2)) (y = depth, b = base width)\n63.63 = 2(b + 1) (for side slope as (1/2:1/2H:V))\nb = 30.82 m\nPerimeter (P) = b + √5y = 30.82 + 2 x √5\nP = 35.3 m\nR = A/P = 63.63 / 35.3 = 1.8 m (R = hydraulic mean depth)\nNow, tractive force (τo) = γwRS = 9.81 x 103 x 1.8 x (1/2000) (γw = 9.81 x 103 N/m3)\n= 8.83 N/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "What minimum value of shear stress is needed to move the sediment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Critical Velocity Ratio",
            "b) Critical Shear Stress",
            "c) Critical Velocity",
            "d) Drag Force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a branch canal is connected to the main canal, the branch canal starts taking water discharge which reduces the discharge in main canal thereby reduces sediment load capacity. This leads to the deposition of sediment load which further diverts the flow towards branch canal. This process continues till all the water in the main canal gets discharged into branch canal. The prime cause of this phenomenon is due to the existence of favorable gradient in the branch canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Design a channel carrying a 30 cumecs. The median grain diameter is taken as 0.5 mm. The bedload concentration is 60 p.p.m by weight. Use Lacey’s Regime perimeter and Meyer-peter’s formulas.",
        "Options": [
            "a) B = 26 m, S = 1/5600, y = 1.25 m",
            "b) B = 22 m, S = 1/5800, y = 1.55 m",
            "c) B = 24 m, S = 1/5500, y = 1.45 m",
            "d) B = 25 m, S = 1/5700, y = 1.35 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Einstein’s equation (qb/q≼qS2/d3/2), the sediment carrying capacity of the channel depends upon the discharge per unit width. Therefore, this gives that floods can carry more amount of sediment than any other state of water because the discharge per unit width of channel is maximum in case of floods. Most of the annual sediment load is done by floods."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The design and execution of flood control scheme is chiefly governed by the peak flood levels",
            "b) Silting of reservoirs and rivers is an important aspect of sediment control",
            "c) The storage capacity of the reservoir is reduced by its silting",
            "d) Natural rivers used for navigation rarely gets silted up posing no cost issues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The scouring and silting may create sharp and irregular curves. This increases the resistance to flow of the channel and thereby, raising the flood levels for the particular discharge."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "BEAST Stands for _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benthic Environmental Assessment Sediment Tool",
            "b) Benthic Environmental Achievement Sediment Tool",
            "c) Benthic Environment Achievement Sediment Task",
            "d) Benthic Erosion Assessment Sediment tool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This causes large scale scouring and siltation of irrigation canals thereby increasing their maintenance. A poorly designed artificial channel gets silted so badly that they sometimes become inoperable and leads to huge economic loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "The basic mechanism behind the phenomenon of sediment transport is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) drag force opposite to the direction of the flow",
            "b) drag force in the direction of the flow",
            "c) free motion of the sediment particles",
            "d) force exerted by water vertically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coherent means that there is a cohesive force between particles such as in the case of clays. The soil is assumed to be incoherent so that each soil grain is studied individually. Most of our river beds are made up of gravels and sands in which there is no cohesion."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Threshold condition is the one in which a few particles on the bed will just start moving",
            "b) Knowledge of critical velocity helps in designing stable non-scouring channels",
            "c) The critical tractive force approach helps in designing unstable channels in alluviums",
            "d) The knowledge of threshold condition is required for the computation of sediment load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force exerted by water in the direction of flow is the drag force or tractive force. If this force on the bed particles exceeds the force opposing their movement then, the bed particles will start moving to lead to the sediment transport."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "A wide unlined channel carrying silt-free water has a depth of 2.0 m. The maximum slope that can be given to a channel is 1 in 10,000. Calculate the maximum tractive stress permissible on the bed to prevent scouring.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2 kg/m2",
            "b) 1.962 kg/m2",
            "c) 2 kg/m2",
            "d) 1 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shield was the first person to analyze the experimental data on incipient motion condition using the critical tractive force approach. The assumption of the entry of clean and clear water in the channel is used to develop non-scouring highest possible flow velocity at the peak flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The water flows at a depth of 0.6 m in a wide stream having a bed slope of 1 in 2500. The critical tractive stress is 0.53 N/m2. Determine the motion of soil grains and the average shear stress.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.35 N/m2 and soil grains will be stationary",
            "b) 2.35 N/m2 and soil grains is in motion",
            "c) 0.235 N/m2 and soil grains will be stationary",
            "d) 0.235 N/m2 and soil grains is in motion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unit tractive force in channels is uniformly distributed along the wetted perimeter. For the bed of the canal, the average shear stress is equal to the tractive force per unit area. For side slopes of the canal, average shear stress is equal to 0.75 times the tractive force per unit area."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Whose theory was the first to provide semi-theoretical analysis of the problem of incipient condition of bed motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lacey’s theory",
            "b) Kennedy’s theory",
            "c) Shield’s theory",
            "d) Strickler’s equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shield was the first person who designed non-scouring channels by providing semi-theoretical analysis. He defined that the bed particles need a drag force greater than or equal to the resistance offered by the particle for its movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which one is the correct expression for Shield’s entrainment function?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tc / Yw. d. (Gs – 1)",
            "b) Tc.Yw / d. (Gs – 1)",
            "c) Tc / Yw. d",
            "d) Tc .Yw. d / (Gs – 1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shield introduced a dimensionless number which is called entrainment function (Fs) which is a function of Reynold’s number at a critical stage of bed movement in alluviums. It is based on the experimental work done by the Shield.\nMathematically, Fs = Tc / Yw. d. (Gs – 1)."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "For the design of non-scouring channels in coarse alluviums, the shield’s entrainment function should be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fs > 0.056",
            "b) Fs < 0.056",
            "c) Fs = 0.056",
            "d) Fs = 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Shield for coarse alluvium, Fs = 0.056 (d > 6 mm). When the particle Reynold’s number is more than 400, the application of the curve plotted by Shield between Reynold’s number and entrainment function becomes simpler. Also, the value of the entrainment function becomes constant and equal to 0.056."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is the minimum size of the bed material that will remain at rest in a channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) d > or = 11 R.S",
            "b) d < or = 11 R.S",
            "c) d = 11 R.S",
            "d) d > 11 R.S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strickler’s formula is not used for moveable boundary channels as it does not account for the roughness due to undulations in the bed channel. It is used to calculate Manning’s rugosity coefficient and is valid for rivers with the bed of coarse material i.e. rigid boundary channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "What is the limitation of the Shield’s expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be used when the diameter of a particle (d) is < 6mm and Reynold’s number > 400",
            "b) It can be used only when Reynold’s number > 400",
            "c) It can be used only when the diameter of the particle is < 6 mm",
            "d) It can be used when the diameter of a particle is > 6mm and Reynold’s number > 400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For no movement of the sediment particles, Tc  > or = T0.\n0.056. Yw. d. (Gs – 1) >or = Yw. R. S where, for sand of gravel Gs = 2.65\nd >or = 10.82 R.S\nd >or = 11 R.S."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Calculate the Manning’s rugosity coefficient in a coarse alluvium gravel with D-75 size of 5 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.025 m",
            "b) 0.035 m",
            "c) 0.055 m",
            "d) 0.1 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The curve plotted by Shield between Reynold’s number and Entrainment function forms a suitable basis for the design of channels where it is required to prevent bed movement. When the particle size exceeds 6 mm such as for coarse alluvium soils, the particle Reynold’s number has found to be more than 400 representing roughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The manning’s coefficient for a lined trapezoidal channel with a bed slope of 1 in 4000 is 0.014 and it will be 0.028 if the channel is unlined. The area in the case of the lined section is 19.04 m2 and for the unlined section is 29.09 m2. What percentage of earthwork is saved in a lined section relative to an unlined section, when a hydraulically efficient section is used in both the cases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24.44 %",
            "b) 34.55%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 37.66%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The strickler’s formula is n = d1/6/24 where d = 0.05 m.\nn = 0.051/6/24 = 0.025 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Calculate the critical tractive stress if the median diameter of the sand bed is 1.0 mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.53 N/m2",
            "b) 0.61 N/m2",
            "c) 0.73 N/m2",
            "d) 1.61 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The percentage of earthwork saving due to the lining is (A2 – A1)/A2 x 100.\n= (29.09 – 19.04) / 29.09 x 100\n= 34.55%."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Calculate the ratio of the tractive critical stress to the average shear stress if the water flows at a depth of 0.8 m in a wide stream having a bed slope of 1 in 3000. The median diameter of the sand bed is 2 mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.53",
            "b) 1.86",
            "c) 0.86",
            "d) 1.53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given size of the particle is less than 6 mm so; shield’s equation cannot be used. The general relation is given by Mittal and Swamee which gives results within +5% of the values of Shield’s curve for all particle sizes.\nTc = 0.155 + [0.409 d2/(1 + 0.177 d2)0.5] \n= 0.155 + [0.409 x 12/(1 + 0.177 x 12)0.5] = 0.53 N/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Determine the shear stress required to move the single grain on the side slopes, if the critical shear stress required moving the similar grain on the horizontal bed is 2.91 N/m2. Consider the angle of the side slope with the horizontal as 30° and the angle of repose of soil as 37°.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.61 N/m2",
            "b) 2.61 N/m2",
            "c) 2.91 N/m2",
            "d) 1.00 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical tractive stress is given by (d < 6 mm) –\nTc = 0.155 + [0.409 d2/(1 + 0.177 d2)0.5] \n= 0.155 + [0.409 x 22/(1 + 0.177 x 22)0.5] = 1.40 N/m2.\nThe average shear stress = Yw. RS = 9.81 x 0.8 x 1/3000 = 2.616 N/m2\nRatio = 1.40/2.616 = 0.53."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "On what condition does the resistance equations of Chezy’s formula and manning’s formula are applicable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) τo",
            "b) τc",
            "c) τo < τc",
            "d) τo > τc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The direct accurate mathematical solution based on the resistance equations given by Chezy’s formula and Manning’s formula is very complicated in Indian based alluvial channels. So, therefore hypothetical theories given by Kennedy and Lacey are used, as these theories are based on experiments and experience from existing channels over the years.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "What is the problem in India for artificial channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formation of Depressions",
            "b) Formation of Alluvial Soil",
            "c) Untimely Rains",
            "d) Improper Usage of Channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average shear stress (τo) which is acting on the boundary of an alluvial channel should be less than the critical shear stress (τc), then the channel shape remains unchanged, and hence the channel is considered having rigid boundary. So based on this condition Chezy’s formula and Manning’s formula can be applied.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "What is the effect of scouring in channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Channel Section gets reduced",
            "b) Reduces Discharge Capacity",
            "c) Improper Working of Channel",
            "d) Breaching of Canal Banks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In prehistoric periods, the area starting from the Himalayas to Vindhya mountains is used to in the form of depressions with water flowing over it. But over the ages these depressions got filled with fine silt particles, thereby forming into alluvial soil. So the rivers present in this area of north India flow in alluvial soil carrying silt. So, therefore the artificial channels carrying water from such rivers thus have to carry silt sediment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "What is the effect of silting in channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduced Discharge Capacity of Channel",
            "b) Causes Loss of Command",
            "c) Breaching of Canal Banks",
            "d) Failure of Irrigation Structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given velocity of flow of a channel and certain depth can carry in suspension, some amount of silt. But if the velocity is more and depth is not fully charged with silt it will erode the bed and sides of the channel. And if the velocity is less, the silt cannot be carried in suspension by the flow, hence it is dropped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which type of state is achievable in artificial channels but not in rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbulent State",
            "b) Laminar State",
            "c) Regime State",
            "d) Uniform State"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Scouring is not a rare phenomenon in channels. It is very understandable and can be controlled or avoided by proper designing of channels. Scouring causes loss of command in channels and lowers full supply level of channel. This causes breaching of canal banks and in turn causes failure of foundations of irrigation structures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "On what basis for designing the regime state is obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silt and Velocity of Flow",
            "b) Silt",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Depth of Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The silting problem is very common in any kind of artificial channels, or we can say there is no natural or artificial channel with the silting problem. Silting interferes with the proper working of a channel, as it causes reduction in the channel section due to siltation, which thereby reduces the discharge capacity of the channel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "What vital factor is not considered in regime theories during the design of regime channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity of Flow in the Channel",
            "b) Type of Flow in the Channel",
            "c) Quantity of Sediment Entering a channel",
            "d) Area in which the Channel flows"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The channel is said to be in regime state, when the flow of the channel is such that silting and scouring effects need no special attention. This state is not easy to achieve in rivers but can be achieved in artificial channels, by proper designing of the channels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "According to Kennedy the silting action in channels is due to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of Eddies",
            "b) Slope of the Bed",
            "c) Area of Channel",
            "d) Type of Flow in the Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basis for designing a channel to be in regime state, whatever the amount of silt has entered the channel has to be kept in suspension, so that it does not settle down and get deposited in the channel anywhere. And the velocity of the flow in the channel should be such that it does not produce silt by eroding the banks and beds of the channel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Based on his research what factor is given by Kennedy for free silting and scouring actions in a channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Critical Velocity (Vo)",
            "b) Bed Slope of Channel",
            "c) Hydraulic Mean Depth",
            "d) Rugosity Coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quantity of sediment load entering the channel from the head works plays an important role in designing the regime channels, as it controls the cross-section and shape of the regime channel. Moreover the design of regime channel is not complete until provisions are made for the effects produced by the actual quantity of sediment load present in the channel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Given to design the irrigation channel to carry 80 cumecs of discharge. The channel slope is 1 in 3000. The critical velocity ratio is 1.3. Take rugosity coefficient as 0.021.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth = 3 m, Base width = 15 m",
            "b) Depth = 3.5 m, Base width = 15.5 m",
            "c) Depth = 3.3 m, Base width = 15.2 m",
            "d) Depth = 3.2 m, Base width = 15.1 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the observations of his research, he concluded that the silting action in channels is due to the generation of eddies, rising to the surface. These eddies are in turn generated by the friction of flowing water with the channel surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Design a regime channel for a discharge of 90 cumecs and silt factor is 1.3 use Lacey’s Theory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth = 2.2 m, Base width = 40.5 m, Slope = 1/4670",
            "b) Depth = 2.12 m, Base width = 40.42 m, Slope = 1/4675",
            "c) Depth = 2.135 m, Base width = 40.3 m, Slope = 1/4676",
            "d) Depth = 2.123 m, Base width = 40.1 m, Slope = 1/4672"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eddies affect the formation of silting action in a channel brief investigation shows that the vertical component of these eddies try to move sediment up and the weight of sediment tries to bring it down, thus keeping the sediment in suspension. So, silting is avoided if sufficient velocity is generated to form eddies and keep the sediment in suspension. This velocity is called critical velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "According to Lacey what factor is needed to have a true regime in an artificial channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow is Uniform",
            "b) Critical Velocity = Actual Velocity",
            "c) No Silting or Scouring Action",
            "d) Lining of the Channel Bed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Given Q = 80 cumecs, S = 1/3000, m = 1.3, n = 0.021\nCritical velocity (Vo) = 0.55my0.64 (y = depth of the channel)\n= 0.55 x 1.3 x (2)0.64\n= 1.114 m/sec\nArea (A) = Q/Vo = 80 / 1.114 = 71.8 m2\nNow assume side slope as (1/2): 1(1/2H: V)\nNow, A = y (b + y x 1/2)\n71.8 = 2(b + 2 x 1/2)\n71.8 = 2(b + 1)\nb = 34.9 m\nPerimeter (P) = b + 2 x √5/2y\n= 34.9 + 4.47\n= 39.37 m\nNow R = A/P = 71.8 / 39.37 = 1.82 m\nV = ((1/n + (23 + 0.00155/s)) / (1 + (23 + 0.00155/s)n/\\(\\sqrt{RR}\\)))\\(\\sqrt{RSRS}\\) \nV = 0.78 m/sec\nNow calculating for critical velocity,\nVo = 0.55 x 1.3 x y0.64\n= 0.715 x y0.64\nNow assume y = 2.5 m\nVo = 0.715 x (2.5)0.64 = 1.28 m/sec\nA = 80 / 1.28 = 62.5 m2\n62.5 = 2.5 (b + 1/2(2.5))\nb = 23.75 m\nP = 23.75 + 2 x √5/2(2.5) = 29.35 m\nR = A/P = 2.13\n√R  = 1.46\nV = 75.27/1.4 x (1.46/54.8) = 1.432 m/sec\nV > V0\nNow assume y = 3.2 m\nVo = 0.715 x (3.2)0.64 = 1.51 m/sec\nA = 80 / 1.5 = 53.33 m2\n53.33 = 3.2 (b + 1.6)\nb= 15.1 m\nP = 15.1 + √5(3.2)\nP = 22.2 m\nR = A/P = 53.33/22.2 = 2.4 m\n√R = 1.56\nV = (75.27/1.4) x (1.56/54.8)\n= 1.53 m/sec\nTherefore V = Vo\nHence use the depth equal to 3.2 m and base width 15.1 m with slope 1/2:1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Whose equation was the first on the rate of bed load transport?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DU-Bois empirical formula",
            "b) Shield’s formula",
            "c) Meyer-Peter’s formula",
            "d) Einstein’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first equation was proposed by DU-Bois on the rate of bedload transport. He assumed that the bed load transportation rate was proportional to the excess of existing tractive force over the critical value required to initiate the movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about Einstein’s theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He put forward a mathematical approach to the problem of bed load transport",
            "b) He further postulated probability of the grain being dislodged is directly proportional to the lift force which the flow can exert on the grain",
            "c) He introduced a factor called Einstein’s bedload function",
            "d) He gave a curve graph which can be used to compute the bedload transport rate of a given channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: He put forward a semi-theoretical approach to the problem of bed load transport. It was assumed that every particle travels a certain minimum distance before coming to rest after it is dislodged from the bed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about sediment load phenomenon and its measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The material is kept in suspension by the turbulence or by the generation of eddies",
            "b) In laminar flow, the shear stress is caused due to the difference of the velocities at the top and the bottom",
            "c) In turbulent flow, momentum transfer is not very significant",
            "d) Due to the formation of eddies, the sediment transfer from high concentration  regions to the low concentration regions takes place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sediment carrying capacity will reduce if the width of the river increases as the discharge per unit width will decrease. The deposition of the sediment will start which will increase the bed slope.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "In a wide stream, a suspended load sample taken at a height of 0.30 m from the bed. The stream is 5.0 m deep and has a bed slope of 1/4000. The bed material can be of uniform size. Estimate the shear friction velocity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.111 m/s",
            "b) 0.211 m/s",
            "c) 0.311 m/s",
            "d) 0.711 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In turbulent flow, momentum transfer or mass exchange takes place due to the jumping of particles from higher velocity region to lower velocity region. Due to this transfer of momentum between two adjacent fluid layers, effective shear stress is caused at the interface between the layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "For the usual turbulent flow, calculate the critical shear stress if the mean diameter of the grain particle of bed material is 0.3 mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.300 N/m2",
            "b) 0.106 N/m2",
            "c) 0.206 N/m2",
            "d) 0.116 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sediment moves only on the top layers of the bed. Hence, the lower limit can be considered as equal to the thickness of the bed layer which is approximately equal to 2d and the upper limit as the total water depth. The sediment concentration at this depth can be considered equal to the concentration of bed load.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Calculate the corresponding hydraulic mean depth that would exist in the channel if the bed was unrippled. The rugosity coefficient in an unrippled channel is 0.015 and the rugosity coefficient actually observed by experiments on the rippled bed of channel is 0.020. Consider the value of hydraulic mean depth of the channel as 1.5 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 m",
            "b) 2.5 m",
            "c) 0.97 m",
            "d) 0.77 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: V*= Shear friction velocity = (S0/Dw)1/2 where Dw is the density of water and So (Yw.R.S) is shear stress at the bottom.\nV* = [(Dw. g.R.S)/Dw]1/2 = (g.R.S)1/2\nV* = (9.81 x 5 x 1/4000)1/2 = 0.111 m/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Calculate the quantity of bed load transport by using Meyer and Peter formula if the effective tractive force that causes bed load transportation is 2.5 N/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.04 N/m/second",
            "b) 1.5 N/m/second",
            "c) 2.5 N/m/second",
            "d) 0.476 N/m/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For usual turbulent flow, the value of critical shear stress is given by 0.687d where d is the arithmetic average diameter of sediment in mm.\nS0 = 0.687 d\nS0 = 0.687 x 0.3 = 0.206 N/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Calculate the effective unit tractive force that causes bed load transportation if the unit tractive force produced by the flowing water is 3.20 N/m2. The Manning’s coefficient on an unrippled bed is 0.0108 and the actual observed value of Manning’s coefficient on ripped channels is 0.0222. Take the value of critical shear stress that is required to move the grain particle as 0.5 N/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.58 N/m2",
            "b) 0.222 N/m2",
            "c) 1.08 N/m2",
            "d) 0.58 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula that is used to take into account the effect of bed ripples is-\nR’ = R (n’/n) 3/2 where, R = 1.5 m, n’ = 0.015, and n = 0.020\nR’ = 1.5 x (0.015/0.020)3/2 = 0.97 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What is range of side slopes for a canal in cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 H : 1 V to 1.5 H : 1 V",
            "b) 1.5 H : 1 V to 1.5 H : 1 V",
            "c) 1.5 H : 1 V to 1 H : 1 V",
            "d) 1 H: 0.5 V to 1 H : 1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flatter slopes such as 1 : 1 and 1.5 : 1 are also constructed at the time of execution, but actual capacity of channel is worked out in 1/2 : 1 slope because even if we provide 1 : 1 or 1.5 : 1 slope the silt gets deposited on this slope and gives a new side slope 1/2 : 1. Therefore the actual capacity is calculated using 1/2 :  1 slope.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "With what equation we can calculate the berm width?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (s1 – s2) d1",
            "b) (s2 – s1) d1",
            "c) (s2) d1",
            "d) (s1) d1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The side slopes of a canal are designed such that they are stable, depending upon the type of soil present in canal area. A canal in cutting is provided with steeper slope than a canal in filing, as the stability of soil is more in case of canal in cutting than in canal in filing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "What is the primary purpose of the banks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aesthetic View",
            "b) Inspection Paths",
            "c) Retaining Water",
            "d) Means of Communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Berm is the horizontal distance between the toe of the bank and top edge of the cutting. If s2 : 1 is the slope in filling and s1 : 1 is the slope in cutting, and the initial depth of the berm from the bed of the canal is d1 then width of the berm is (s2 – s1) d1. As d1 varies, the width of the berm also varies. As siltation occurs the formula is (s2:1/2) y (y=over all new depth of the berm).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What type of roads is provided for inspection purposes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Road",
            "b) Dirt Road",
            "c) Service Roads",
            "d) Toll road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The silt which gets deposited is very fine and impervious therefore it acts as a good lining which reduces losses, leakage, breaches etc. This also gives strength to the banks and protects them against erosion and breaches. This deposition also provides scope for future widening of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "What is provided as a measure of safety during driving?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeboard",
            "b) Banks",
            "c) Service Roads",
            "d) Dowlas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main purpose of the banks is to retain water in the canal itself. This retaining action is always needed, in cases of low availability of water or during the period of floods. The other purposes of the banks include a means of communication and inspection paths.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Which structure is provided when the disposition of earth becomes costlier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Borrow pits",
            "b) Spoil Banks",
            "c) Back Berm",
            "d) Freeboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For inspection purposes of the canal, service roads are provided and they even serve as a means of communication in remote areas. Depending upon the size of the canal these roads are provided at a height of 0.4 m to 1 m above the fixed surface level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "What type of structure is provided when earth has to be brought from somewhere else for canal construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeboard",
            "b) Borrow Pits",
            "c) Spoil Banks",
            "d) Berms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A structure of 0.3 m high and 0.3 to 0.6 m wide is provided along the banks, with side slopes of 1.5: 1 to 2: 1. This structure is known as dowlas. They also help in preventing soil erosion during rains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which type of borrow pits are preferred more?",
        "Options": [
            "a) External Borrow Pits",
            "b) Internal Borrow Pits",
            "c) Borrow pits",
            "d) Spoil Banks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The disposition of earth becomes costlier when the earthwork in excavation exceeds earthwork in filling. To dispose this earth economically, it should be collected on the edge of the bank embankment. The soil is deposited on both banks or only on one bank in the form of heaps. Longitudinal drains are excavated to run along their sides to dispose rain water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "What is the condition for digging of borrow pits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B/2 > b",
            "b) Depth of pit 7 < 1 m",
            "c) Should in the Centre",
            "d) Dig only External Pits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the earthwork in filling exceeds the earthwork in excavation then the earth has to be brought from somewhere else to facilitate the construction of the canal. The pits or the places where the earth has been brought are called borrow pits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a reason which leads to a canal breach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to faulty design and construction of banks",
            "b) Due to leakage or piping",
            "c) Due to the maintenance of service roads",
            "d) Due to intentional cuts made by cultivators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Berms provide a path for inspection. Excessive loss of water due to seepage is checked. It is so because berms are formed of fine silt which makes berms fairly impervious.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a preventive measure for the maintenance of the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strengthening of canal banks",
            "b) Formation of berms by internal silting",
            "c) Provision of Pushta or cover to the saturation line",
            "d) Silt removal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Breaches are the gaps created in the canal banks due to breaking up of the banks. The maintenance of service roads includes removal of grass and small bushes, levelling and surfacing of roads. The slopes if damaged should be repaired to facilitate drainage of roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Internal silting method and external silting method are the methods of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) strengthening of canal banks",
            "b) formation of berms",
            "c) silt removal",
            "d) formation of breaches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Preventive measures are aimed at providing additional stability at various components parts of the canal. Remedial measures are aimed at repairing or removing the causes of trouble like aquatic weed control, silt removal, and maintenance of service roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong about the internal silting method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The extra strength is gained by increasing the section of the banks",
            "b) The additional soil is derived from the natural process of silting internally",
            "c) This method of strengthening the canal is very cheap, simple and efficient",
            "d) To decelerate the silting process low submersible spurs may be constructed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Internal silting method is adopted only when new canals are constructed as the section has to be sufficiently wide. In the external silting method, subsidiary banks are constructed to hold the water externally in a confined position. Both of these are methods of strengthening of canal banks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following combination is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silt removal – Silt ejectors and silt escapes",
            "b) Aquatic weed control – Mechanical removal of plants",
            "c) Breach due to piping – provision of a sand core in the bank",
            "d) Breaches in a big canal – Dumping huge quantity of earth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The spurs project into the canal section from the banks. They provide high silting rate and spurs may be raised after silting has taken place up to the top of spurs. Thus silting takes place in successive layers and finally, silt deposit reaches a predetermined height which is then raised up to the top of the bank.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Berm is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a horizontal strip at the N.S.L",
            "b) a device to remove silt",
            "c) another name of the canal bank",
            "d) a gap created in the bank of the canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is very essential to bring the flow of water out of the channel section to accomplish silting of banks externally. Subsidiary banks are required to hold the water externally in a confined position and are constructed parallel to the canal main banks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The Remodelling of canal system is done to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) beautify the canal surroundings",
            "b) correct deformations in the canal",
            "c) exhibit the canal in exhibition",
            "d) widen up the channel section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Canal water is taken in the compartment through the inlet. When the length of the compartment is between 1200 to 1500 m it is called long reach the system. The whole canal discharge is taken in the compartment and this is done when the water is not required for irrigation purposes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "What type of losses can be mainly avoided by lining the canals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation Losses",
            "b) Seepage Losses",
            "c) Erosion of Canal Bed",
            "d) Discharge Losses at Branch Canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For good quality of irrigation products and to avoid crop failures due to natural famines and scarcity of water a huge amount of capital should be invested in the irrigation projects. For example in our country for the five year plan (1997 – 2002) the capital invested in the irrigation projects is 115000 lakh crores. This says that irrigation water is a costly commodity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "What is the name given to the land unfit for agriculture due to waterlogging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Desert",
            "b) Tundra",
            "c) Waterlogged Area",
            "d) Thur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If lining is not provided in the canal then irrigation water is lost in the form of percolation and absorption as seepage losses. This loss is very significant as it reduces the potential of the irrigation water, which is a costly commodity. So, in order to reduce seepage losses the lining of the canal is needed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Design a lined canal carrying a discharge of 20 cumecs. The slope is 1 in 7000. Assume suitable values for side slopes and lining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side Slope = 1.2: 1, Depth = 4.4 m",
            "b) Side Slope = 1.4: 1, Depth = 4.1 m",
            "c) Side Slope = 1.5: 1, Depth = 3.77 m",
            "d) Side Slope = 1.3: 1, Depth = 4.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to uncontrolled seepage losses the water in the canal gets percolated and the water table level in underground rises. This level rises up to or near the ground level. This renders the land unfit for agriculture as the crop roots bring up the alkali salts to the ground level. This phenomenon is known as waterlogging and the land is called thur.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Design a lined canal to carry a discharge of 400 cumecs and slope is 1 in 6000. Take side slopes as 1 : 1 and rugosity constant as 0.012. Assume limiting velocity as 3 m/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total Depth = 6.3 m, Bed Width = 15 m",
            "b) Total Depth = 6.28 m, Bed Width = 14.2 m",
            "c) Total Depth = 6.5 m, Bed Width = 14 m",
            "d) Total Depth = 6.25 m, Bed Width = 14.4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: With the help of lining canals can be designed for both in smaller cross section and shorter in length. Steep gradients can be provided as higher velocities are allowed, and flat slopes can also be provided without silting action on lined canals. Therefore, due to these reasons the command area can be increased.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Depending on what factor does the lining of a canal can increase the capacity of the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Width of the Canal",
            "b) Type of Flow",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Side Slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Let us assume side slope as 1.5 : 1  (1.5H : 1V), the rugosity constant as 0.015.\nNow let us design a triangular section.\nA = y2 (θ + cotθ), P = 2y(θ + cotθ), and R = A/P = y/2\nTanθ = (1/1.5) and cotθ = 1.5 and θ = 0.59\nA = y2 (0.59 + 1.5) = y2 (2.09)\nP = 2 y (0.59 + 1.5) = y (4.18)\nR = 0.5y\nNow Manning’s equation gives\nQ = 1/n x A x R2/3 x S1/2\n20 = (1/0.015) x y2 (2.09) x (0.5y) 2/3 x (1/7000)1/2\ny= 3.02 m\nFreeboard = 0.75 m\nTotal depth = 3.02 + 0.75 = 3.77 m and side slope = 1.5 : 1\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Mathematically, depending on what factor we can say velocity increases the capacity of the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coefficient of Viscosity",
            "b) Coefficient of Capillarity",
            "c) Coefficient of Roughness",
            "d) Coefficient of Resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: V = 1/n x R2/3 x S1/2\n3 = (1/0.012) x R2/3 x (1/6000)1/2\nR = 4.7 m\nDesign a trapezoidal section canal.\nA = y (B + yθ + y cotθ), P = B + 2yθ + 2y cotθ\nNow Tanθ = 1/1, θ = 0.785 radians, and cotθ = 1\nNow A = y (B + y x 0.785 + y x 1) = y(B + 1.785y), P = B + 2y(0.785) + 2y(1) = B + 2.57y\nA = Q/V = 400/3 = 133.33 sq.m\n100 = y (B +1.785y), B = 100/y – 1.785y\nR = A/P = 133.33/P\n4.7 = 133.33/B + 2.57Y\ny= 5.5 m\nB = 14.4 m\nTotal Depth = 5.5 + 0.75 = 6.25 m\nBed Width = 14.4 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What type of major dangers can the lining of canals extinguish?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leakages",
            "b) Floods",
            "c) Water-logging",
            "d) Seepage Losses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reason is very simple. The lined surface provides a smooth surface for the flow of water with minimum resistance, whereas the unlined canal provides more resistance due to vegetation, undulations, rocks etc. Moreover the velocity of flow in lined canal is high when compared with the velocity in unlined canal, as the capacity of canal is dependent on the velocity directly if velocity increases so does the capacity of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What costs are reduced with the help of lining a canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A.R and M.O Costs",
            "b) Irrigation Water Costs",
            "c) Construction Costs",
            "d) Transportation Costs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coefficient of roughness is indirectly proportional to velocity in any mathematical formula, or condition, or equation. So, therefore the value of this coefficient is more for unlined canals than the lined canals. Hence the velocity is more for lined canals than the unlined canals and therefore capacity for lined canals is more.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of the lining of the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seepage control",
            "b) Prevention of water-logging",
            "c) Increase in channel capacity",
            "d) Increased maintenance costs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The construction of larger reservoirs and bigger dams will be necessary if there is heavy seepage loss in canals. Lining the canals reduces their impounding capacity and hence lower the construction costs of these works.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "What is the range of value of Manning’s coefficient for straight alignment for cast in-situ concrete lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.012 – 0.015",
            "b) 0.015 – 0.018",
            "c) 0.018 – 0.020",
            "d) 0.020 – 0.025"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Huge expenditure is spent on annual repair and maintenance of the unlined canal. The provision of lining reduces expenditure required for removal of silt, minor repairs like plugging of cracks, cuts, and removal of weeds and water plants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A lined canal is not susceptible to erosion",
            "b) The provision of adequate lining reduces the danger of breaches of channel",
            "c) The lining does not reduce the money spent in removing weeds",
            "d) Lining eliminates flood dangers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vegetation on the sides and bottom of the canal retards the flow of water in unlined canals. The higher the velocity, the greater is the capacity of the channel and hence, capacity is a function of velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The velocity varies inversely with the Manning’s coefficient",
            "b) For unlined channels in good condition, the value of Manning’s coefficient is 0.015 for concrete",
            "c) Flatter slopes can be provided without silting on a lined channel",
            "d) The lining does not help to bring high areas under the command"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In absolutely straight reaches and with relatively higher discharges lower values of Manning’s constant may be attained. For cast in-situ concrete lining, the value of n varies from 0.015–0.018 and for cement plastered masonry the value varies from 0.012-0.015.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What types of channel sections are usually adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangular and Circular channel",
            "b) Triangular and Trapezoidal channel",
            "c) Rectangular and Trapezoidal channel",
            "d) Rectangular and Triangular channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, Triangular and Trapezoidal channel sections are adopted. For smaller discharges, the Triangular channel section is adopted and trapezoidal channel for larger discharges.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is the maximum permissible velocity in Cement concrete lining (Unreinforced) as per Indian Standards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 2.5 m/sec",
            "b) 1.5 to 2 m/sec",
            "c) 1.2 to 1.8 m/sec",
            "d) 1.5 to 2.5 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum permissible velocity for unreinforced cement concrete lining is 2.0 to 2.5 m/sec. For Boulder lining, the maximum permissible velocity is 1.5 m/sec.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "What is the minimum value of free-board for Main and Branch Lined canals if the discharge is more than 10 cumecs as per specified by BIS code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.60",
            "b) 0.50",
            "c) 0.75",
            "d) 0.30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In main and branch canals for discharge more than 10 cumecs, the minimum value of freeboard is 0.75 m. For branch canals and distributaries in which discharge is less than 10 cumecs the value is 0.60 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "What is the minimum value of inspection bank width recommended by Indian Standards if the discharge is more than 30 cumecs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.0",
            "b) 5.0",
            "c) 6.0",
            "d) 7.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical distance between the full supply level (F.S.L) and the top of the bank is called freeboard. It depends on the size of the canal, location of the canal and water level fluctuations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Calculate hydraulic mean depth for concrete-lined channel to carry a discharge of 350 cumecs at a slope of 1 in 5000. The value of manning’s constant for the lining is 0.015. The side slopes of a channel may be taken as 1.5:1. Assume limiting velocity in the channel as 2m/sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.20 m",
            "b) 2.40 m",
            "c) 2.60 m",
            "d) 2.80 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum value of the top width of the bank depends on the value of discharge. For discharge greater than 30 cumecs, the minimum value of the top width of the inspection bank is 8.0 m and for Non-inspection bank is 5.0 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Calculate the central depth of a triangular channel section to carry a discharge of 15 cumecs. Consider the available slope as 1 in 9000. Assume the side slopes of the channel be 1.25:1 and manning’s constant is 0.015 for good brick work in lining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.94 m",
            "b) 3.14 m",
            "c) 2.25 m",
            "d) 2.77 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Higher velocities can be safely used in lined canals. The maximum permissible velocities for concrete linings when the lining is not reinforced are up to 2.5 m/sec. The lining can be reinforced if still higher velocities are desired.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is applied under pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shotcrete Lining",
            "b) Boulder Lining",
            "c) Asphaltic Concrete Lining",
            "d) Brick Lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The name given to this lining is to designate that the mortar is applied under pressure with the help of a nozzle on the surface of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is popular in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boulder Lining",
            "b) Brick Lining",
            "c) Cement Concrete Lining",
            "d) Shotcrete Lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Brick Lining is very popular in India due to bricks can be laid by ordinary masons, rigid quality control is not needed, expansion joints are not needed, huge employment is provided, isolated damaged parts can be easily repaired, plastering of bricks can be done to increase the canal capacity and its life span also.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is mixed and placed under temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cement Concrete Lining",
            "b) Shotcrete Lining",
            "c) Asphaltic Concrete Lining",
            "d) Dry Stone Lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Asphaltic concrete lining has been under evolution. It is used in very few places. This concrete is a careful mixture of asphalt and graded stone aggregate, and is mixed and applied under elevated temperature. This is a flexible lining and readily confirms to subgrade.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "What is the biggest advantage of boulder lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impervious Lining",
            "b) Dry Stone Lining",
            "c) Dhamalis",
            "d) Pervious Lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the boulder lining is a pervious lining, it allows free flow of water from submerged or saturated subgrade into the canal. Moreover, this lining does not need any drainage arrangements. This lining can be used in areas where water table is higher than FSL of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is only used for lining the side slopes of the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shotcrete Lining",
            "b) Dry Stone Lining",
            "c) Asphaltic Concrete Lining",
            "d) Cement Concrete Lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This type of lining is only used for lining the side slopes of the canal by proper placing and packing of stones, either after laying a filter paper or not, depending on the soil requirement. Therefore this lining does not help in preventing the seepage losses but helps to maintain the shape of the canal, hence reducing the maintenance cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which type of cement grade is used in cement concrete lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M20",
            "b) M25",
            "c) M10",
            "d) M15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shotcrete lining can be used for smaller jobs, because this lining requires lighter equipment and small crew to carry out the works. It can also be used in rehabilitation of old canals and repair works. The trimming of the canal section can be avoided by using this lining in irregular canals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "For how many days curing of concrete lining takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 days",
            "b) 28 days",
            "c) 27 days",
            "d) 26 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If there is settlement of subgrade in a canal where brick lining is present, the mortar joints present between the bricks or tiles provide numerous cracks so that seepage of canal water would be insignificant. The local area can be repaired without any problem even in case of abnormal settlement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "In the laying of concrete, what paper is laid to make filter blanket effective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filter Layer",
            "b) Filter Blanket",
            "c) Tar Paper",
            "d) Sandpaper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mixture ratio of M15 grade is 1:2:4 (cement, sand, coarse aggregate) and this ratio is a good quality type for construction of cement concrete lining. This lining gives satisfactory service, high durability, hydraulic efficiency, weed free surface, long life, minimum maintenance cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "In soil-cement lining the Portland cement is added to the soil up to the extent of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4% to 5%",
            "b) 2% to 8%",
            "c) 0.1% to 5%",
            "d) > 10%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Portland cement up to the extent of 2% to 8% is added to the locally available soil. Water is then added and thoroughly mixed so as to bring the soil to its optimum moisture content. The material is then placed and compacted at the site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is restricted to the availability of suitable soils in the area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compacted earth lining",
            "b) Soil-cement lining",
            "c) Cement mortar lining",
            "d) Stone lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of this lining is restricted to the soil available in the area where the canal has to be constructed. Soil graded to obtain the required characteristics and is compacted at optimum moisture content. Transportation of such soils from outside is not recommended as it would be uneconomical.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which lining is restricted to small canals and water-courses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compacted earth lining",
            "b) Asphalt lining",
            "c) Sodium carbonate lining",
            "d) Stone lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sodium carbonate lining is not very durable and it lasts only for about 3 to 4 years in ordinary cases. Hence it is restricted to small canals and watercourses. This consists of a layer of clayey soil and sodium carbonate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "A flexible membrane impregnated with tar or bitumen is spread over the subgrade in _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) asphalt lining",
            "b) soil-cement lining",
            "c) cement mortar lining",
            "d) puddle clay lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Asphalt lining a flexible membrane-like rot proof canvas or cloth is infused with tar or bitumen is spread over the subgrade. This forms an impervious barrier and is responsible for preventing seepage loss.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "What is the safe limiting velocity for cement concrete lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 m/s",
            "b) 2.2 m/s",
            "c) 2.7 m/s",
            "d) 1.8 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For cement concrete lining, the safe limiting velocity is 2.7 m/s. For boulder lining, it is 1.5 m/s and for burnt clay tile lining it is approximately 1.8 m/s. This serves as a guide for selecting canal slopes and alignments.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The most economical type of lining is the one which shows ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum benefit-cost ratio",
            "b) maximum benefit-cost ratio",
            "c) zero benefit-cost ratio",
            "d) benefit-cost ratio = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The one which shows the maximum annual benefit-cost ratio is the most economical lining. It may have a higher cost initially but longer life than another type of lining having a lesser value of the annual benefit-cost ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following guideline is not recommended for the choice of lining when the bed width of the canal is up to 3 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single burnt clay tile lining or brick lining",
            "b) PCC slab lining",
            "c) Flexible membrane lining with adequate earth/tile cover",
            "d) In-situ cement concrete lining in bed as well as on sides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The choice of suitable lining for different size of a canal depends on canal slopes and alignments, size and importance of canal, the climate of the area, initial expenditure, etc. In-situ cement concrete lining in bed and on sides is generally preferred for canals when bed width is greater than 8 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cause for the hydrostatic pressure on the lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seeping of the rainwater in the backfill",
            "b) When the water table remains below the canal bed",
            "c) The backfill is of low drainage",
            "d) The backfill is of high permeability (i.e. > 3 cm/sec)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the subgrade is made of clear gravel or sand of good permeability (> 3 cm/sec) and the water table is not likely to go above the canal bed no drainage arrangements may be necessary. There will be no appreciable time lag in the dissipation of drawdown pore pressures in the subgrade for such case.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Drainage relief pockets are provided ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) at isolated locations in the bed as well as sides of the lined canal",
            "b) in the bed of the canal",
            "c) in the sides of the canal",
            "d) anywhere in the canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Drainage relief pockets are provided with pressure relief valves filled with a graded filter containing gravel, coarse sand, and fine sand. They are provided at isolated locations in the bed as well as on the sides below the lining at suitable spacing (@ 15 to 20 m intervals).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Pressure relief valves may help in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) releasing the hydrostatic pressure",
            "b) holding the hydrostatic pressure",
            "c) increasing the hydrostatic pressure",
            "d) may increase or decrease the hydrostatic pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The permeability of lining may decide the quantum of seepage loss from a canal. The seepage losses from a canal for a particular area will depend on the local conditions such as the values of land and water, population intensity, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Pipe drains run _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinally on the bed and transverse to the length of canal on the side slopes",
            "b) longitudinally to the length of the canal on the side slopes and transverse to the bed",
            "c) longitudinally to the length of the canal",
            "d) transverse to the bed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure relief valve is a flap valve opening upwards into the canal. It helps in releasing the hydrostatic pressure as soon as the differential head exceeds the safe pressure. These valves open out as soon as the differential pressure goes beyond 10 cm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong about the requirement of good lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lining should be able to withstand the differential sub-soil pressure",
            "b) Brick lining, concrete lining or precast slab lining can be easily repaired as compared to cast-in-situ concrete lining",
            "c) The hydraulic efficiency generally reduces with time",
            "d) Brick tile lining may provide better abrasion  resistance than cement concrete and boulder lining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Provision of open-jointed pipe drains is one of the methods of drainage arrangements. It will run longitudinally on a trench excavated below the lining on the canal bed along the length of the canal and transverse to the length of the canal on the side slopes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which type of lining is adopted when the channels have become stable and no danger of scouring is expected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brick lining",
            "b) Single burnt clay tile lining",
            "c) In-situ cement concrete lining",
            "d) Flexible membrane lining in the bed and rigid lining on the sides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A canal may have to transport a considerable amount of sediment load which damages the lining by abrasion. Cement concrete and stone boulder linings provide better abrasion resistance as compared to the brick tile lining.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about Expansive soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expansive soils exhibit shrinkage and swelling properties",
            "b) They have high compressibility and liquid limits with more than 50",
            "c) Black cotton soil is the most common expansive soil in India",
            "d) The lesser the swelling pressure, the more troublesome is the soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The expansive soils are clayey soils having clay mineral montmorillonite and chief property of such a soil is its swelling pressure. The soil is more troublesome and problematic if it has high swelling pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "What is the recommended value of CNS thickness to be used for lining over expansive soil with swelling pressure of 200-300 KN/m2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75 to 85 cm",
            "b) 90 to 100 cm",
            "c) 105 to 125 cm",
            "d) > 125 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A layer of some cohesive non-swelling soil (CNS) is added over the expansive soil surface to counteract the swelling pressure. The larger the thickness of CNS, the lesser would be the resulting swelling and deformations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Safety ladders are generally provided on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) side slopes",
            "b) bed slopes",
            "c) anywhere on the canal",
            "d) both side slopes and bed slopes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For swelling pressure ranging from 50-150 KN/m2, the value of CNS thickness varies from 75 to 85 cm and for swelling pressure 200-300 KN/m2, the value is 90 to 100 cm. The CNS thickness is more for more expansive soil and less for less expansive soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Safety ladders are provided in large irrigation canals to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) enable the fish to pass from one place to another",
            "b) enable the cattle to cross the canal",
            "c) enable the swimmers to get out of the canal",
            "d) provide safe exit to avoid accidental drowning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In large canals, it is generally provided on side slopes along the canal length at suitable intervals. The ladders are provided on both the banks in straight reaches at about 300 m staggering distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "CNS material shall be non-swelling with a minimum of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 KN/m2 of cohesion",
            "b) 15 KN/m2 of cohesion",
            "c) 20 KN/m2 of cohesion",
            "d) 30 KN/m2 of cohesion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Free swell index is the increase in the volume of soil when subjected to submergence in water without any external constraint. If the value is less than 100, the soil is treated as non-expansive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about the identification of CNS material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The CNS material can be identified by using A-line chart",
            "b) The permissible deformation of the CNS layer is 20 mm",
            "c) The swelling pressure should  not exceed 10 KN/m2",
            "d) The soil with liquid limit less than 30% and plastic index less than 15% is considered suitable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Safety ladders are generally provided in large canals on both the banks which consists of a number of ladder rungs at different elevations along the canal length. In case any person or cattle that may be swept away with the flowing water may catch hold one such ladder rung and can climb the higher rungs to get out of the canal to prevent themselves from drowning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "A land is said to be water-logged when _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the aeration is stopped in the root zone due to the rise in water content",
            "b) there is a reduction in crop yield",
            "c) there is an accumulation of alkali salts in the root zone of the crop",
            "d) there is salinity in the soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A land is said to be water-logged when the productivity of land gets affected and the crop root-zone gets deprived of proper aeration due to the flooding or high water table. It represents a saturated condition of the soil especially that of the crop root-zone with water. It also leads to the salinity of the soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "What is the pH range for strongly alkaline soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.4 – 7.8",
            "b) 7.9 – 8.4",
            "c) 8.5 – 9.0",
            "d) > 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Very strongly alkaline soils (pH>9) and ultra-acidic soils (pH<3.5) are very rare. The USDA classifies soil pH for alkalinity as follows:\n\n\n\n\nDenomination\npH range\n\n\nSlightly alkaline\n7.4 – 7.8\n\n\nModerately alkaline\n7.9 – 8.4\n\n\nStrongly alkaline\n8.5 – 9.0\n\n\nVery strongly alkaline\n> 9.0\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seepage drains reduce the chances of water-logging",
            "b) Untimely maturity of the crops is the characteristic of water-logged lands",
            "c) The percolation loss can be reduced by keeping the intensity of irrigation low",
            "d) There is no way to keep a watch over the problem of water-logging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Presence of excessive moisture lowers the temperature of the soil. In low temperatures the bacterial activities are retarded and their growth rates are also affected. It affects the soil-crop badly as soil microbial activity is disturbed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Swampy land is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ill-aerated land",
            "b) the land where cultivation operations are impossible",
            "c) land having deposition of alkali salts in the root zone of the crops",
            "d) saline land"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By observing variations in the ground-water level is one of the ways of keeping a check on the problem. It can be done by measuring the depth of water levels at regular intervals in the wells dug in the area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a remedial measure for water-logging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controlling seepage from the canals",
            "b) By lowering the F.S.L of the canals",
            "c) Quick disposal of rainwater",
            "d) Installation of lift irrigation systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrologic equation:- Inflow = Outflow + Storage\nInflow represents the amount of water that enters the sub-soil in various processes. The term outflow represents mainly evaporation from the soil, transpiration from plants, and underground drainage of the track. The term storage represents a change in the ground-water reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor do not contribute to water-logging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inadequate drainage",
            "b) Seepage from unlined canals",
            "c) Frequent flooding",
            "d) Excessive tapping of groundwater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The normal cultivation operations such as tilling, ploughing is difficult in wet soils. The cultivation operation becomes impossible if the free water may rise above the surface of the land in extreme cases. Such land is called swampy land.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not a remedial measure for waterlogging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good drainage for irrigated land",
            "b) Conjunctive use of water in the basin",
            "c) The lining of canals and watercourses",
            "d) Contour bunding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to efflorescence, there is a deposition of salts on the surface of soil forming a thin crust after the evaporation of water. Land affected by that is saline soil and the soil water surrounding the roots of the plants reduces the osmotic activity of the soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which factor depends upon the depressions of the terrain and causes water logging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Irregular Topography",
            "b) Impervious Obstruction",
            "c) Inadequate Surface Drainage",
            "d) Excessive Rains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In hilly areas, the water is drained quickly, but in case of flat or irregular terrains having depressions the drainage is not adequate. This leads to more stagnation of water causing percolation and rising of water table.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which factor is concerned with the growth of weeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excessive Rains",
            "b) Submergence due to Floods",
            "c) Over and Intensive Irrigation",
            "d) Seepage of Water through the Canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a particular is continuously submerged under due to floods, this paves the way for the growth of water plants like weeds and grasses e.t.c. and obstructs the natural surface drainage flow causing waterlogging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Due to inadequate drainage which factor causes waterlogging with constant percolation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Over and Intensive Irrigation",
            "b) Impervious Obstruction",
            "c) Inadequate Surface Drainage",
            "d) Flat Topography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During rains storm water gets mixed with irrigation water. The irrigation water should be removed so as to not mix with storm water as this leads to percolation. Moreover, if proper drainage is not present constant percolation happens and water table rises.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "What factor creates temporary and continuous waterlogging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Submergence due to Floods",
            "b) Flat Topography",
            "c) Impervious Obstruction",
            "d) Excessive Rains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Excessive rainfalls create temporary waterlogging, but if adequate drainage is not present or provided then it leads to continuous waterlogging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which factor leads to waterlogging due to obstruction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inadequate Natural Drainage",
            "b) Flat Topography",
            "c) Impervious Obstruction",
            "d) Over and Intensive Irrigation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, water after seeping the soil moves horizontally before even seeping further. But this movement is sometimes is obstructed by some obstructions like stone, ice, or some impervious stratum below the top layers of pervious soil. In these cases seeping water cannot go deep and resulting in the rise of water table.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which factor comes into play when less permeable substratum is present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat Topography",
            "b) Impervious Obstruction",
            "c) Excessive Rains",
            "d) Inadequate Natural Drainage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When there is the presence of less permeable substratum below the top layers of permeable soils there is poor drainage of water into the deep ground. So, therefore if proper natural drainage is present waterlogging takes place.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "When a canal is taken as an example what factor about it causes waterlogging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seepage of Water from the High Lands",
            "b) Seepage of Water through the Canals",
            "c) Over and Intensive Irrigation",
            "d) Excessive Rains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a canal is unlined then there room for seepage losses through the side slopes, and bed of the canal. This leads to the rise of water table in the adjoining areas due to percolation of water, which ultimately leads to waterlogging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which factor causing waterlogging suggests extensive irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impervious Obstruction",
            "b) Excessive Rains",
            "c) Over and Intensive Irrigation",
            "d) Seepage of Water from High Lands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When intensive irrigation is practiced, it only irrigates a small portion of the whole irrigable land. Due to this over irrigation it leads to heavy percolation which leads to rising of water table causing waterlogging. So, to prevent waterlogging extensive method of irrigation is recommended.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "How many types of structures can be constructed in the fields to remove excess waters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Open ditches are constructed in fields to remove the excess rain water falling in the ground or excess irrigation water applied to the fields. So, therefore for collection of these waters the land is sloped towards these ditches.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What is the name given to the drains used in depressions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow Surface Drains",
            "b) Deep Surface Drains",
            "c) Open Drains",
            "d) Drains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Structures like open ditches, fields drains, and other related structures like artificial pipes etc can be constructed in the fields to remove excess waters from heavy rainfalls and excess irrigation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "What is the cross sectional shape of shallow surface drains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangular Shape",
            "b) Circular Shape",
            "c) Rectangular Shape",
            "d) Trapezoidal Shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shallow surface drains are those types of open drains constructed in depressions on the fields to remove excess irrigation water, and storm water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which type of open drains would be fully operative only in rainy season?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow Surface Drains",
            "b) Deep Surface Drains",
            "c) French Drain",
            "d) Drains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shallow surface drains are in turn connected to the outlet drains, which are large enough to carry the maximum flood water of the catchment area from the shallow drains, and even from underground tile drains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "What structure is constructed to carry back into the underground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Land Grading",
            "b) Random Field Drains",
            "c) Surface Inlet",
            "d) Open Drains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the shallow surface drains are designed to carry normal storm water and excess irrigation water. These are designed for normal runoff from the storm water, but we have to take excess irrigation into the account. So, for maximum discharge the shallow surface drains are given a trapezoidal cross sectional shape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "In surface inlet what is provided to deal with trash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cunnette",
            "b) Beehive Grate",
            "c) Surface Inlet",
            "d) Blind Inlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These drains carry both discharge from shallow surface drains and the seepage water from underground. To carry the seepage water from underground, a cunnette of about 0.6 m depth is provided at the center of the drain. The cunnette is lined void weed growth, and to withstand high velocities. It is fully operative only in rainy season because otherwise the flow will be confined in the cunnette only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which type of drains is used for small quantity of waters removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blind Inlet",
            "b) Shallow Surface Drains",
            "c) Deep Surface Drains",
            "d) Open Drains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surface inlets are the structures constructed to carry the pit water back into the subsurface. The materials used in the construction are cast iron pipe or manhole of bricks or monolithic concrete.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "How can tile drainage help to increase crop yields?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases Free Gravity Water",
            "b) Increases Volume of Soil",
            "c) Decrease Air Circulation",
            "d) Increases Water Table Level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Surface drains are needed for crops cultivated on flat lands to remove excess irrigation water, whereas subsurface drains are needed for soils having poor internal drainage and high water table. So, therefore for maximum productivity of crops both surface and subsurface drains are sometimes essential especially in regions of high water table.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which type of soils is benefited by using tile drainage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry Soils",
            "b) Black Soils",
            "c) Wet Soils",
            "d) Red Soils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tile drainage helps in lowering the water table level which in turn increases the crop yields. It also helps in increasing the volume of soil from where the roots of the crops can obtain food.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "In what chemical ways does tile drainage help in plant growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases Alkalinity of Soils",
            "b) Increases salinity of Soils",
            "c) Increases Nitrogen",
            "d) Reduces and Removes Toxic Substances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As tile drainage helps in lowering the groundwater level, it gives room for increase in volume of the soil and helps the roots to hold on to the soil very tight. It also provides well drained soil to hold rainfall, resulting in less runoff. Due to these reasons, the soil erosion is reduced by tile drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Under what strata the tile drainage should not be placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In Shallow Depths",
            "b) More Pervious Strata",
            "c) Less Pervious Strata",
            "d) Pervious Strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tile drainage requires less labour and time in tilling and harvesting the soils as these do not obstruct farming. Planting in wet soils may decrease crop yields. So, therefore the delay in planting and decrease in crop yields in wet soils can be improved by using tile drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "What structure is surrounded around the tile drains when used in less pervious strata?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Envelope Filters",
            "b) French Drains",
            "c) Beehive Grate",
            "d) Surface Inlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tile drainage helps in reducing and removal of toxic chemicals and substances like sodium and other soluble salts, which harms the growth of plants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "What is the size of the tile at an outlet of a 12 hectare drainage system, if the D.C is 2 cm and the tile grade is 0.5%. Assume the rugosity coefficient as 0.015 for the tile drain material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 cm",
            "b) 20 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 25 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tile drainage should not be placed under or below the less pervious strata because in this case, the drains may remain dry even though the land above the impervious strata may be logged as this water will not reach the drains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which type of alternate layouts system for tile drainage has two mains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grid Iron System",
            "b) Natural System",
            "c) Double main System",
            "d) Herring Bone System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Envelope filters surround the tile drains when used in less pervious strata. These filters help in increasing the effective tile diameter and in turn help increasing the inflow rate, and also help in preventing the inflow of soil into the drains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "How many cubic metres of water will be removed for this particular period of a system designed to use a D.C of 1.5 cm draining 20 hectares for a capacity of 5 days?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10000 m3",
            "b) 25000 m3",
            "c) 15000 m3",
            "d) 20000 m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Volume of water passing the drain in one day = (1/100 x 12 x 104) = 1200 m3/day\nVolume of water passing the drain in one second = (1200/24 x 3600) = 1/72 m3/sec\nQ = 1/72 m3/sec\nQ = 1/n x A x R2/3 x S1/2\nA = πD2/4, P = πD, R = A/P = D/4\n1/72 = (1/0.015) x (πD2/4) x (D/4) x (0.5/100)\nOn solving the value of D = 17.4 cm\nUse D = 20 cm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which among the following salt is also called black alkali?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Na2CO3",
            "b) Na2SO4",
            "c) NaCl",
            "d) NaOH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Na2CO3 is present in excess in black alkali soils. It is known as a black alkali because it dissolves some organic constituents of soil which appears black in solution with it. The patches of black stain are generally spotted on the ground.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which is the least harmful salt for agricultural soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Na2CO3",
            "b) Na2SO4",
            "c) NaCl",
            "d) NaOH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NaCl is found in excess in white-alkali soils. In this, salinity is caused by soluble salts other than alkali salts. The reaction between NaCl and soil (S) produces Na(S) and Cl– ion and the soluble products are leached away from the soil surface by drainage water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Alkali soils are reclaimed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) leaching of soil",
            "b) using limestone as a soil amendment",
            "c) using gypsum as a soil amendment",
            "d) provision of drainage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plant roots contain pure water on one side of the membrane and highly concentrated salt solution on the other side. By osmosis, the pure water within the roots will start flowing out of the roots towards the salt solution until the pressure becomes equal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "If the salt concentration of the irrigation water ranges from 0.5 – 2 g/L, then what is the restriction on its use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No restriction on its use",
            "b) It should be used with appropriate water management practices",
            "c) It is not generally advised for use unless consulted with specialists",
            "d) No dependency on the salt concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Alkali soils are best reclaimed by cationic exchange i.e. replacement of alkali from soil colloids by calcium ions. Application of gypsum in the soil reduces alkalinity to a great extent and makes the soil fertile. Good drainage leaches away the by-product of the reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "If the salt concentration of the soil water (saturation extract) in milli-mhos/cm is in between 4.5 – 9, then what is the salinity of the soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-saline",
            "b) Slightly saline",
            "c) Medium saline",
            "d) Highly saline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the salt concentration is less than 0.5 g/L, then there is no salinization risk and no restriction on the use of irrigation water. If the concentration is more than 2 g/L, there is high risk and is not generally advised for use. If the concentration is in between there is slight to moderate risk and it should be used with appropriate water management practices.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Solonchak soil is the other name for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) alkali Soils",
            "b) sodic Soils",
            "c) saline-alkali soils",
            "d) saline soils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The salt concentration in the water extracted from a saturated soil defines the salinity of the soil.\n\n\nS.NO\nThe salt concentration of soil water\nSalinity\n\n\n1.\n0 – 4.5 milli-mhos/cm\nNon-saline\n\n\n2.\n4.5 – 9.0 milli-mhos/cm\nSlightly saline\n\n\n3.\n9.0 – 18 milli-mhos/cm\nMedium saline\n\n\n4.\n>18 milli-mhos/cm\nHighly saline\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "A soil sample has an Exchangeable sodium percentage (ESP) of 16%, its electrical conductivity is 3.2 Milli-Mohs/cm and a pH of 9.5. How is the soil classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saline soil",
            "b) Saline-alkaline soil",
            "c) Alkaline soil",
            "d) Non-saline soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Solonchak soil is also called white alkali or saline soils. They have an excessive concentration of natural soluble salts and low exchangeable sodium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "What are the three classes of salty soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saline soil, Saline-alkali soil, Non-saline soil",
            "b) Saline soil, Alkali soil, Non-saline soil",
            "c) Saline soil, Alkali soil, Saline-alkali soil",
            "d) Alkali soil, Non-saline soil, Saline-alkali soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The three classes of salty soil are based on these three properties pH range, ESP, and conductivity of saturated extract. Alkali soil has pH range in between 8.5 and 10, ESP greater than 15, and conductivity of saturated extract less than 4 milli-mhos/cm at 25°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "What is Solonetz soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White alkali soil",
            "b) Black alkali soil",
            "c) Highly saline soil",
            "d) Non-saline soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The three classes are –\ni. Saline or white alkali or solonchak soil- High soluble salts and low ESP\nii. Alkali or Sodic or black alkali soil – Low salt content but high ESP\niii. Saline-alkali soils – High salt content and High ESP.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Estimate the leaching requirement when electrical conductivity (EC) value of a saturated extract of soil is 10 m mho/cm at 25% reduction in the yield of the crop. The EC of irrigation water is 1.5 m mho/cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 6.66%",
            "c) 7.5%",
            "d) 10%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solonetz soil is another name for sodic soil or alkali soil or black alkali soil. These are formed by excess accumulation of alkalies such as Na, K, etc. Such soils have low salt content but high Exchangeable sodium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "On which factor does the pricing of irrigation water is done on a flat rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of Crops Sown",
            "b) Amount of Irrigation Water Used",
            "c) For the Whole Field Sown",
            "d) Per Hectare"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the pricing of irrigation water is done on the flat rate or crop rate basis, then these rates are specified per hectare of each sown crop, cultivated by the cultivators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "On how many factors does the specified rates in the crop rate system of pricing depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the pricing of irrigation water groundnut is priced four times the wheat crop even though groundnut uses only one-third of water used by wheat. But groundnut is priced more because the reason is that groundnut has a higher earning capacity compared to wheat. So, therefore from this we can say that groundnut is a cash crop and wheat is a food crop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What does the crop rate system may lead to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overutilization Water",
            "b) Careful use of Water",
            "c) Sufficient use of Water",
            "d) Insufficient use of Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specified rates in the crop rate system of pricing depending on the factors like water requirement of each crop, and earning capacity of that crop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "In crop rate revenue system field assessment is done by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canal Officer",
            "b) IAS Officer",
            "c) Tahsildar",
            "d) Patwari"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This system does help the cultivators for economizing in the use of water because the cultivators will be charged at a flat rate for the area of crops grown. So, therefore the cultivators will never bother to the wastage of water and will use the water recklessly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Who has the authority to grant remissions to the cultivators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IAS Officer",
            "b) Canal Officer",
            "c) Patwari",
            "d) Tahsildar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As this method does not encourage the cultivators to economically use the water, it leads to over utilization of water which in turn leads waterlogging, salinity of irrigated lands, and wastage of precious irrigation water, which ultimately leads to scarcity of irrigation water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "In which method of pricing measuring devices are installed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct Revenue Collection",
            "b) Crop Rate System",
            "c) Volumetric Method of Pricing",
            "d) Crop Rate Revenue System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The field assessment in the crop rate revenue system, the area required by each crop grown by the cultivators is carried out and recorded by patwari at the time of sowing, cultivating, and harvesting.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which type of system is not in practice in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crop Rate Revenue System",
            "b) Direct Revenue Collection",
            "c) Crop Rate System",
            "d) Volumetric Method of Pricing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We cannot expect a complete yield from the complete area of the crops sown. Due to natural calamities or due to human made mistakes the yield of the crop may decrease. So, when the failure of crop occurs due to the reasons which cannot be controlled by the cultivators, the canal officers have the authority to grant remissions to the cultivators in full or part.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which type of system can be easily used in tube well irrigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct Revenue Collection",
            "b) Crop Rate Revenue System",
            "c) Volumetric Method of Pricing",
            "d) Crop Rate System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this type of system measuring devices like water meters, modular outlets, and venturi meters at the outlets of irrigation minors because in this pricing of irrigation water is done on basis of actual consumption of water by each cultivator or by a group of cultivators like society.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Depending on how many factors the government generally fixes the irrigation water revenue rates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depending on the factors like water requirement of the crops, and earning capacity of the crop the government generally fixes the revenue rates of irrigation waters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "According to which factor the real cost of irrigation water can be worked out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintenance Costs",
            "b) Initial Capital",
            "c) Economic Considerations",
            "d) Total Area of Irrigated Land"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Based on economic considerations like computing the cost of irrigation project, its annual operating and maintenance costs, and recovery of the capital during its lifespan.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What policy was framed in India to reduce the losses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Irrigation Water Policy",
            "b) Water Law",
            "c) Policy of Water",
            "d) National Water Policy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To work out the real cost of irrigation waters based on economic considerations, a rate is worked from these considerations. Such a rate, which is worked in terms of rupees per some unit quantity of water, is known as economic water rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "What is the main agenda of the National Water Policy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quality Check of Irrigation Water",
            "b) Recommendations to States",
            "c) Maintenance of the Irrigation Structures",
            "d) Recover Charges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to reduce the huge losses and subsidies, given by the government in operations of irrigation water systems and the urgent need to increase the water rates a new policy was framed in India in 1987.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "In the main agenda of National Water Policy what charges can be exempted for time being?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recovery of Annual Operation Charges",
            "b) Recovery of Maintenance Charges",
            "c) Recovery of Fixed Capital",
            "d) Irrigation Water Charges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Economic water rates are higher than the rates being charged by the government bodies in the country. For instance in Gujarat state charged a rupees 0.3 per kiloliter, but only rupees 0.18 per kiloliter is charged by State Tube well Corporation. Similar situations are being faced in states like Orissa, Andhra Pradesh etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "What is the name of the committee appointed by the government on 23-10-1991?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Committee on Revenue Collection on Irrigation Water",
            "b) Committee on Pricing of Irrigation Water",
            "c) Committee on Recovery of Charges",
            "d) Committee on Finding the Irrigation Structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main aim or agenda of the National Water Policy is that to recover the revenue rates to adequate the annual operation and maintenance charges and a part of the fixed capital. In this way, we can also convey the scarcity value of natural resources to the consumers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which state has completely avoided the irrigation revenue rates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Punjab",
            "b) Maharashtra",
            "c) Andhra Pradesh",
            "d) Gujarat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For some time being or in the initial working years of the irrigation structures (say 10 years) the recovery on the fixed capital cost charges as we must first fully rationalize our revenue rates in such a way that we recover annual and maintenance expenditure completely on the irrigation structures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "On what factors does the economic water rate depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With an initiative to rationalize the irrigation water rates in different states, the planning commission of India has appointed a Committee on Pricing of Irrigation Water on 23-10-1991.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Depending on the topography of the river basin, into how many classifications the river reaches are divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The classifications given on the basis of topography of river reaches are river in hills (upper reaches), rivers in plains (lower reaches), and tidal rivers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "The rivers in hills are further classified into how many groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Before entering the plains the upper reaches of the rivers flow through the hills, hence the name river in hills. These are further subdivided into a rocky river stage, and boulder river stage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which stage of the river is formed by erosion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aggrading",
            "b) Tidal Rivers",
            "c) Boulder River Stage",
            "d) Rocky River Stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this type of stage of the river the flow is formed by rapid erosion. These river reaches have high steep with swift flow, and form rapids along their courses. The bed load carried by these reaches cannot be determined by usual bed load transportation formulas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "What type of river stage widens the bed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Degrading",
            "b) Incised River Stage",
            "c) Boulder River Stage",
            "d) Stable Type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The river bed in these reaches is created by itself, consists a mixture of boulders, gravels, shingles, and alluvial sand deposits. In latter stage, the river flows through deep well defined beds and wider floodplains. Here the river flows in a straight course. Due to the floods, the boulders and material travels downward and gets deposited there after floods. Because of the opposition to the flow due to these obstructions the river takes new course and thus widens the river bed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "In what reaches the river flows in a zigzag manner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boulder River Stage",
            "b) Lower Reaches",
            "c) Degrading",
            "d) Tidal Rivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chief character of the river in these reaches is that it flows in a zigzag manner called meandering. This meandering is due to the difference in carrying the sediment which is similar to the bed load from one bank to the other bank of the river.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Into how many groups the rivers in floodplains can further be divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: River in the floodplains is further divided into aggrading, degrading, stable, braided, and deltaic types.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "In the meandering process on which side of the bank erosion takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convex Side",
            "b) Bottom of the River",
            "c) Concave Side",
            "d) Due to Sediment Load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In these reaches there is a constant erosion of the river bed on the concave side and the deposition of the eroded soil on the convex side of the successive bends or between two successive bends.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "In which type of river building up of slope is present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deltaic",
            "b) Stable type",
            "c) Degrading Type",
            "d) Aggrading Type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This type of river is formed due to the silting action which increases the bed slope. This silting action is due to various factors like heavy sediment load, construction of obstructions like dam or a weir, and sudden intrusion from a tributary.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "In which type of river there is a reduction of the available slope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Braided",
            "b) Stable Type",
            "c) Aggrading Type",
            "d) Degrading Type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This type of river is formed due to the constant erosion to reduce and finally dissipate available excess land scape. It is found below a dam or weir or barrage or above a cut off.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "In to how groups rivers in India are divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rivers in India are broadly classified into two types, namely Himalayan Rivers and Non-Himalayan Rivers. This classification is based on the basis of the origin of the rivers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which type of rivers can derive water from all seasons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tidal Rivers",
            "b) Non-Himalayan Rivers",
            "c) Himalayan Rivers",
            "d) Deltaic Rivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These types of rivers can derive water from rains in monsoon and winter seasons, but in summer they can derive water from the melting snow or ice from the mountains as these rivers take off from the Himalayas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "What is the example of Himalayan Rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cauvery",
            "b) Godavari",
            "c) Tapti",
            "d) Ganga"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Himalayan Rivers carry huge amounts of sediment because they flow through Himalayan rocks which are soft and friable. The reason is that the zone in which these rivers flow is very much prone to earthquake disturbances causing landslides and increased rock sediment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "What is the source of water for the Non-Himalayan Rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer Season",
            "b) Rainy Season",
            "c) Winter Season",
            "d) Himalayan Rivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ganga is the Himalayan River because it has its origin in Himalayan mountain glacier called Ganges, it flows through the alluvial plains in Northern India, and it is a perennial river.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "In which parts of India do non perennial rivers flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) North India",
            "b) Central and South India",
            "c) Eastern India",
            "d) West India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In months of August and July the rainfall is more than 3/4 of the average rainfall. So, due to this reason the North Indian Rivers rise in high floods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which river is the example of Non-Himalayan Rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chenab",
            "b) Beas",
            "c) Godavari",
            "d) Jhelum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Non-Himalayan Rivers are not perennial rivers. They receive most part of the water from the rainy seasons. And for the rest of the year they receive water from the groundwater as base flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which type of rivers is more stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Himalayan Rivers",
            "b) Non-Himalayan Rivers",
            "c) Virgin Rivers",
            "d) Flashy Rivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These rivers flow in Central and Southern India, as these regions are full of plateaus, valleys which is not the case in Northern India where the land terrain is of plains. Here the rivers do not have a constant water source as in case of perennial rivers, which have Himalayan mountain ranges ice as their source.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The flood discharge in Himalayan Rivers can be great as how times the normal winter flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 to 75",
            "b) 25 to 50",
            "c) 75 to 100",
            "d) 50 to 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Godavari is the best example of non-perennial rivers. It originates from Maharashtra (Central India) and merges into the Bay of Bengal in Andhra Pradesh (South India).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "According to what variations the Himalayan Rivers are very complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) Discharge and Sediment Load",
            "c) Type of Bed Soil",
            "d) Terrain of the River Basin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Non-Himalayan Rivers are more stable compared to Himalayan Rivers as they flow through non-alluvial rivers. They also pose no risk of a rise in high floods during rainy seasons because these rivers draw their waters from these seasons itself.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "What is the shape of cross section of a straight reach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Circular",
            "c) Trough",
            "d) Trapezoidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sediment which is being carried by the river poses numerous problems like the flood level gets increased, silting occurs in irrigation and navigation channels, meandering of rivers takes place, and the river gets splitted into number of channels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which type of river tends to develop bends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alluvial River",
            "b) Flashy River",
            "c) Virgin River",
            "d) Himalayan River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Meandering of a river causes the river to change its original path and forces them to flow in new courses devastating vast areas of land and damaging nearby irrigation structures like dams, weirs, canals, and other structures like railway lines, and roads etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Where are shoals formed in a bend in a river?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concave Side",
            "b) Convex Side",
            "c) Middle Section of the River",
            "d) At the Bottom of the River Bed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape of cross section of a straight reach is in the shape of a trough, with high speed velocities of flow in the middle of the section.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "The complete formation of which curve leads to the formation of a meander?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal Curve",
            "b) S-Curve",
            "c) Vertical Curve",
            "d) Circular Curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The diagram shows a structure with cross section shape as a trough and the currents in the diagram shows transverse rotary currents, which in turn gives the information that the high velocity flow is in the middle of the section, and water level is high at the ends than at the middle. So, therefore according to this information interpreted the diagram represents a straight reach.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is the name given to the straight reaches between two successive curves in a meander?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cut-Off",
            "b) Meander Belt",
            "c) Crossings",
            "d) Bend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alluvial River tends to form the bends as this type of rivers are always characterised by scouring on the concave side and silting on the convex side. And this scouring and silting action gets continued by the action of centrifugal force in the bend.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "How many numbers of variables govern the meandering process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Velocities at the bottom of the bend are much less than the velocities at the top, and enough centrifugal force is not present to counteract this tendency of water at the top. Due to this the water dives in from the top at the concave side and moves at the bottom towards the convex side. These rotary currents cause erosion at the concave side and deposition at the convex side, forming shoals on the convex side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "What was the initial belief for the meandering process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity of the Flow",
            "b) Excessive Bed Slope",
            "c) Discharge",
            "d) Type of Sediment Load Carried"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When bend is developed in a river, the process moves downstream by the formation of shoals on the convex side with the help of secondary currents. The formation of shoals on the convex side leads further erosion on the concave side. So, therefore formation of successive bends of reverse order leads to complete formation of an s-curve called meander.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Into how many categories the river training works are classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Based on the purpose of the river training works are undertaken, these works are classified into three categories. They are training for discharge, training for depth, and training for sediment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which category of river training work deals with flood control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Training for Sediment",
            "b) Low Water Training",
            "c) Training for Depth",
            "d) Training for Discharge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main aspect of river training works is to confine the flow to the river channel itself and controlling and regulating the river bed configuration which in turn ensures the safe and effective disposal of floods and sediment load. The first and foremost aim of these works is to stabilize and train the river along a certain alignment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which category of river training work helps in navigation of the channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean Water Training",
            "b) Training for Depth",
            "c) Training for Discharge",
            "d) Training for Sediment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This work is undertaken for prime purpose of flood control. It aims to provide sufficient cross section for the safe passage maximum flood and makes the adjoining areas flood proof by construction of levees or dykes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "What is the main aim of mean water training?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective Disposal of Suspended and Bed Loads",
            "b) To Constant Velocity",
            "c) Flood Control",
            "d) Provide Sufficient Water Depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This work is primarily undertaken with the aim of providing adequate depth in the navigable channels even in low water periods. This is done by enhancing the flow in the desired channel by closing other channels by the process of bandalling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "How types of methods are adopted for the training of rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aim of mean water training is to provide effective disposal of suspended and bed loads, and thus preserve the channel in good shape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "How types of groynes are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally seven methods are adopted for training rivers, which includes bank protection. These methods are namely; Levees, Guide Banks, Spurs, Artificial cut-offs, Pitched Islands, Miscellaneous Methods, and Pitching of Banks and provision of launching aprons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Into how many groups groynes are classified according to the function they serve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depending upon the material used for the construction of the groynes, they are classified into two types, namely impermeable groynes and permeable groynes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Into how many groups the gravity weir is sub-divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the material used and certain design features, the gravity weir is sub-divided into three groups. They are vertical drop weir, sloping weir, and parabolic weir. Sloping weir is again classified into two groups, namely masonry slop weir and dry stone slope weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which type of weir is suitable for any type of foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sloping Weir",
            "b) Vertical Drop Weir",
            "c) Parabolic Weir",
            "d) Masonry Sloping Weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In gravity weir, the uplift pressure is due to the seepage of water below the floor and is resisted entirely by the weight of the floor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "What is the main difference between a dam and weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height and Duration of Storage",
            "b) Capacity of Water",
            "c) Material used for Construction",
            "d) Location of the Structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In non-gravity type weir the thickness of the floor is relatively kept less, and the uplift pressure is largely resisted by the bending action of the reinforced concrete floor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "What is the difference between a weir and a barrage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discharge Capacity",
            "b) No Solid Obstruction",
            "c) Storage Capacity",
            "d) Velocity of Flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This type of weir is suitable for kind of foundation because it is provided with or without crest gates, cutoff piles are provided at both upstream and downstream, to protect against scouring aprons are provided at both up and down streams, and at downstream to relieve uplift pressure graded inverted filter is provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "In which type of weir energy dissipation takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barrage",
            "b) Vertical Drop Weir",
            "c) Sloping Weir",
            "d) Parabolic Weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The figure represents a sloping weir made up of dry stone or rock fill. It also represents body walls at both upstream and downstream sides and rock falls laid in the form of glacis with few intervening core walls.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which type of weir is of recent origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical Drop Weir",
            "b) Masonry or Concrete Sloping Weir",
            "c) Parabolic Weir",
            "d) Barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weir is an obstruction across the river to raise its water level and divert into new channel. It can also store water for short duration of time of short supplies, known as storage weir. The only main difference between dam and weir is that dam can store water comparatively for longer duration than weir and the dam is at more height than the weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "What number of causes is responsible for the failure of weirs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Barrage is almost a similar structure like a weir, but the difference is that barrage is not a solid obstruction across a river and moreover the heading of the river is controlled by gates alone. The crest level in barrage is kept at low level. During floods the gates are kept for discharge of excess waters and when the flood recedes the gates are lowered, thus solving the silting problem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "When the weight of the weir balances the uplift pressure caused by the head of water seeping below the weir, it is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gravity weir",
            "b) non-gravity weir",
            "c) vertical drop masonry weir",
            "d) concrete glacis weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Gravity weir, the weight of the weir balances the uplift pressure caused by the seepage water. In non-gravity weirs, the weight of the concrete slab and the divide piers together keep the structure safe against the uplift.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which weir is also called Dry Stone Slope Weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Masonry weir",
            "b) Gravity weir",
            "c) Rock-fill weir",
            "d) Concrete weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rock-fill weir is also called Dry Stone Slope Weir. It is the simplest type of construction and is economical only when the stone is easily available. This type of weir is also becoming obsolete with the development of concrete glacis weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Which type of weir is suitable for hard clay and consolidated gravel foundations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity weir",
            "b) Non-gravity weir",
            "c) Masonry weir with a vertical drop",
            "d) Rock-fill weirs with sloping aprons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This type of weir was used in all the old head-works and is particularly suitable for hard clay and consolidated gravel foundations. Masonry weir is becoming obsolete and all the modern constructions are done by the modern concrete weirs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which weir is of recent origin and their design is based on modern concepts of sub-surface flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity weir",
            "b) Non-gravity weir",
            "c) Masonry dam with a vertical drop",
            "d) Concrete weir with sloping glacis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design of concrete weir with sloping glacis is based on the modern concepts of sub-surface flow i.e. Khosla’s theory. Sheet piles are driven at sufficient depths at the upstream and downstream floor end. The hydraulic jump is formed on the downstream sloping glacis to dissipate the energy of the flowing water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Which weir is now extensively used especially on pervious foundations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical drop masonry weir",
            "b) Rock-fill weirs with sloping aprons",
            "c) Concrete weirs with sloping glacis",
            "d) Non-gravity weirs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Modern concrete weirs with sloping downstream glacis are generally provided with low crest counter-balanced gates. This is now exclusively used on permeable foundations. Masonry weirs are suitable for hard clay and gravel foundations. Rock-fill weir is suitable for fine sandy foundations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about Non-gravity weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The weir floor is designed continuous with the divide piers as a reinforced structure",
            "b) The weight of the concrete slab balances the uplift pressure",
            "c) The weight of the divide piers also keep the structure against uplift",
            "d) Brick piers have to be used in place of RCC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The weir floor and divide-pier are designed as a reinforced structure continuously. The RCC has to be used in place of brick piers and as the weight of the floor can be much less than that of gravity weir, considerable savings are obtained.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Into how many components the diversion headwork is divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diversion head work is generally divided into eight component parts, namely weir, divide wall, fish ladder, pocket or approach ladder, scouring sluices, silt prevention devices, canal head regulator, and river training works."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "In order to find the proper location for the head works on the river, the river is divided into how many stages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to find an appropriate location for the head work on the river, the river is divided into four stages. They are mountainous stage, boulder stage, alluvial plain, and delta stage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "By constructing which structure we can help the fish in their migration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scouring Sluices",
            "b) Silt Excluder",
            "c) Fish Ladder",
            "d) Divide Wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The figure represents the plan of a fish ladder installed in the channel, where the water comes to the channel from end and leaves it at the other end. Baffle walls are also provided in the path to control the silt and sediment load and also the velocity of the flow, thus helping the fish.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "What device is placed in front of head regulator for silt removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weir",
            "b) Silt Extractor",
            "c) Silt Excluder",
            "d) Barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If perhaps divide wall is not provided then the currents approach the scouring sluices from all directions and their effectiveness is reduced. Thus the dividing wall helps in concentrating the scouring action of the under sluices from washing out the silt deposited in the pocket.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which device is used for silt removal after it enters the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silt Excluder",
            "b) Silt Ejector",
            "c) Weir",
            "d) Barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the name itself suggests (regulator) head regulator helps in regulating the supply of flow easy in a canal, controls silt entry into the canal, and shut river floods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Depending on how many considerations the capacity of under sluices is fixed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Before the start of monsoons the fish migrate to the upstream in search of warm water. So, therefore some provision is made to make some space available for them to travel. And this achieved by the construction of fish ladder as they provide the room for movement and also slows down the flow for easy traveling of fish.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "How many river training works are needed on the canal head works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silt excluder is placed in front of the head regulator by which the silt is removed from the water even before the water enters the canal. The fundamental principle on which this device acts is the fact that stream carrying silt in suspension, the concentration of silt charge is more in upper layers than in lower layers. Therefore this device is so designed for separating these two layers without disturbance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "When the depth is small, the name for the jump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undular Jump",
            "b) Direct Jump",
            "c) Strong Jump",
            "d) Oscillating Jump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Whenever the jump is small the water shall not rise suddenly but will pass through a number of undulations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "For what limits of Froude number, the jump is said to be weak jump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.1 to 2.4",
            "b) 1.9 to 2.9",
            "c) 1.5 to 2.2",
            "d) 1.7 to 2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In certain cases when the jump is high, then the difference in a jump is large and it occurs suddenly or abruptly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "How many assumptions are made for the derivation of momentum formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Froude number from 1.7 to 2.5 a series of rollers develop on the surface of the jump, but at the downstream side the surface is smooth. The energy loss is low and a uniform velocity is maintained. The jump under these conditions is called a weak jump.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Depending upon the Froude number, into how many groups the jumps are classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the value of Froude number is 9 or more, then the energy dissipation reaches up to 85% in the flow. The jump under this condition is called strong jump.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "On which surface the energy dissipation is less efficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal Bed",
            "b) Freeboard",
            "c) Level Floor",
            "d) Sloping Glacis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the derivation of momentum formula four assumptions are made. Namely, the jump happens abruptly, friction is negligible, bed is horizontal, and flow is streamlined.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "The length of the jump is how times the height of the jump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According the values of Froude number (F1) the jumps are classified into six groups. Namely, no jump for F1 = 1, for F1 = 1 to 1.7 the jump is undular jump, for F1 = 1.7 to 2.5 the jump is weak jump, for F1  = 2.5 to 4.5 the jump is oscillating jump, for F1 = 4.5 to 9 the jump is steady jump, and for F1 = 9 or above the jump is strong jump.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "In what limits the slopes of the glacis are provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2:1 to 5:1",
            "b) 3:1 to 4:1",
            "c) 5:2 to 6:2",
            "d) 4:3 to 7:5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: On sloping glacis, there is less energy dissipation because the vertical component of velocity remains intact. And when a jump happens only the horizontal component of velocity impact the glacis and vertical component remains unaffected.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "For what value of Froude number the jump is steady jump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F1 = 1",
            "b) F1 = 1.7 to 4.5",
            "c) F1 = 4.5 to 9",
            "d) F1 = 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally the length of the hydraulic jump is calculated in a region where there is a heavy turbulence and it is found to be five times the height of the jump.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What are the two main causes of failure of hydraulic structure on the pervious foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seepage and Over-turning",
            "b) Undermining and Uplift",
            "c) Over-turning and Piping",
            "d) Overturning and Uplift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Whenever a hydraulic structure is founded on a pervious foundation, it is subjected to seepage of water beneath the structure in addition to all other forces. The water seeping below endangers the stability of the structure and may cause its failure either by Piping or Undermining and Direct uplift.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The structure finally subsides in the hollow formed in the foundation in which failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collapse",
            "b) Overturning",
            "c) Undermining",
            "d) Uplift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the apron is not sufficiently strong to counteract the excessive upward pressure, it may fail by rupture. The uplift pressure is not important for an upstream apron because the downward weight of stored water on the upstream apron is sufficient to neutralize the effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Heave piping may occur on the _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) downstream of sheet pile or cut off wall",
            "b) upstream of sheet pile or cut off wall",
            "c) body of earth structure",
            "d) below the foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Undermining takes place due to excessive percolation of water under pressure below the foundation. The seepage water when retains a sufficient residual force at the emerging downstream end, it may dislodge and lift up the soil particles leading to the increased porosity by progressive removal of the soil. This leads to the failure of the structure as it ultimately subsides in the hollow so formed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "What is the value of Bligh’s coefficient for coarse-grained soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 5 to 9",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of Bligh’s creep coefficient (C) is different for different soil.\n\n\nS.No.\nType of soil\nValue of C\n\n\n1.\nMicaceous sand\n15\n\n\n2.\nCoarse-grained soil \n12\n\n\n3.\nSand mixed with boulder and gravel and for loam soil\n5 to 9\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "For sand mixed with boulder and gravel and for loam soil, the safe hydraulic gradient should be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/15",
            "b) 1/12",
            "c) 1/5 to 1/9",
            "d) 1/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For Micaceous sand, the safe hydraulic gradient is less than 1/15 and for Coarse-grained soil is 1/12. For light sand and mud, the safe hydraulic gradient should be less than 1/8.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a limitation of creep theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No distinction between the vertical and horizontal creep",
            "b) No distinction between effectiveness of outer and inner faces of sheet pile",
            "c) Significance of exit gradient is not considered",
            "d) Only a nominal floor thickness is required on the upstream side so as to resist water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The thickness is generally increased by 33% so as to allow a suitable factor of safety. The water on the upstream side is more than the downstream side and it counterbalances the uplift caused on that side. Hence, only a nominal thickness is required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "If the value of Bligh’s coefficient for a particular soil is equal to 12 then, what is the safe hydraulic gradient for that soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/12",
            "b) 1/9",
            "c) 1/15",
            "d) 1/5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydraulic gradient i.e. HL/L is equal to the coefficient of creep 1/C.\nBligh’s coefficient = 12\nSo, safe hydraulic gradient = 1/12.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "As per Bligh’s theory, thickness to be provided by taking a factor of safety equal to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2/3",
            "b) 4/3",
            "c) 1/3",
            "d) 1/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The worst condition is that when the water level on U/s side is maximum and no water on D/s side. It would be more economical to provide more creep length on U/s side instead of D/s side. A vertical cut-off at U/s end is more useful than at the D/s end of the floor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "In Lane’s weighted creep theory, he suggested a weightage factor _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/3 for horizontal creep and 1.0 for vertical creep",
            "b) 1/3 for vertical creep and 1.0 for horizontal creep",
            "c) 2/3 for horizontal creep and 1/3 for horizontal creep",
            "d) 2/3 for vertical creep and 1/3 for horizontal creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: He proposed that horizontal creep has less head and is less effective in reducing uplift than vertical creep. A weightage factor of 1/3 is proposed for horizontal creep and 1.0 for vertical creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following limitation of Bligh’s theory forms the basis of Lane’s creep theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No distinction between the vertical and horizontal creep",
            "b) No distinction between effectiveness of outer and inner faces of sheet pile",
            "c) Significance of exit gradient is not considered",
            "d) Bligh’s theory holds good when the length of the horizontal floor is greater than or equal to twice the depth of the deepest pile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A weightage factor of 1/3 is proposed by Lane for horizontal creep and 1.0 for vertical creep. The weighted creep length –\nL = (1/3) B + V where B = sum of horizontal contacts and sloping contacts less than 45° to the horizontal and V = sum of vertical contacts and sloping contacts greater than 45° to the horizontal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "What is the value of Lane’s coefficient for fine sand and coarse sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 and 5",
            "b) 5 and 7",
            "c) 7 and 8.5",
            "d) 7 and 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bligh calculated the total length of creep by adding the vertical and horizontal creep together. Lane proposed horizontal creep is less effective in reducing uplift and introduced the weightage factor for the same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "What is the range of Lane’s coefficient for clayey soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0 to 3.5",
            "b) 2.5 to 3.0",
            "c) 1.6 to 3.0",
            "d) > 3.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For very fine sand or silt, the value of Lane’s coefficient is 8.5. For fine sand and coarse sand, the value is 7.0 and 5.0 respectively. Also, the safe hydraulic gradient should be less than 1/7 and 1/5 for fine sand and coarse sand respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is the path represented by the streamlines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic Jump",
            "b) Flow Net",
            "c) Energy Dissipation",
            "d) Water Flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The laplacian equation represents two sets of curves, namely one set of lines called streamlines and the other set called equipotential lines. These two sets of lines intersect orthogonally. The resultant flow diagram of these two sets is a flow net.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "How many corrections are needed for the complex profile broken from simple forms, to be valid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The streamlines represent a path along which the water flows through the subsoil. Every particle entering the upstream will trace its own path and represents its own streamline.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "By how many considerations the depth downstream vertical cutoff is governed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The corrections needed are correction for mutual interference of piles, correction for thickness of floor, and correction for slope of the floor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "What is laplacian equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) d2φ / dx2 + d2Φ/dz2",
            "b) d2Φ / dx2 + d2Φ/dz2",
            "c) dΦ / dx + d2Φ/dy2",
            "d) d2φ / dx2 + d2Φ/dz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to prevent undermining, it is absolutely necessary to provide a reasonably deep vertical cutoff at the downstream end of the downstream pucca floor. The depth of this downstream vertical cutoff is governed by two considerations, namely maximum depth of scour and safe exit gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "What type of points is needed to be joined to form an equipotential line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal Pressure Points",
            "b) Residual Heads which still need Energy Dissipation",
            "c) Velocity Gradient Points",
            "d) Points of intersection of Streamlines and Velocity Components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flow nets proposed by the khosla’s theory says that the loss head depends upon the whole geometry of the figure, that is the shape of foundation, depth of impervious boundary and levels of upstream and downstream beds. If the equipotential lines are traced closer, then the loss of head is fast and vice versa.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "The component of which force is to be counterbalanced so that the soil grains remain stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upthrust Pressure Forces",
            "b) Forces due to Velocity Components",
            "c) Pressure Force",
            "d) Seepage Water Force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The laplacian equation is based on Φ(flow potential) which is a combination of flow potential Kh, where K is coefficient of permeability of soil and h is residual head at any point. The equation is represented as d2Φ/dx2 + d2Φ/dz2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "What is the name of the gradient pressure at the exit end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient of Pressure",
            "b) Exit Gradient",
            "c) Streamline Gradient",
            "d) Equipotential Gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streamlines enter from the upstream with some head (H), but in case of equipotential lines it is considered that in downstream side water is not present. So, even though energy dissipation takes place there will some residual head (h) will be present at certain points on the streamlines. Therefore, joining these points together forms an equipotential line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which method is evolved by khosla for designing of hydraulic structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Method of Gradients",
            "b) Method of Variables",
            "c) Method of Independent Variables",
            "d) Method of Flow Nets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The seepage water exerts a force tangential to the streamlines at each point in the direction of the flow. This force, when resolved has an upward component from point 5, where the streamline turns upward. So, therefore in order to keep the soil grains stable the upward component of this force should be counterbalanced by the submerged weight of the soil grain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the upstream apron length according to Bligh?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.208 (CH)1/2",
            "b) 2.208 (H/13)1/2",
            "c) 2.208 (H)1/2",
            "d) 2.208 (C/H)1/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The upstream apron length according to Bligh is 2.208 (CH)1/2, where C is the creep coefficient and H is the head of water against the weir. The downstream apron length is given by 2.208 (H/13)1/2 which should be sufficient to withstand uplift pressures below it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "What is the empirical formula given by Bligh for the design of the top width of the weir wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B’ = H / (G-1)",
            "b) B’ = H / (G-1)1/2",
            "c) B’ = (H + height of weir)/G",
            "d) B’ = H / (G+1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Bligh, the top width of weir wall (B’) is given by H / (G-1)1/2 where H is head of water over the weir wall at the time of maximum flood and G is the specific gravity of floor material. The top width generally varies from 1.5 m to 1.8 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "What is the correct calculation for balance floor length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total length – (the downstream length + twice the cut-off length)",
            "b) Total length + (the downstream length + twice the cut-off length)",
            "c) The downstream length – twice the cut-off length",
            "d) The downstream length + twice the cut-off length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to prevent the scour from reaching the pucca floor, upstream and downstream aprons are provided and the length of these aprons are put forward by Bligh’s formulas. The cut-off is provided by Khosla’s theory and then the balance floor length is provided under the crest and on the upstream side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "The ordinate of the uplift pressure at a point is found to be 2.8 m while designing the downstream floor thickness of a weir. If the relative density of concrete is 2.4 then the minimum thickness of the floor to be provided for resisting uplift pressure without accounting safety factor is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.16 m",
            "b) 2 m",
            "c) 0.8 m",
            "d) 2.8 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: D/s floor thickness is given by (Neglecting the factor of safety value = 4/3)\nt = h / (G-1) where h = 2.8 m and G = 2.4\nt = 2.8 / 1.4 = 2 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The minimum thickness (t) of the downstream floor required in the design of weir can be expressed by the equation ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) h / (G+1)",
            "b) (h-t) / (G-1)",
            "c) h / (G-1)",
            "d) 1.33 h /(G-1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per Bligh’s theory, the thickness of D/s floor is expressed as h/(G-1) where h = ordinate of the H.G line above the top of the floor and G is the specific gravity of the floor material. To allow a suitable F.O.S  this value is generally increased by 33%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "The width provided at the site for the river to flow and also the length of the weir is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) waterway",
            "b) launching apron",
            "c) top width",
            "d) bed mean width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Waterway is provided between the abutments of a weir for river water to flow. It is also the length of the weir and may be calculated from Lacey’s regime perimeter formula. The weir length is generally increased to avoid the risk of overtopping of the training works.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "BY increasing the length of the floor on the upstream of the weir axis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the uplift pressure will increase below the floor downstream of the weir",
            "b) the uplift pressure will decrease below the floor downstream of the weir",
            "c) the uplift pressure will remain the same in both cases",
            "d) the uplift pressure may increase or decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of upstream cutoffs has a considerable effect on decreasing the uplift pressure especially from a value of 1 m to 2 m. The provision of sheet pile at the U/s end and sufficient thickness of floor resists the uplift pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Calculate the length of the downstream floor for a vertical drop weir having crest shutters, if the total maximum head loss is 2.5 m. Assume the value of Bligh’s constant as 12.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.62 m",
            "b) 11.80 m",
            "c) 12 m",
            "d) 10 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Total max. head loss (HL) = 2.5 m and C = 12\nAs per Bligh, the length of D/s floor with crest shutters is given by –\nL2 = 2.21 C (HL/13)1/2 = 11.62 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Calculate the top width of the weir wall (B’) if the head of the water over the weir wall at the time of the maximum flood is 2 m. Take the specific gravity of the floor material as 2.4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7 m",
            "b) 2 m",
            "c) 2.4 m",
            "d) 1.3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per Bligh, the top width of the weir wall (B’) is given by B’ = H / (G-1)1/2.\nGiven G = 2.4 and H = 2 m\nB’ = 2 / (2.4-1)1/2 = 1.69 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Calculate the length of upstream talus if the length of the downstream loose stone talus is 20 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 m",
            "b) 10 m",
            "c) 40 m",
            "d) 15 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For designing the proper weir portion, the length of upstream talus (L4) is kept equal to half the length of D/s talus.\nGiven the length of loose D/s talus = 20 m\nThe length of upstream talus = 20/2 = 10 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Into how groups the design of a barrage is divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The complete design of a barrage or a modern glacis weir is divided into two groups, namely hydraulic design and structural design.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "How many types of aspects are determined by using the hydraulic design in design for a weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a hydraulic design is used for a weir on the permeable foundations, then the design is classified into two aspects, namely design for subsurface flow and design for surface flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Which factor should be kept in safe limits to avoid failure of structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seeping Pressure",
            "b) Exit Gradient",
            "c) Side Slopes",
            "d) Velocity of Flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The hydraulic design of a weir involves determining the section of the weir, details of upstream cutoff, crest, glacis, floor, downstream cutoff, and protection works of upstream and downstream.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "By how many factors the design of protection works is based?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The method of independent variables given by Khosla can be used to determine the uplift pressures exerted by the seeping water on the floor of the weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "The inverted filter used in protection arrangement, protects the weir from what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silting Action",
            "b) Scouring",
            "c) Piping",
            "d) Leakage Problems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To ensure the safety of the structure or to say to protect the structure from failure due to piping, the exit gradient should be kept within the safe limits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "How many factors govern the design a weir or a barrage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The protection works are needed both on the upstream and downstream side to prevent the scour hole which is travelling close to the pucca floor of the weir and to relieve the uplift pressure. So, in order to achieve this, the protection arrangement consists of an inverted filter and launching apron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "On par with retrogression factor, how many other certain factors are to be considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It helps in reducing the possibility of piping by allowing the flow of seepage water through it, without allowing the foundation soils to be lifted up. Therefore the filter consists of layers of materials of increasing permeability from bottom to top.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "What is the name given to the first effect created by the construction of a weir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crest Damage",
            "b) Afflux",
            "c) Scouring",
            "d) Retrogression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The information or rather say the data pertaining to these factors, namely high flood levels for the river at the weir site, river cross section at the weir site, stage discharge curve at the weir site, and maximum flood discharge for the river at the weir site are to be collected before designing a weir or  barrage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "What is the basic cause of retrogression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flood Levels",
            "b) Seepage Pressure",
            "c) Silt Carrying Capacity",
            "d) Fault in the Design of Protection Works"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Apart from retrogression, other factors like crest levels, afflux, waterway and discharge per meter, and pond level are to be decided while designing a weir or a barrage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which famous barrage is built across the River Ganges in West Bengal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Durgapur barrage",
            "b) Damodar barrage",
            "c) Farraka barrage",
            "d) Bhimgoda barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Farraka barrage is 2.2 km long and carries a rail-cum-road bridge across the river Ganges in the state of West Bengal. Durgapur barrage is also situated on West Bengal but on Damodar River.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which barrage is built across the River Krishna?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grand Anicut",
            "b) Prakasam barrage",
            "c) Jobra barrage",
            "d) Ottakal pick-up weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Prakasam barrage is situated in the Vijayawada in Andhra-Pradesh on Krishna River serving the irrigation needs of adjoining areas. This is a 1.2 km long river road bridge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which barrage is situated near the longest river bridge in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jobra barrage",
            "b) Shah Nehar barrage",
            "c) New Okhla barrage",
            "d) Bhimgoda barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jobra barrage is also known as Mahanadi barrage and is built across the River Mahanadi near Cuttack in Orissa. This is 2 km long road bridge and is situated near the longest river bridge, the Mahanadi road bridge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Which of the following barrage is the last stretch of Godavari River before it drains into the Bay of Bengal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bhimgoda barrage",
            "b) Mahanadi barrage",
            "c) Dowleswaram barrage",
            "d) Prakasam barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dowleswaram barrage is 3.4 km long and is built across the River Godavari in the Godavari districts of Andhra Pradesh. This is located near Rajamundry city where the Godavari divided into two streams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "The famous Grand Anicut barrage is located on _______________ river.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Krishna",
            "b) Cauvery",
            "c) Godavari",
            "d) Mahanadi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is located on the Cauvery river from Tamil Nadu state and is situated 193 km downstream of the famous Mettur Dam near Salem. The design flood discharge is 1.8 cusecs serving the irrigation needs of the adjoining areas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following barrage has the highest design flood discharge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Durgapur barrage",
            "b) Bhimgoda barrage",
            "c) Prakasam barrage",
            "d) Tajewala barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design flood discharge of the Prakasam barrage is as high as 33,984 cumecs. It serves three major canals that run through the entire city of Vijayawada. The design flood discharge of other barrages are-\ni. Durgapur barrage – 15,576 cumecs\nii. Bhimgoda barrage – 19,300 cumecs\niii. Tajewala barrage – 10,024 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which barrage replaced the Tajewala barrage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Farakka barrage",
            "b) Hathni kund barrage",
            "c) Kota barrage",
            "d) Shah Nehar barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Hathni Kund is a concrete barrage situated on the Yamuna River in Haryana and it replaced the Tajewala Barrage in 1999 which is out of service now. It diverts water into the Western and Eastern Yamuna Canals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The Ganges Treaty between India and Bangladesh is an agreement to share surface waters at the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Farakka Barrage",
            "b) Hathni Kund barrage",
            "c) Mahanadi Barrage",
            "d) Durgapur barrage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The treaty was signed in 1996 established a 30-year water-sharing agreement. This was done in order to share surface waters at the Farakka barrage near their mutual border.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Pick up the incorrect one.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ottakkal barrage – Cauvery River",
            "b) Tajewala barrage – Yamuna River",
            "c) Shah Nehar barrage – Beas River",
            "d) Grand Anicut – Cauvery River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a pick-up weir located at Ottakkal in Kerala state on Kallada River. The design flood discharge is 2830 cumecs. It is one of the major points of Kallada irrigation project constructed in order to increase the water level in order to make the river more navigable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following best the Hirakud reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The purpose is Recreation and fishery",
            "b) Reservoir for irrigation and water supply",
            "c) Reservoir for flood control, power, and irrigation",
            "d) Reservoir for irrigation and power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is one of the first major multipurpose river valley projects and is built across the Mahanadi River in Orissa. The dam was constructed to regulate the flow of the river and produce hydroelectricity through several plants. It irrigates almost 75,000 km2 of land.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "On what term does the construction of a fall in the case of the main canal depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discharge Capacity of the Canal",
            "b) Length of the Canal",
            "c) Topography",
            "d) Cost of Excavation and Filling versus Cost of fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the available natural slope is steeper than the bed slope of the canal, then this is adjusted by the construction of vertical falls or drops in the canal bed at suitable intervals. But such a drop will not be stable, therefore in order to maintain this drop a masonry structure is constructed. This is known as canal fall or canal drop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "On what factor in case of branch canals, the construction site for a fall depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost of Excavation",
            "b) Topography",
            "c) Commanded Area",
            "d) Cost of fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main does not irrigate any area directly, so therefore the site of the fall is based on the considerations of economy in cost of excavation and filling versus cost of fall. The excavation and filling on both sides of the fall should be balanced because unbalanced work causes extra cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "How many types of falls are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By considering the commanded area of a branch canal or a distributary canal the location for the falls is decided. The procedure is to fix the FSL needed at the head of the off taking channels and outlets. Thus the FSL can be marked at all commanded points and hence deciding appropriate locations for the falls in canal FSL and therefore in canal beds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "What number of major defects does the ogee fall have?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the idea of the construction of falls various types of falls have been designed. Some important falls are ogee falls, rapids, trapezoidal notch falls, simple vertical drop type and sarda type falls, straight glacis falls, Montague type falls and inglis falls.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "In which fall the depth discharge relationship is unaffected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trapezoidal Notch Fall",
            "b) Ogee Fall",
            "c) Rapids",
            "d) Straight Glacis Fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diagram gives clear image that in this fall a high crested fall takes place into the water cushion below. There is no clear hydraulic jump or energy dissipation, as the velocity jet enters the deep pool of downstream. Hence it is a simple vertical drop type fall.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which type of fall is suitable for 60 cumecs discharge and 1.5 m drop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Montague Type Fall",
            "b) Rapids",
            "c) Straight Glacis Fall",
            "d) Baffle Fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diagram shows that water is gradually led down the convex and concave curves. It also shows the draw down on the upstream side which results in lower depths, higher velocities and subsequent soil erosion. The curves provide smooth surfaces which results in less energy dissipation, which again causes soil erosion. Hence the diagram is ogee fall type.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is the reason for the construction of baffle wall in baffle fall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To Maintain Uniform Velocity Flow",
            "b) To Ensure Formation of Jump",
            "c) To Reduce Soil Erosion",
            "d) To Ensure Uniform Discharge of the Flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ogee fall has two major defects. Heavy drawdown occurs on the upstream side, which results in lower depths, higher velocities and bed erosion. The kinetic energy of the flow will not be dissipated due to smooth transition, causing erosion on downstream bed and banks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which type of fall is not adopted in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ogee Fall",
            "b) Rapids",
            "c) Inglis Fall",
            "d) Montague Type Fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this fall the notches could be designed to maintain the normal water depth in the upstream channel at any two discharges, as the intermediate values do not vary much. Therefore the depth discharge relationship of the channel is not affected by the introduction of the fall.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Canal drops are provided to _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dissipate the excess energy",
            "b) increase the driving head of flow of water",
            "c) dissipate excess land slope",
            "d) dissipate inadequate land slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: when a canal fall or drop is provided at a suitable section, it brings down the canal bed line. In this process, water comes down with a great force and all the potential energy is converted into kinetic energy. The excess energy of the flow is destroyed with some suitable energy dissipation method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "In case of branch canals and distributary channels, the falls are located with consideration to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) command area",
            "b) topography",
            "c) cost economy",
            "d) availability of earth material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is done in case of branch canals and distributary channels which irrigate the area directly, the FSL is fixed and marked at the head of the off-taking channel and outlets. In the case of the main canal which does not irrigate the area directly, the site of the fall is determined by considerations of economy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "By providing a natural drop in one drop _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the quantity of unbalanced earthwork decreases",
            "b) the quantity of unbalanced earthwork increases",
            "c) the quantity of balanced earthwork increases",
            "d) number of fall increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of branch canals and distributary canals, the procedure is to mark the FSL required on the L-section of the canal. It is done so as to cover all the commanded points that decide the suitable locations for fall in canal FSL and in canal beds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "______________ fall is adopted for smaller discharges and larger drops.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ogee fall",
            "b) Sarda fall",
            "c) Glacis fall",
            "d) Well-type fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  A Cylinder fall popularly known as Syphon or Well-Type fall is useful for affecting larger drops and for small discharges. They are commonly used where high levelled small drains do outfall into low levelled bigger drains and also as tail escapes for small canals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Calculate the velocity over the notch (V1) and the velocity through the pipe (V3) if the full supply discharge is 2 cumecs. The area of flow over the trapezoidal notch is 0.58 m2. Assume the value of diameter of the pipe used as 1 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) V1 = 3.44 m/sec and V3 = 2.54 m/sec",
            "b) V1 = 2.54 m/sec and V3 = 3.44 m/sec",
            "c) V1 = 3.44 m/sec and V3 = 3.44 m/sec",
            "d) V1 = 0.44 m/sec and V3 = 2.04 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design discharge of a notch fall is obtained by adding the discharge of rectangular and V-notch i.e. trapezoidal notch taking the value of the coefficient of the discharge as 0.75. The notches are designed by taking into consideration full supply discharge and half supply discharge w.r.t normal water depths in the channel in both cases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What is the height of the centre of pressure above the water level in the inlet well if the R.L of the centre of pressure is 150.83 m and the R.L of water level in inlet well is 148.30 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.53 m",
            "b) 1.78 m",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 1.99 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity over the notch (V1) = full supply discharge / Area over the notch and the velocity through the pipe (V3) = Full supply discharge / Area of pipe.\nV1 = 2/0.58 = 3.44 m/sec\nV3 = 2/0.785 = 2.54 m/sec (Area of pipe = 0.785 m2).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Calculate the diameter of the inlet well if the X and Y coordinate of the jet (issuing from the centre of pressure) w.r.t the water surface in the inlet well is 1.05 m and 1.88 m respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.575 m",
            "b) 2.82 m",
            "c) 1.79 m",
            "d) 0.83 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height of the centre of pressure (Y) above the water level in the inlet well is given by –\nY = R.L of C.P – R.L of water level in inlet well\nY = 150.83 – 148.30\nY = 2.53 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following loss is not considered while calculating the total head loss between the inlet well and D/s FSL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Entry and exit losses",
            "b) Loss due to friction",
            "c) Loss due to enlargement of the section",
            "d) Loss due to contraction of section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diameter of the inlet well is kept as 1.5 times the value of X.\nGiven, X = 1.05 and Y = 1.88\nDiameter = 1.5 x 1.05 = 1.575 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "The discharge formula used in the design of the syphon well drop is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8/15 Cd. (2g)1/2. tan (Q/2). H5/2",
            "b) 2/3 Cd. (2g)1/2. L. H3/2",
            "c) 8/15 Cd. (2g)1/2. tan (Q/2). H3/2",
            "d) 2.22H3/2 [L + 0.4nH]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The head loss between the inlet well and the D/s FSL is given by adding the losses due to entry, exit, loss due to sudden enlargement and loss due to friction in the pipe.\nHL = 0.5 V22/2g (Entry loss) + (V2 – V3)2/2g (sudden enlargement loss) + fLV32/2gd (Friction loss) + V32/2g (Exit loss)\nWhere, V2 = Velocity of entry in pipe, V3 = Velocity through the pipe, L = assumed pipe length, d = diameter of the pipe, f = Darcy’s coefficient of friction = 0.012 and g = acceleration due to gravity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In a trapezoidal notch fall, the top width of the notch is kept between 3/4th to full water depth above the sill of the notch",
            "b) The syphon fall is designed to maintain a fixed supply level in the channel",
            "c) A cylinder fall is popularly known as syphon well drop",
            "d) Energy dissipators are provided for small discharges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The discharge passing through a trapezoidal notch is given by adding the discharge of a rectangular notch and V-notch which is given by-\nQ = 2/3 Cd. (2g)1/2. L. H3/2 + 8/15 Cd. (2g)1/2. tan (Q/2). H5/2\nQ = 2.22H3/2 [L + 0.4nH] \n(Where n = 2 tan (Q/2) and coefficient of discharge = 0.75).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "In what intervals the top width of the notch lies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2 to full water depth",
            "b) 3/4 to full water depth",
            "c) Full water depth",
            "d) 1/4 to full water depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally the number of notches is adjusted by hit and trial method. The width of the notch lies between 3/4 to full water depth above the sill of the notch.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "By what value the thickness of notch pier should not be less than the water depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One fourth of water depth",
            "b) Equal to water depth",
            "c) Half the water depth",
            "d) Three fourth of the water depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The thickness of the notch pier should not less than half of the water depth and even it can be more when the pier has to carry a superstructure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "In case of design of sarda type fall the length of crest is kept equal to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thickness of the Canal",
            "b) bed Width of the Canal",
            "c) water Depth in the Canal",
            "d) hydraulic Jump on the fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this type when the notch is provided there is heading up or drawdown of water level in the canal near the fall. Therefore the whole width of the canal is divided into number of notches. The crest is kept higher than the bed level of the canal, but in no case the total length of the weir will not exceed the bed width of the canal upstream.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "What is formula used to determine the crest level while designing a sarda type fall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x L x H3/2 x (H/Bt)1/6",
            "b) Q = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x L x H3/4 x (H/Bt)1/4",
            "c) Q = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x L x H1/4 x (H/Bt)1/8",
            "d) Q = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x L x H x (H/Bt)1/6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this case of designing a sarda type fall fluming is not possible, therefore the length of the crest is kept equal to the bed width of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "What is the height of the baffle wall in case of designing inglis fall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hb = yc",
            "b) hb = y – y1",
            "c) hb = y1",
            "d) hb = yc – y1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the discharge level is under 14 cumecs rectangular crest is used. The top width is 0.55√d and base width is (h+d)/G (G = 2 for masonry). If the discharge is more than 14 cumecs then trapezoidal crest is used. Top width is equal to 0.55\\(\\sqrt{(H+d)}\\) with upstream slope is 1: 3 and downstream slope is 1 : 8.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "What is the shape of upstream wings in design of baffle fall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trapezoidal",
            "b) Rectangular",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Discharge formula is used to determine the crest level.\nQ = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x L x H3/2 x (H/Bt)1/6, where Cd = 0.415 for rectangular crest and 0.45 for trapezoidal crest, L = length of crest, Bt = Top width of crest, height of crest above bed = y – H, y = normal depth of channel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "What type of crest width is provided in designing a straight glacis fall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deep Crest",
            "b) Shallow Crest",
            "c) Broad Crest",
            "d) Narrow Crest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The height of the baffle wall is given by hb = yc – y1 , where yc = critical depth given by yc = (q2/g)1/3 and y1 = 0.183 x q0.89 x HX-0.35 (HX = HL when no fluming)\nThickness of the baffle wall is 2/3hb and length of baffle wall is 5.25hb.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "The discharge value of water is controlled by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic Jump",
            "b) Falls",
            "c) Regulators",
            "d) Velocity of the flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water enters the main canal from the river and this water has to be divided into different branches, distributaries in accordance to the relative demand on these different channels. Therefore this process of distribution of water is called as canal distribution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "How many types of canal irrigation works are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The discharge value of water has to be adjusted to any value necessary to distribute the water effectively. This is done with the help of regulators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "How many main functions of a head regulator are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Canal regulation works are the structures constructed in order to control and regulate the discharges, depths, and velocities in the canals. These structures ensure the efficient functioning of the irrigation canal system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "How many numbers of conditions of flow are to be followed while designing the cross regulator and head regulator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are five types of canal irrigation works, namely canal falls, canal regulators, canal escapes, metering flumes, and canal outlets and modules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "By what structures the regulator can control the supplies entering the off take channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sluice Gates",
            "b) Falls",
            "c) Piers and Planks",
            "d) Dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This off taking channel makes a zero angle with parent channel initially and then separates out in transition. This is the best ideal alignment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "What is the main purpose of the canal escape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To Maintain Uniform Flow in the Canal",
            "b) To Remove Surplus Water",
            "c) To Maintain Constant Velocity of the Flow",
            "d) To Help for Proper Hydraulic Jump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The canal escape is a side channel constructed to remove surplus amounts of water from an irrigation channel such as main canal, branch canal, distributary canal etc into the natural drain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a reason for surplus water present in a canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No Fall",
            "b) No Proper Hydraulic Jump",
            "c) No Proper Uniform Velocity of Flow",
            "d) Cultivators closing their outlets thinking their demand is over"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The presence of the surplus amount of water in canal can be due to difficulty in regulation at the head or due to heavy rainfall or due to cultivators closing their outlets suddenly thinking that the demand of water is over.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "What is the other name for canal escape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canal Outlet",
            "b) Escape",
            "c) Surplus Water Escape",
            "d) Canal Inlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to reasons for surplus amount of water to be present in the canal, the supplies shall be reduced or stopped from the head works. Therefore in order to avoid this damage immediate action is needed. This can be achieved by the means of an escape generally called surplus water escape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "What type of escape is preferred these days?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weir Type Escape",
            "b) Venturi Flume",
            "c) Regular Type Escape",
            "d) Tail Escape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case if a breach occurs in a canal then immediate information is sent to the head to close the canal supplies immediately. But the water present from head to breach will cause damage if passed through the breach. So, therefore the escape existing on the upstream of the breach is opened to allow the water through the escape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "What is the other name given to weir type escape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surplus Water Escape",
            "b) Venturi Flume",
            "c) Tail Escape",
            "d) Scouring Escape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To minimize the damage from a breach or any such leakages causing surplus of water to be present in the canal the canal escapes should be present at regular intervals depending upon the importance of the channel and it’s availability of a suitable drainage for the disposal of the escaped water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of the regulator type escape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To Remove Excess Silt",
            "b) To Maintain Uniform Flow in the Canal",
            "c) To Perform Proper Hydraulic Jump",
            "d) For Distribution of Discharge for the Canals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this type of escape the crest of the weir wall is kept at RL equal to canal FSL. When the water level rises up FSL it gets escaped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Scouring escapes have become obsolete because of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piers",
            "b) Weir Walls",
            "c) Falls",
            "d) Silt Ejectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this type of escape the flow is controlled by gates and the sill of the escape is kept at bed level. These types of escape give better control and can be used for completely emptying the canal. Hence these types of escapes are preferred these days.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "For what purpose is the meter used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measuring the amount of Silt entering the Canal",
            "b) Measuring the Velocity of the Flow",
            "c) Measuring the Hydraulic Jump",
            "d) Measuring Discharge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The meter is a structure constructed in a canal for measuring the discharge of the canal accurately. It is an artificially flumed structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What is the slope of a throat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) From 0.5:1 to 1:1",
            "b) From 1:1 to 3:1",
            "c) From 1:1 to 2:1",
            "d) From 1:3 to 1:2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By using the masonry walls the normal section of the channel is narrowed with a slope of 1:1 to 2:1 to a rectangular section known as the throat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "How many types of metering flumes are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the throat the channel is diverged so as to attain its normal section with the help of masonry wings with a slope of 2:1 to 10:1. Therefore due to gradual convergence and divergence the loss of head in the flume will be less.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "What is the formula for discharge when venturi meter is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(Q = C_d (a_2/\\sqrt{(a_1^2 – a_2^2)})\\sqrt{2h}\\) ",
            "b) \\(Q = C_d (a_1 * a_2/\\sqrt{(a_1^2  – a_2^2)})\\sqrt{2gh}\\) ",
            "c) \\(Q = (a_1 * a_2/\\sqrt{(a_1^2  – a_2^2)})\\sqrt{2g}\\) ",
            "d) \\(Q = C_d (a_1/\\sqrt{(a_1^2  – a_2^2)})\\sqrt{2gh}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since we use the throat for converging purpose in the flume the velocity of the flow increases. After the throat the channel is diverged for expansion, thus again the velocity becomes normal. Due to this increase and decrease of the velocity we can measure the discharge of the flow. This is quiet the procedure on which the venturi meter works. Hence, the metering flumes works on the principle of venturi meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "What is the main drawback of standing wave flume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loss of Hydraulic Jump",
            "b) Loss of Velocity of Flow",
            "c) Loss of Head",
            "d) Loss of Discharge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two types of metering flumes used, which work on the principle of venturi meter are non-modular venturi flume and standing wave flume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "What is the formula for discharge, when standing wave flume is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q = 1.7 x B x H3/2",
            "b) Q = 1.7 x Cd x B x H3/2",
            "c) Q = 1.7 x Cd x B x H",
            "d) Q = 1.7 x Cd x H3/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The diagram represents a gradual channel leading to throat and gradual expanding of channel leading away. Moreover stilling wells are provided at the entrance and at the throat for measuring the head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What is the main purpose of the canal outlet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To Connect Head with a Minor Channel",
            "b) To Avoid Leakage",
            "c) To Avoid Exit Gradient",
            "d) For Proper Discharge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The canal outlet is a small structure that is built at the head of the watercourse so as to connect it with a distributary channel or a minor channel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "How many types of outlets are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The available types of outlets are classified into three classes. These classes are non-modular outlets, semi-modules, and rigid modules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which structure in the entire network of canals is a link between the government and the cultivators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weirs",
            "b) Falls",
            "c) Modules",
            "d) Canal Escapes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the entire network of the canals, up to the modules the control and maintenance falls under the jurisdiction of state government, and beyond the modules the entire working of water courses is takencare by the cultivators. Hence the modules are the structures which provide the link between government and the cultivators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Open sluice and drowned pipe outlet come under which class of modules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modular Outlets",
            "b) Semi Modules",
            "c) Rigid Modules",
            "d) Non-modular Outlets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since these outlets are required in large numbers, they should be cheaply available. And moreover the outlets should be sufficiently strong enough with no moving parts, to avoid periodic maintenance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is the common example of rigid modules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pipe Outlet",
            "b) Open Sluice",
            "c) Gibb’s Module",
            "d) Venturi Flume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The outlet or module should be simple because it can easily be constructed or fabricated by the masons or technicians. Interference with the cultivators should also be avoided to prevent undue tapping of water by the cultivators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "In which class of outlets the discharge is independent of water level of the water course?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-modular Outlets",
            "b) Semi Modules",
            "c) Rigid Modules",
            "d) Modular Outlets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In open sluice or drowned pipe outlet the discharge depends upon the difference between the head in a distributary and the water courses. The discharge in these two also vary widely either with a change in the water level of the distributary or that of a water course. Hence, the open sluice and drowned pipe outlet come under non-modular outlets class.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "When the flexibility of an outlet equals unity, then the outlet is said to be in?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub-proportional",
            "b) Setting",
            "c) Sensitivity",
            "d) Proportionality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Gibb’s module the discharge is constant within the fixed limits, irrespective of variation of water levels of either the distributary or of a water course or both. Thus Gibb’s module is a common example of a rigid module.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "For which type of class of outlets the sensitivity is zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rigid Modules",
            "b) Semi Modules",
            "c) Non-modular Outlets",
            "d) Flexible Modules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The outlets in the class of semi-modules are those in which the discharge is independent of the water level of the water course but depends only on the water level of the distributary as long as a minimum working head is available. Therefore, the discharge is directly proportional to the water surface level in the distributary.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What is the minimum difference between the upstream and downstream water levels to allow designed discharge through the module?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Modular Depth",
            "b) Efficiency of an Outlet",
            "c) Drowning ratio",
            "d) Proportionality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An outlet is said to be proportional when the rate of change of outlet discharge equals the rate of change of channel discharge or in other words, we can say when flexibility equals unity then the outlet is proportional or in proportionality. Hence, F = (m/n) x (y/H) = 1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of the depth of water levels over the crest is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency of an Outlet",
            "b) Drowning Ratio",
            "c) Minimum Modular Head",
            "d) Modular Limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of rate of change of discharge through the outlet to the rate of change of water level of distributary, to the normal depth of the channel is known as sensitivity. Since the discharge is fixed for rigid modules the sensitivity is zero.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of head output to the head input called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modular Limit",
            "b) Minimum Modular Head",
            "c) Efficiency of an Outlet",
            "d) Drowning Ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A minimum difference between the water levels of both upstream and downstream is to be maintained so as to enable the module to pass the designed discharge is known as minimum modular head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which type of non-modular outlet is used in South India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open Sluice",
            "b) Pipe Outlet",
            "c) Gibb’s Module",
            "d) Open Flume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A non-modular may be in the form of a rectangular opening or open sluice or a simply submerged pipe. Pipe outlet is simple type of non-modular and therefore it is widely used in South India.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Why would a submerged pipe outlet be laid inclined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To Provide Proper Exit Gradient",
            "b) To Maintain Proper Hydraulic Jump",
            "c) To Increase Silt Conductivity",
            "d) To Increase the Discharge Capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using suppressed weir formula the discharge through the opening is given when discharge consists of flow over upper part of section (HL may be considered as free discharge), then the discharge is given by q1 = (2/3) x Cd1 x \\(\\sqrt{2g}\\) x B x HL3/2 and if the flow is through the remaining part (through submerged orifice) the discharge is given by q2 = Cd2 x \\(\\sqrt{2gH_L}\\) x B x d.\nTotal discharge is given by q = q1 + q2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "How many types of submerged pipe outlets can be laid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally the diameter of the pipe varies from 10 to 30 cm. They are generally laid in concrete and fixed horizontally. They are also laid sloping upwards by depressing the upstream end of the pipe so as to increase the silt conductivity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "What is the formula for velocity through the pipe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total loss of head = Entry loss + Frictional loss",
            "b) Total loss of head = Frictional loss + Velocity head at exit",
            "c) Total loss of head = Entry loss + Velocity head at exit",
            "d) Total loss of head = Entry loss + Frictional loss + Velocity head at exit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The submerged pipe outlets can be laid either horizontally or sloping upwards. Generally, they are embedded in concrete and fixed horizontally at right angles to the direction of flow. They can also be laid sloping upwards to increase the silt conductivity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "What is the formula for discharge through the pipe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q = Cd x A",
            "b) Q = Cd x A x \\(\\sqrt{2gH_L}\\) ",
            "c) Q = Cd x \\(\\sqrt{2gH_L}\\) ",
            "d) Q = A x \\(\\sqrt{2gH_L}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the difference in the water level of the distributary and the water course is known then by using the formula total loss of head = entry loss + frictional loss + velocity head at the exit. Mathematically it is represented as HL = 0.5V2/2g (1.5 + f’ l/d) where l = length of pipe, d = diameter of pipe and f’ = coefficient of friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "What is the range of modular outlet called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Modular Head",
            "b) Working Range",
            "c) Minimum Loss of Head",
            "d) Modular Ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After knowing the velocity through the pipe, we can calculate discharge using the relation discharge = velocity x area. Mathematically q = V x A, therefore q = Cd x A x \\(\\sqrt{2gH_L}\\) where q = discharge, Cd = coefficient of friction, A = area of pipe, HL = difference of head between FSL of distributary and FSL of water course.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "To ensure the modularity of the modular outlet what should be maintained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Modular Head",
            "b) Efficiency of an Outlet",
            "c) Drawing Ratio",
            "d) Modular Range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flexible and rigid modules are preferred to non-modular outlets because to ensure the equitable distribution of water in the water courses irrespective of their being at high or low levels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "What is the value of HL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water Level of Water course",
            "b) Water Level of Distributary",
            "c) The Water Level of Distributary – Water Level of Water Course",
            "d) Discharge/Area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Outlets are termed as modular outlets only when they work in certain range or say certain limits of water level in the distributary channel and the water course. The range over which each module acts as a modular outlet is called a working range or range of modularity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of semi-modules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free pipe outlet",
            "b) Kennedy’s Gauge outlet",
            "c) Open flume outlet",
            "d) Gibb’s module"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gibb’s module is the most important and widely used rigid module. It was designed by A. S Gibb, formerly Executive Engineer in Punjab Irrigation Department. The discharge range varies from 0.03 to 0.45 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simplest and the oldest type of a flexible outlet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kennedy’s gauge outlet",
            "b) Open flume outlet",
            "c) Free pipe outlet",
            "d) Adjustable orifice semi-module"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silt conduction for pipe outlet discharging freely into the air is quite good and has high efficiency. This can be provided only at a few places where there is a sufficient level difference available between the distributary and the watercourse.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which module is mostly adopted and is considered to be the best of all the modules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adjustable orifice semi-module",
            "b) Open flume outlet",
            "c) Venturi-flume outlet",
            "d) Free pipe outlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The discharge can be computed by –\nQ = Cd. A. (2gH)1/2 where H is the head on U/s side measured from FSL of distributary up to the centre of pipe outlet and A is the area of cross-section of the pipe.\nQ = 0.62 x [3.14/4 x 0.25 x 0.25] x (2 x 9.81 x 0.55)1/2\nQ = 0.09 cumecs or 9 lit/sec.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Calculate the minimum modular head loss involved in ASOM if the head measured from the upstream water level in the distributary is 1.5 m and the width of the throat as 0.16 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.50 m",
            "b) 1.15 m",
            "c) 1.07 m",
            "d) 1.00 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adjustable Proportional Module (APM) is also called Adjustable Orifice Semi-Module (AOSM). It consists of an orifice provided with a gradually expanding flume on the downstream side of the orifice. This outlet is very popular due to several merits over other types and is used in Punjab and Haryana.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "The only irrigation semi-module through which the discharge is not proportional to H1/2 where H is the head causing flow through the module is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) kennedy’s gauge outlet",
            "b) open flume outlet",
            "c) free pipe outlet",
            "d) adjustable orifice semi-module"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum modular head loss involved in ASOM is given by the formula –\nHL = 0.82 HS – W/2 where HS = Head measured from the U/s level in the distributary to the lowest point of the roof block and W = width of the throat\nHL = (0.82 x 1.5) – 0.08 = 1.15 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "An irrigation outlet is said to be proportional, when its ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Setting = outlet index/ channel index",
            "b) Setting = channel index/ outlet index",
            "c) Setting = channel index x outlet index",
            "d) Setting = channel index + Outlet index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The APM (Adjustable Proportional Module) has a setting of 6/10 which is aimed at exact proportionality. But the channels using such module silted very badly and hence, the setting was increased to 8/10 to enable the outlet to carry higher silt charge. The outlet is then known as A.O.S.M.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect advantage of AOSM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The adjustment can be made by raising or lowering the roof blocks at low costs by dismantling the masonry in which the roof bolts are fixed",
            "b) Any undue tampering of roof blocks by the cultivators can be easily detected",
            "c) The module is not perfectly rigid",
            "d) It is the most simple and cheaper outlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The discharge through an open flume outlet is given as –\nQ = Cd. W H3/2 where W = 0.15 m, Cd = 1.71 and H = 1.8 m\nQ = 1.71 x 0.15 x 1.83/2 = 0.62 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "For a wide trapezoidal channel, the channel index is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2/3",
            "b) 5/3",
            "c) 4/3",
            "d) 1/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The discharge through free pipe outlet and Kennedy’s flume outlet is given by-\nQ = Cd. A. (2gH)1/2 where H is the head on U/s side measured from FSL of distributary up to the centre of pipe outlet, Cd is the coefficient of discharge, and A is the area of cross-section of the pipe.\nThe discharge through an open flume outlet is given as: Q = Cd. W H3/2 where W is the width of the throat.\nThe discharge through AOSM is given by- Q = Cd. (W. y0).(2gH)1/2 where ‘y0’ is the height of an orifice opening.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of rigid module?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gibb’s module",
            "b) Khanna’s rigid module",
            "c) Foote module",
            "d) Crump’s proportional module"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crump’s Adjustable Proportional Module is also called Adjustable Orifice Semi-Module. In this type, a cast-iron roof block is provided at the entrance end which is screwed to the masonry entrance by the bolts fixed in the masonry. This block is given the lemniscate curve at the lower end on the entrance side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "The discharge range of Gibb’s module varies from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.03 to 0.45 cumec",
            "b) 0.01 to 0.03 cumec",
            "c) 0.45 to 0.55 cumec",
            "d) 0.55 to 0.75 cumec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The discharge range of Gibb’s rigid module varies from 1 to 16 cusecs or 0.03 to 0.45 cumecs. It is often economical to construct it in R.C.C for lower values of discharge i.e. 1 to 3 cusecs. For discharge value greater than 3 cusecs it can be constructed in brick masonry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "The outlet discharge is maintained constant and it is not at all dependent on the water levels in the parent and the field channels in _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) non-modular outlet",
            "b) modular outlet",
            "c) semi-modular outlet",
            "d) proportional outlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Canal escape helps in removing surplus water from an irrigation canal into a natural drain. The cattle crossing are not of much use on canals carrying considerable water depths and for the ones who don’t know swimming. Bed bars help in desilting the canal section during its maintenance and indicate the correct alignment and bed levels of the canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "In cattle crossings, the exact distance to be kept between the two ramps on the same side should theoretically be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 BV/U",
            "b) 2 BVU",
            "c) 2 BU",
            "d) 2 BU/ V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A non-modular outlet is the one in which discharge is directly dependent on the working head. In the semi-modular outlet, the discharge is directly dependent on the water level in the parent channel. A proportional module is a type of semi-module.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Gibb’s module holds good for the standard design in which _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outlet index m = 2 and H/D = 1/7",
            "b) Outlet index m = 1/3 and H/D = 1/7",
            "c) Outlet index m = 5/3 and H/D = 1/7",
            "d) Outlet index m = 2/3 and H/D = 1/7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An upward rotational flow is imparted if the head causing flow increases at the outer wall restricting against the baffles. The water spins round in the compartment between two successive baffles and finally drops on the incoming water stream of water. This dissipates excess energy and helps in maintaining constant discharge for a wide variation in the head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of the following CD works carry drainage over the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aqueduct and Syphon Aqueduct",
            "b) Super passage and Syphon",
            "c) Level-crossing and inlets outlets",
            "d) Canal Syphon and Aqueduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Aqueduct and Syphon Aqueduct, the canal is carried over the natural drain. In level crossing and inlet and outlets, the canal water and drainage water are allowed to intermingle with each other.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "The canal water flows freely under gravity in which of the following CD works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aqueduct and Super passage",
            "b) Super passage and Syphon",
            "c) Canal Syphon and Aqueduct",
            "d) Level-crossing and inlets outlets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In canal syphon and syphon aqueduct, canal water flows under symphonic action. The canal and the drainage system approach each other practically at the same level in CD works like Level crossing and inlets and outlets.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "A Super passage is the reverse of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) syphon",
            "b) aqueduct",
            "c) inlets and outlets",
            "d) syphon Aqueduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Aqueduct, the drainage water runs below the canal either freely or under symphonic action. In Super passage, the drain is taken over the canal such that the canal water runs below the drain. Similarly, a syphon is also a reverse of aqueduct syphon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about canal syphon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSL of the canal is much above than the bed level of the drainage trough",
            "b) To minimize the trouble of silting, a ramp is provided at the exit",
            "c) The canal water flows under symphonic action",
            "d) For siphoning small discharges, barrels are adopted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For siphoning higher discharges, horseshoe-shaped, rectangular or circular barrels are adopted. For siphoning small discharges, precast RCC pipes are adopted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which CD work is generally adopted when the drainage discharge is small and the drain crosses the canal with its bed level equal to or slightly higher than the canal FSL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syphon Aqueduct",
            "b) Level crossing",
            "c) Inlets and outlets",
            "d) Aqueduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Level crossing is generally adopted when the canal and the drainage are practically at the same level and for high flood drainage discharge but short-lived. Aqueduct or super passage is adopted when high flood drainage discharge is large.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The drainage water is sometimes allowed to join the canal water to augment canal supplies through a hydraulic structure is called as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) canal outlet",
            "b) canal inlet",
            "c) module",
            "d) level crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The structure allows the drainage water to enter the canal and get mixed with the canal water. It helps in augmenting canal supplies. It is adopted when high flood drainage discharge is small.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "The crossing arrangement preferably made at the junction of a huge canal and a river stream carrying a short-lived high flood discharge at almost equal bed levels is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) super passage",
            "b) aqueduct",
            "c) level crossing",
            "d) canal syphon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is a type of cross-drainage works in which the canal water and the drain get intermixed. The arrangement is generally adopted when a huge canal crosses a large torrent carrying a high short-lived flood.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "In a syphon aqueduct provided with a pucca bottom floor, the uplift will occur on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the roof slab",
            "b) the bottom floor",
            "c) both the roof slab as well as the bottom floor",
            "d) nowhere since the flow is free in the canal as well as in the drainage channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The uplift pressure on the floor of the aqueduct is caused due to seepage of water from the canal to the drainage and the sub-soil water table in the drainage bed. The drain bed of the aqueduct is generally depressed and provided with the pucca floor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of CD works carrying the canal over the discharge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The damage caused by floods is not rare",
            "b) The canal is not open for inspection and maintenance",
            "c) The CD works are less liable to damage than the earthwork of the canal",
            "d) During heavy floods, the foundations are susceptible to scour or waterway of the drain may get choked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this arrangement, the canal is above the ground hence it is open to inspection. The damage done by light floods is rare. The CD works are less liable to damage than the earthwork of the canal when the canal passes below the drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "In which of the following arrangement, the perennial drainage discharge is advantageously used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level crossing",
            "b) Inlets and Outlets",
            "c) Syphon",
            "d) Aqueduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In level-crossing, a regulator is provided across the drainage to control the discharge. When there are no floods the torrent regulator is kept closed and during floods, the regulator is opened so as to pass the flood discharge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of CD works carrying drainage over the canal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The arrangement is generally constructed when the drain is very big as compared to the section of the canal",
            "b) The damage caused by floods is not rare",
            "c) The CD works are more liable to damage than the earthwork of the canal",
            "d) The perennial canal is not open to inspection or maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is not necessary to have equal values of escaped discharge and admitted discharge. There can be fewer outlets for more number of inlets. The outlet can be combined with some other work where a separate arrangement is provided for escaping at a small extra cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The relative bed levels of the canal and the drainage may be changed and manipulated by _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) changing the alignment",
            "b) changing the positions of the water table",
            "c) altering the head level",
            "d) use of dewatering equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The canal alignment may be changed so that the crossing is shifted to the d/s where drainage bed is low if the conditions are not suitable for the construction of a siphon-aqueduct. Thus, sufficient headway becomes available for constructing an aqueduct. The CD works are finalized before the canal alignment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The type of canal alignment which involves maximum CD works is a ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ridge canal",
            "b) contour canal",
            "c) side slope canal",
            "d) both ridge and contour canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The point of crossing is shifted upstream or downstream of the drainage by suitably changing the canal alignment. It manipulates the bed levels of the canal and the drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "What is Lacey’s equation for fixing the approximate value of the required waterway for the drain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P = 4.75 Q",
            "b) P = 4.57 Q",
            "c) P = 4.75 Q1/2",
            "d) P = 4.57 Q1/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct equation for fixing the waterway requirement for Aqueduct and Syphon-Aqueducts is given by P = 4.75 Q1/2 where P is the wetted perimeter in meters and Q is the total discharge in cumecs. The wetted perimeter may be taken equal to the width of the drain and equal to the waterway required in case of wide drains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "The maximum permissible reduction in the waterway from Lacey’s perimeter is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) 30%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The width of the perimeter should be so adjusted as to provide the required perimeter i.e. minimum value = 0.8P in case of small drains. From Lacey’s perimeter, the maximum permissible reduction in the waterway is 20% and the provision is made in a suitable number of bays or spans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "The permissible velocity through the barrels is generally limited to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 to 2 m/sec",
            "b) 2 to 3 m/sec",
            "c) 2.5 to 3 m/sec",
            "d) 1 to 2 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The permissible velocity through the barrels is generally limited to 2 to 3 m/sec. A higher value of velocity requires higher and longer marginal banks since it causes quick abrasion of the barrel surfaces by the rolling grit and results in a higher amount of afflux on the U/s side of the aqueduct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is applicable for the design of channel transition when the water depths of the flumed and unflumed section are the same or maybe different?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitra’s method of design of transitions",
            "b) Chaturvedi’s method of design of transitions",
            "c) Hind’s method of design of transitions",
            "d) The general method of design of transitions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mitra’s method was derived on the basis that the rate of change of velocity per unit length remains constant (i.e. water depth). Chaturvedi’s method is used for the design of channel transitions when water depth remains constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "In a siphon aqueduct, the worst condition of uplift on the floor occurs when ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the canal is full and the drainage empty with the water table at drainage bed",
            "b) the canal and drainage are flowing full",
            "c) the canal is empty and the drainage full with the water table at drainage bed",
            "d) the canal is full and the drainage empty with water table below the floor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In siphon aqueducts, the uplift due to water table acts where the bottom floor is depressed below the drainage bed. The maximum uplift under the worst condition is when there is no water flowing in the drain and the water table has risen up to drain bed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "To reduce the cost of the CD works we resort to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) fluming",
            "b) blocking of drain",
            "c) cut-off",
            "d) lifting of canal water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fluming is the contraction of the waterway of the canal. It reduces the length of the barrel or the width of the aqueduct. This is likely to produce an economy in certain cases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Which of the following wings protect the earthen slopes of the canal and also guide the drainage water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canal wings",
            "b) Land wings",
            "c) River wings",
            "d) Side wings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reduction in the width of the aqueduct saves cost which is balanced with the extra cost of the transition wings. The permissible head loss and the economy are the factors governing the extent of the fluming.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The head loss through a siphon barrel is usually given by Unwin’s formula by neglecting velocity of approach as HL = [1 + F1 + F2. L/R] V2/2g, where F1 and F2 respectively represent the coefficient of head losses due to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barrel friction and entry",
            "b) Entry and barrel friction",
            "c) Barrel friction and exit",
            "d) Exit and barrel friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Canal wings or land wings provide a strong connection between sides of canal trough and earthen canal banks. Drainage wings or water wings or river wings provide a vertical cut-off for the water seeping from the canal into the drainage bed. It also protects the earthen slopes and guide the drainage water and join it to the guide banks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "A siphon aqueduct is constructed at a canal crossing site where drainage HFL was 212.2 m by allowing an afflux of 0.4 m at high flood discharge. At this site, the water level downstream of the crossing at the same high flood will be _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 212.2 m",
            "b) 212.6 m",
            "c) 211.8 m",
            "d) It cannot be predicted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The head loss through siphon barrels by Unwin’s formula is given as:\nHL = [1 + F1 + F2. L/R] V2/2g\nwhere F1 is coefficient of head loss at entry and F2 is coefficient such that loss of head due to surface friction is given by F2 = a[1+b/R], a and b are the values depending upon the material of the surface of the barrel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "The most appropriate and economical CD work at the above site will be:",
        "Options": [
            "a) An aqueduct",
            "b) A super-passage",
            "c) A siphon aqueduct",
            "d) A siphon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It should be designed for:\nI. full water load and dead weight with no uplift\nII. full-uplift with no water load.\nThe floor should be designed for the summation of the total uplift caused due to the seepage and the static head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Calculate the depth of cut-off for scour holes for an irrigation channel of F.S.Q equal to 354 cumecs and H.F.Q of natural drainage equal to 600 cumecs. Assume the value of friction factor as 1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 m",
            "b) 7.5 m",
            "c) 10.5 m",
            "d) 8 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The D/s HFL of the drain remains the same by the construction of works and the U/s HFL can be obtained by adding afflux to the D/s HFL.\nThe D/s water level = 212.2 m\nThe U/s water level = 212.2 + 0.4 = 212.6 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of hydraulic mean radius for a channel designed by Lacey’s theory which has a mean velocity of 1m/sec. The silt factor can be taken as unity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 m",
            "b) 0.5 m",
            "c) 2 m",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bed of the natural drain 252.2 m is higher than the canal bed 248 by a margin of 4.2 m, the canal may be taken below the drain. The FSL of canal 253 m is above the drainage bed 252.2 m. the super-passage cannot be provided and the canal water has to be siphoned below the drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of the following is usually adopted for contraction and construction joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rubber water bars",
            "b) V-shape metal bars",
            "c) PVC water bars",
            "d) Z-shape metal bars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metal water stops (both V-shape and Z-shape) and rubber water stops are used in ducts of aqueducts and super-passages in expansion joints. PVC water stops are generally adopted for Construction and contraction joints of aqueducts and super-passages.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a movement joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contraction joint",
            "b) Expansion joint",
            "c) Sliding joint",
            "d) Construction joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The various types of joints involved in RCC constructions are divided into the movement joints and the construction joints. The movement joint includes contraction joints, expansion joints, and sliding joints.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "A partial contraction joint is the one in which?",
        "Options": [
            "a) both the concrete and reinforcing steel are interrupted",
            "b) only the concrete is interrupted",
            "c) only the reinforcement is interrupted",
            "d) none of them is interrupted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A complete contraction joint is the one in which both the concrete and reinforcing steel is interrupted. A partial contraction is the one in which only the concrete is interrupted the reinforcing steel running through. A distinction should also be made between them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a movement joint with deliberate discontinuity but no initial gap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contraction joint",
            "b) Expansion joint",
            "c) Sliding joint",
            "d) Construction joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A joint which has no initial gap between the concrete on either side of the joint with a deliberate discontinuity and the joint being intended to accommodate contraction of concrete is called a construction joint. Expansion joint and Sliding joints are movement joints and there is a complete discontinuity in both the reinforcement and concrete.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a movement joint with complete discontinuity in both reinforcement and concrete and intended to accommodate either expansion or contraction of the structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contraction joint",
            "b) Expansion joint",
            "c) Sliding joint",
            "d) Construction joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Expansion joint includes the provision of an initial gap which by opening or closing accommodates the expansion or contraction of the structure. It is sometimes advantageous to incorporate sliding surfaces for the design of the joint.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "In reinforced concrete floors, the movement joints should normally be spaced at a maximum spacing of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 4.5 m",
            "c) 7.5 m",
            "d) 9 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The concrete floor should be cast in panels with sides not more than 4.5 m in case of floors with a nominal percentage of reinforcement. The movement joints should be placed at a maximum spacing of 7.5 m for reinforced floors in two directions at right angles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "The expansion joints in floors and walls should normally be provided at a spacing of not more than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 m",
            "b) 45 m",
            "c) 50 m",
            "d) 55 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum spacing of 30 m is provided between successive expansion joints or between the ends of the structure. The provision of movement joints in each element can be considered independently where sliding joints are provided between walls and either the floor or roof.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "What is the maximum expansion or contraction allowed for the joint filler material with an initial gap of about 30 mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 5 mm",
            "c) 20 mm",
            "d) 30 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joint fillers are normally compressible sheets or strip materials that are used as spacers and they are fixed to the face of first placed concrete. The maximum permissible expansion or contraction is of the order of 10 mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as support for an effective joint sealing compound in floor and floor joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joint fillers",
            "b) Water bars",
            "c) Joint sealers",
            "d) Primers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joint fillers cannot function as water-tight expansion joints by themselves and they can be used as support for an effective joint sealing compound. The gap provided in the joint is being bridged by a water bar.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "What provides a permanent watertight seal during the whole range of joint movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water bars",
            "b) Joint fillers",
            "c) Joint covers plates",
            "d) Joint sealers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These are the preformed strips of impermeable materials which are embedded in concrete during construction. It spans across the joint and provided watertight seal during joint movement. It is important to ensure proper compaction of the concrete with all water bars for the same purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Which of the following is sometimes used in expansion joints to avoid the risk of fault in an embedded water bar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joint fillers",
            "b) Joint sealers",
            "c) Joint covers plates",
            "d) Water stops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Joint cover plates are sometimes used in expansion joints and it may be of copper or sheet lead. It should be clamped to the concrete face on each side of the joint using suitable gaskets to ensure water tightness in case of the copper cover plate. In sheet lead, lead caulking is done to make it completely water-tight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Joint sealing compounds are impermeable ductile materials which are required to ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase the bond",
            "b) provide a watertight seal by adhesion to concrete",
            "c) shorten the water path",
            "d) avoid the risk of a fault in an embedded water bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: They are impermeable ductile materials and commonly used materials are based on asphalt, bitumen or coal tar with or without fillers. These are required to provide a water-tight seal by adhesion to the concrete. Water bars are used to increase the bond and shorten the water path.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "What is the most common metal used for water stops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monel metal",
            "b) Annealed copper",
            "c) Galvanised iron",
            "d) Steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lower part is occupied by joint filler in case of the expansion joints. Since the retention of the material is assisted by gravity and sealing can be delayed until just before the reservoir is put in to service this type of joint is quite successful.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "What is the design frequency discharge for road bridges and culverts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 100 years",
            "b) 1 in 50 years",
            "c) 1 in 75 years",
            "d) 1 in 25 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rail bridges may be designed for 1 in 100 year’s frequency discharge whereas road bridges and culverts are normally designed for 1 in 50-year discharge. The various empirical formulas and the rational formula are used for calculating the same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The existing width of the stream is contracted at the bridge site by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) U/s wing walls",
            "b) D/s wing walls",
            "c) Canal wings",
            "d) Drain wings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is done by U/s wing walls or training works so as to make it equal to regime width and the bridge may then be spanned across it. This contraction of the stream up to regime width leads to the economy since the bridge length is reduced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The relation between the scour depth (R) and Regime scour depth (Re) for an alluvial river having regime width (W) and contracted width (B) is given by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) R = Re (W/B)0.61",
            "b) R = Re (B/W)0.61",
            "c) R = Re (W/B)0.33",
            "d) R = Re (W/B)0.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From theoretical considerations, there will be no scouring and the foundation of the bridge sub-structure will have to be taken below the bed by a nominal amount not by scour considerations. It is done so as to provide sufficient grip on them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The Lacey’s scour depth R given by equation R = 0.473 (Q/f)1/3 is applicable when the river width is equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) actual river width",
            "b) regime width",
            "c) any contracted width",
            "d) span length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stream is contracted so as to keep span length (L) lesser than the regime width (W) for the quasi-alluvial stream. The normal scour depth (D) is given by-\nD = D’ (W’/L)0.61 where W’ = the natural unobstructed width of the stream and D’ = the scour depth in the quasi-alluvial stream having L=W’.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Culverts are all those road bridges whose spans are up to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 8 m",
            "c) 10 m",
            "d) 12 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For purely alluvial streams, the Lacey’s scour depth (R) is given by R = 1.35 (q2/f)1/3 where q is the discharge intensity per unit width of the stream at the bridge site.\nThe value of Lacey’s regime scour depth (Re) is given by R = Re (W/B)0.61.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "A road bridge is proposed to be constructed across an alluvial stream with the estimated design discharge as 2500 m3/s. It is decided to adopt a total effective waterway equal to 300 m for this bridge as against the regime width of 237.5 m due to afflux considerations. If the HFL at the site is at RL 214 m, then the RL of the open foundation can be suggested as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 206.6 m",
            "b) 208.5 m",
            "c) 207.2 m",
            "d) 210.2 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a purely alluvial stream having a span length (L) equal to regime width (W), Lacey’s regime scour depth is given by R’ = 0.473 (Q/f)1/3.\nSilt factor (f) is obtained by the equation f = 1.76 d1/2 where d is the average size of particle in mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of maximum scour depth for a single span structure having normal scour depth 5m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 m",
            "b) 7.5 m",
            "c) 2.5 m",
            "d) 10 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the bridge span is less than 8 m, it is called Culvert Bridge. The minor bridge has a span length in between 8 m and 30 m and Major bridge have a span range of about 30 to 120 m. Long span bridges have a span length of more than 120 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "The average grain size of the bed material is 0.16 mm for medium silt, Lacey’s silt factor is likely to be _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.30",
            "b) 0.45",
            "c) 0.70",
            "d) 1.32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using Lacey’s regime formula for alluvial stream –\nR = 1.35 (q2/f)1/3 = 1.35 (2500/300)1/3 = 5.55 m\nThe foundation may be taken down below HFL by 1.33R or R + 1.2 m (whichever is more).\ni. 1.33R = 7.38 m\nii. R + 1.2 = 6.75 m (<7.38 m)\nHence, foundation level = 214 – 7.38 = 206.6 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The waterway for a bridge on the river in alluvial plain having a dominant discharge of 3600 cumecs should be ________ m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 m",
            "b) 285 m",
            "c) 300 m",
            "d) 225 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factor of safety for single-span structure on a straight reach of the stream is generally taken as 1.5 and is taken as 2.0 for multi-span structures.\nMaximum scour depth = 1.5 x 5 = 7.5 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "The proposed masonry arch bridge having the total height of its abutments or piers from top to bottom as H can be proposed to have economical spans each equal to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2/3 H",
            "b) 2H",
            "c) 1.2 H",
            "d) 1.5 H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water level on the upstream side rise up when a bridge is constructed across a contracted stream. This maximum rise in water level at the site is afflux and clearance is nothing but freeboard. Hence, the greater is the afflux the lesser will be the freeboard for the same deck level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "A bridge culvert is to be constructed across a proposed lined canal. The afflux at this site for a contracted canal width can be computed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unwin’s formula",
            "b) Broad-crested weir formula",
            "c) Orifice formula",
            "d) Molesworth formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The downstream depth is not affected by the bridge as it is governed by the hydraulic characteristics of the d/s channel. Hence, greater is the reduction in the linear waterway, greater is the afflux. It is assumed that the upstream depth before the bridge construction is the same that prevails even after the bridge construction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "While going to the Tirupati Tirumala Devasthanam from Madras, highway road is found to be lowered at several places over which natural drainage flow during the rainy season. Such dips in the roads are called ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) freeways",
            "b) road dips",
            "c) causeways",
            "d) broadways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the guidelines, the economical length of one span for masonry arch bridge is equal to 2H where H is the total height between the bottoms of the foundations to its top. The clear span length is equal to 1.5H for RCC slab bridges.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula is valid when the downstream depth is more than 80% of the upstream depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unwin’s formula",
            "b) Broad-crested weir formula",
            "c) Orifice formula",
            "d) Molesworth formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The afflux for non-erodible beds may be easily computed by using the Molesworth empirical formula given as-\nh = [V2/17.88 + 0.01524] [(A/a)2 – 1]\nWhere, h = afflux in meters, V = velocity in an unobstructed stream in m/sec, A = unobstructed sectional area of the stream in sq.m and a = obstructed reduced c/s area of the stream at the bridge site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "What is the value of the coefficient of discharge for the wide bridge opening with floors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.90",
            "b) 0.94",
            "c) 0.96",
            "d) 0.98"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The arrangement where there is a lowering or dipping of the road to the ground level at frequent intervals and thus allowing the water to flow across the road is called causeways. Such a dip or causeway is provided on the longitudinal profile of the road. This is feasible in less important towns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Calculate the economic length of one span for RCC Slab Bridge if the total height of abutment or pier from the bottom of its foundation to its top is 6m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 4 m",
            "c) 9 m",
            "d) 3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The weir formula is not valid when the afflux is less than 1/4 of the downstream depth i.e. the downstream depth is more than 80% of the upstream depth. In such a case, the discharge is calculated by the Orifice formula which is given by-\nQ = Co (2g) 1/2. L. ϒd. [h + (1+e)Va2 / 2g] where, Co = coefficient for the orifice formula, ϒd = downstream depth, Va2 / 2g = head due to velocity of approach.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "In Broad Crested Weir formula, the discharge is dependent on ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) upstream water depth only",
            "b) downstream water depth only",
            "c) both upstream and downstream water depth",
            "d) independent of both U/s and D/s water depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of Cd varies with different type of bridge openings.\n\n\nTYPE OF BRIDGE OPENING\nVALUE OF Cd\n\n\n1. Narrow bridge with or without floors\n0.94\n\n\n2. Wide bridge opening with floors\n0.98\n\n\n3. Wide bridge opening with no bed floors\n0.96\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Calculate the longitudinal braking force (P) for four-lane bridges designed for class 70R loading.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14 tonnes",
            "b) 21 tonnes",
            "c) 17.5 tonnes",
            "d) 35 tonnes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per guidelines, the economical length of one span for RCC slab bridges is equal to 1.5H where H is the total height of abutment or pier from the bottom of its foundation to the top.\nClear span length = 1.5 x 6 = 9 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The foundations of bridges on erodible beds are taken down below the HFL by an amount equal to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4/3 times the maximum scour depth",
            "b) 2/3 times the maximum scour depth",
            "c) 1.5 times the maximum scour depth",
            "d) 2 times the maximum scour depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the afflux is less than 1/4 D/s depth, there is no effect on the discharge or on the U/s depth due to the formation of the standing wave. The discharge is only dependent upon U/s depth and is independent of D/s depth. It is applicable only when afflux is more than 1/4 of D/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "The field measurement of infiltration is done by ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) potentiometer",
            "b) lysimeter",
            "c) infiltrometer",
            "d) tensiometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Infiltrometer is used for field measurement of infiltration. There are two types of infiltrometer – Single ring infiltrometer and Double ring infiltrometer. Single ring infiltrometer always overestimate because of the lateral movement of water and to overcome this double-ring infiltrometer is used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for laboratory measurement of infiltration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infiltrometer",
            "b) Rainfall Simulator",
            "c) Tensiometer",
            "d) Lysimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rainfall simulators are used for laboratory measurement of infiltration and Infiltrometer is used for field measurement of infiltration. Lysimeter is used to measure evapotranspiration and tensiometer is used to measure capillary potential.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Deep vertical movement of water in the ground is called as ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) infiltration",
            "b) percolation",
            "c) runoff",
            "d) seepage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate of infiltration is directly proportional to the temperature. As temperature increases, viscosity decreases and resistance to flow decreases and infiltration increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Vegetation cover or grass-cover _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases the field capacity",
            "b) decreases the field capacity",
            "c) may increase or decrease the field capacity",
            "d) have no effect on field capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soils having small pore size such as clay have low infiltration capacity than the soils having large pore size such as sandy soil. One exception is when the clay is present in dry conditions; the soil can develop large cracks which lead to higher infiltration capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression of Horton’s equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ft = fC + (fC – fO) e-K.t",
            "b) ft = fC + (fC – fO) eK.t",
            "c) ft = fC + (fO – fC) eK.t",
            "d) ft = fC + (fO – fC) e-K.t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of infiltration measured by infiltrometer is more than the infiltration rate determined by the rainfall simulator. The rate of infiltration is directly proportional to the depth of surface retention. As the depth of retention is more in infiltrometer hence the rate of infiltration is more in infiltrometer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "An irrigation project is classified as a major project when the CCA involved in the project is more than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000 hectares",
            "b) 5000 hectares",
            "c) 10000 hectares",
            "d) 2500 hectares"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Culturable Command Area is the basis for the design of watercourse and the basis for the design of an irrigation project. The irrigation schemes in India are classified into three parts viz. Minor, Medium and Major Irrigation schemes depending upon the areas involved. Major irrigation scheme is the one where CCA involved in the project is greater than 10,000 hectares.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "A minor irrigation scheme serves up to ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 hectares",
            "b) 500 hectares",
            "c) 1000 hectares",
            "d) 2000 hectares"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The irrigation schemes in India are classified into three parts depending upon the areas involving culturable command area.\n\n\nType of scheme\nAreas involving CCA\n\n\n1. Minor irrigation scheme\n< 2000 hectares\n\n\n2. Medium irrigation scheme\n2000 to 10000 hectares\n\n\n3. Major irrigation scheme\n> 10000 hectares\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Energy is required in the utilisation of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) groundwater",
            "b) surface water",
            "c) both groundwater and surface water",
            "d) capillary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For irrigation purposes, groundwater is largely tapped in India through wells and tube wells. Manual, wind, diesel or electric power can be used for lifting water from open wells. The subsequent development in the technique of tapping groundwater is the use of tube wells which requires diesel or electric power.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Which of the following property of geological formation represents its water storage capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permeability",
            "b) Porosity",
            "c) Both permeability and porosity",
            "d) Transmissibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Porosity is the quantitative measurement of the interstices of voids present in the rock. In other words, it is the maximum amount of water that can be stored in the rock.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "The zone of aeration in a groundwater profile does not include ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) capillary zone",
            "b) soil water zone",
            "c) intermediate zone",
            "d) saturation zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Depending upon the number of interstices present, the aeration zone is divided into three classes. The capillary fringe is a continuation of the zone of saturation and does contain some interstitial water. Soil zone is the depth from the surface penetrated by the roots of vegetation and the remaining intermediate part is intermediate zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "In which of the following zone the stresses are beyond the elastic limits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zone of rock fracture",
            "b) Zone of rock flowage",
            "c) Zone of saturation",
            "d) Zone of aeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the zone of rock flowage, interstices are absent because the stresses are beyond the elastic limits. The rocks remain in a state of plastic flow and water present in this zone is known as internal water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The rate of flow of water through ground strata can be estimated by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manning’s formula",
            "b) Strickler’s formula",
            "c) Dupuit’s equation",
            "d) Darcy’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A French Scientist Mr. H Darcy on the basis of experimental evidence gave a law governing the discharge through soils. According to the law, the discharge is directly proportional to the head loss and the area of cross-section of the soil and inversely proportional to the length of the soil sample.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The relation between Transmissibility (T) and Permeability (K) for an aquifer of depth d is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) K = T.d",
            "b) T = K.d",
            "c) T = K.log d",
            "d) T = ln (Kd)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transmissibility is measured by the coefficient of transmissibility (T) and was introduced by Theiss. It can be defined as the rate of flow of water through an aquifer of unit width and full-depth under a hydraulic gradient and at a temperature of 20°C. The relation between K and T is given as T=K.d.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Darcy’s law is valid when the flow is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) laminar and steady",
            "b) non-uniform",
            "c) turbulent",
            "d) both laminar and turbulent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Darcy’s law has been demonstrated to be valid only for laminar flow conditions because the flow in sands, silts, and clays is invariably laminar.\nMathematically, v = K.i where v = discharge velocity, K = coefficient of permeability and I = hydraulic gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "The coefficient of permeability indicates the ease with which water can flow through a soil mass. The soil type which has less permeability is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gravelly soil",
            "b) clayey soil",
            "c) sandy soil",
            "d) both sandy and gravel soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The approximate average value of the coefficient of permeability in clayey soil is 0.04 x 10-5 cm/sec. The permeability coefficient of gravel soil is of the order of 4cm/sec and for sandy soil is 0.04 cm/sec.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most important zone for a groundwater hydraulic engineer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zone of rock fracture",
            "b) Zone of rock flowage",
            "c) Zone of saturation",
            "d) Zone of aeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is the most important zone for a hydraulic engineer as this water has to be tapped out and the water in this zone is under hydrostatic pressure. In this zone, water exists within the interstice which is nothing but groundwater.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Which zone contains water that is under molecular attraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zone of rock fracture",
            "b) Zone of rock flowage",
            "c) Zone of saturation",
            "d) Zone of aeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Zone of aeration is the space above the water table and below the surface and the water exists in this zone by molecular attraction. The water in this zone is not at hydrostatic pressure and the gravity water moves through this zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "The geological formation which yields only insignificant quantity of groundwater is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aquifer",
            "b) aquifuse",
            "c) aquiclude",
            "d) aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geological formations which are porous and contain a good amount of water but does not yield water freely to wells due to its lesser permeability is called aquitard. The water yield from such a formation is insignificant. Sandy clay is an example of the aquitard.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The geological formation which may contain water but does not contain any yield is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aquifer",
            "b) aquifuse",
            "c) aquiclude",
            "d) aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The geological formations which are porous but have no permeability are termed as an aquiclude. Water cannot be extracted from such formations. A clay layer is an example of aquiclude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Which of the following geological formation contains and readily yields water to our tube wells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquifuse",
            "c) Aquiclude",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The geological formations which are both porous and permeable hence sufficient quantity of water can be extracted from them. Aquifers vary in depth and thickness and in general, confined and non-confined aquifers are two main categories of the aquifer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of the following geological formation does not contain any amount of groundwater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquitard",
            "b) Aquifer",
            "c) Aquiclude",
            "d) Aquifuge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geological formations which are very dense and contain no water in voids and are neither porous nor permeable are termed as aquifuge. Granite rock is an example of aquifuge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The quantum of water contained in the soil pores which cannot be extracted by gravity drainage is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pellicular water",
            "b) capillary water",
            "c) hygroscopic water",
            "d) available water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the saturated formations are drained under the action of gravity drainage, the volume of water drained is less than the volume of void space. The water contained in these voids cannot be drained out by force of gravity. The water which is always retained by these interstices due to molecular attraction is called pellicular water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "What is the volume of groundwater which can be extracted by gravity drainage from a soil stratum when expressed as percentage fraction of the volume of the soil stratum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pellicular water",
            "b) Available water",
            "c) Specific yield",
            "d) Field capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Yield is the volume of groundwater extracted by gravity drainage from a saturated water-bearing material. It is known as the specific yield when it is expressed as the ratio of the volume of the total material drained.\nSpecific Yield = (Volume of the water obtained by gravity drainage/ total volume of drained material) x 100.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Field capacity of a ground aquifer equals _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) specific yield",
            "b) 100 – specific yield",
            "c) 100/ specific yield",
            "d) field capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Field capacity can be expressed as the percentage of the total volume of the material drained. Specific retention or field capacity is given as –\nF.C = volume of water held against gravity drainage/total volume of the material drained x 100\nThe summation of Specific yield and field capacity is equal to the porosity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Water wells excavated through confined aquifers are known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) artesian wells",
            "b) non-artesian wells",
            "c) gravity wells",
            "d) water table wells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Specific retention can be defined as the amount of water held between the grains due to molecular attraction on the walls of the interstices. If the effective size of grain decreases, the surface area between the interstices will increase causing more specific retention and less specific yield. In fine soils like clay, the specific retention would be more and it results in small specific yield.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "In case of a flowing well, the piezometric surface is always _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) below the ground level",
            "b) above the ground level",
            "c) at the ground level",
            "d) above or below the ground level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gravity wells which are constructed to tap water from the unconfined aquifer are known as unconfined or non-artesian wells. Such wells are also known as water table wells or gravity wells since the water level in these wells is equal to the level of the water table.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The line joining the static water levels in several wells excavated through a confined aquifer is known as the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cone of depression",
            "b) piezometric surface",
            "c) perched water-table",
            "d) hypsometric curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Perched water table is the top surface of the water held in the perched aquifer. Cone of depression is the surface of the water table surrounding the well which takes up a curved shape. The piezometric surface is an imaginary surface that defines the level to which water will rise representing the total head in an aquifer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The permeability of an aquifer (m/day) will ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase with an increase in temperature of water flowing through the aquifer",
            "b) decrease with an increase in temperature of water flowing through the aquifer",
            "c) not get affected by the change in temperature of water flowing through the aquifer",
            "d) increase up to 20°C and then decreases with the increase in the temperature of water flowing through the aquifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The permeability is inversely proportional to the viscosity of water and viscosity decreases with increase in temperature. Hence, permeability will increase with an increase in temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The discharge per unit drawdown at a well is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) specific yield",
            "b) specific retention",
            "c) specific capacity",
            "d) specific storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Specific capacity of a well can be defined as the well-yield per unit of drawdown. The value is not constant but decreases as the discharge increases. The value is not the same for all drawdowns, it should be determined for the fall of the first meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Coefficient of storage (A) has the dimensions of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) L3",
            "b) L",
            "c) L2",
            "d) Dimensionless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Storage coefficient can be defined as the volume of water released from an aquifer of 1 m2 area and full depth per meter fall of the piezometric head. Its unit will be m3/m2/m i.e. dimensionless.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The units of specific capacity of a well are _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) m3/sec",
            "b) m2/sec",
            "c) m/sec",
            "d) no units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Specific capacity is given by –\nSpecific capacity = discharge of the well / Drawdown = Q / (C1Q + C2Q2) = m3/sec/m = m2/sec. This equation also shows that the specific capacity of the well is not constant but decreases as the discharge increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Specific yield for an unconfined aquifer is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than porosity",
            "b) less than porosity",
            "c) equal to porosity",
            "d) unrelated to porosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific yield is expressed as the ratio of the volume of the water obtained by gravity drainage to the total volume of the material drained. Since, Specific yield + Specific retention = Porosity. Evidently, the specific yield is less than the porosity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "A perched aquifer is found within ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) unconfined aquifer",
            "b) confined aquifer",
            "c) aquiclude",
            "d) both confined and unconfined aquifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes an impervious medium carrying saturated soil-mass exists over the water table which can be used as a source of water. This body of saturated material is a kind of aquifer termed as a perched aquifer. It is a special case that is found to occur within an unconfined aquifer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "The specific capacity of a confined well under equilibrium condition and within the working limits of drawdown ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) is constant at all drawdowns",
            "b) decreases as the drawdown are increased",
            "c) increases as the drawdown are increased",
            "d) may increase or decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The following equation shows that specific capacity decreases as Q increases and Q increase only when the drawdown is increased by heavier pumping and hence, specific capacity decreases as drawdown is increased.\nSpecific capacity = Q/(C1.Q + C2.Q2). i.e. Discharge/ Drawdown (Well loss + Aquifer loss).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "The standard specific capacity of a well is the well-discharge per unit of drawdown. This value of discharge should be obtained at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) any drawdown",
            "b) a particular drawdown of 3 m",
            "c) the first 1 m of drawdown",
            "d) the first 2 m of drawdown"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Specific capacity is the rate of flow from a well per unit of a drawdown. The value is not the same for all drawdowns, it should be determined for the fall of the first meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "An example of aquitard stratum in the ground profile is a layer of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) granite rock",
            "b) clay",
            "c) sandy clay",
            "d) sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The geological formations which are porous and contain a good amount of water but does not yield water freely to wells due to its lesser permeability is called aquitard. The water yield from such a formation is insignificant. Sandy clay is an example of the aquitard.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "An aquifer which is confined at its bottom but not at the top is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) semi-confined aquifer",
            "b) confined aquifer",
            "c) unconfined aquifer",
            "d) artesian aquifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unconfined aquifer is the one in which the topmost water-bearing stratum having no confined impermeable overburden lying over it. Aquifer water serves as an upper zone of saturation and it is subjected to hydrostatic pressure only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The clogging of well screens and consequent reduction in pump efficiency is indicated by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the high value of the well-loss",
            "b) the low value of the well-loss",
            "c) variable value of the well-loss",
            "d) both high and low value of the well-loss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the screen size is compatible to the surrounding porous media, the well loss is caused by the axial movement inside the well up to the pump intake (since the well loss through the screen is very small). When clogging of the screen increases, the well loss increases which adversely affects the pump efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The performance of a well is measured by its ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) specific capacity",
            "b) specific yield",
            "c) storage coefficient",
            "d) permeability coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of the percolating water depends on the depression head. If the amount of water withdrawn from the well is more, increasing the depression head, higher flow velocities will prevail in the vicinity of the well. At a certain stage, depression head may become so great that the soil particles also start coming with the percolating water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The safe depression head for open wells is generally taken to be x times the critical depression head when x is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/6",
            "b) 1/3",
            "c) 1/2",
            "d) 3/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific capacity is the measure of the well performance indicating the rate of water percolation into a well. It is also defined as the yield of a well under the head of one meter. The specific capacity of the well is not constant but decreases as the discharge increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "The yield of a well depends on ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) permeability of soil",
            "b) area of aquifer opening into the wells",
            "c) actual flow velocity",
            "d) permeability and actual flow velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The depression head is kept equal to one-third of the critical depression head. The maximum or critical yield corresponds to the critical depression head and the maximum safe yield corresponds to the working head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which type of open well is suitable when the sub-soil is formed of gravel or coarse sand deposits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unlined wells",
            "b) Wells with pervious lining",
            "c) Wells with impervious lining",
            "d) Temporary wells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yield of a well is the rate at which water percolates into the well under the safe maximum depression head or the critical depression head. It depends on the position of the water table, permeability, and porosity of the soil, rate of water withdrawal from the well, and amount of water storage in the well.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "A well 3 meters in diameter has its normal water level 3 meters below the ground level. By pumping water level in the well is depressed to 10 meters below the ground level. In 4 hours the water rises by 5 meters. Calculate the specific yield of the well.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.213 m3/hr",
            "b) 5 m3/hr",
            "c) 1.242 m3/hr",
            "d) 3.224 m3/hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Permanent lining or wells with impervious lining is sunk in regions with alluvial soil formation. Unlined wells or temporary wells are of very shallow depths and can be constructed only when the water table is very near to the ground. Wells with pervious lining is generally suitable in the strata of gravel or coarse sand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "An open well is called shallow well when ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the depth of well is small",
            "b) the water table is high",
            "c) it does not encounter mota formation",
            "d) it finds the foundation in the mota formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sunk wells are constructed in soft formations and the subsoil formation may be sandy or clayey. The lining is first constructed above the ground level and then it sunk in the sub-soil formation by putting a load on the lining, therefore, it is called sunk well.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "If the sub-soil formation is of fine sand, the rough value of the specific yield of well per unit area of the well (K/A) given by Marriot is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25",
            "b) 0.50",
            "c) 0.75",
            "d) 1.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific yield (K) is calculated from the formula, K = 2.303 (A/T) log (H1/H2) where A is the area of the well, T is the total time of recuperation to bring the water level from depth H1 to H2.\nGiven values, A = 3.14/4 x 9 = 7.065 sq. m, T = 4 hours, H1 = 7m, H2 = 2m\nK = 2.303 x 7.065 x 1/4 x log (7/2) = 2.213 m3/hr under a head of one meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Which of the following method of lifting water is very suitable when the depth of well is from 12 to 20 meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Denkli",
            "b) Churus",
            "c) Persian wheel",
            "d) Windmill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A shallow well is that well which does not encounter mota formation. A deep well is that well which goes below the water table and finally finds its foundation in the mota formation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "A well is to be constructed in a fine sandy sub-soil formation. The discharge of the well under the depression head of 4 m is 0.004 m3/sec. Calculate the diameter of the well.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 m",
            "b) 2.5 m",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 3.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Open wells have comparatively bigger diameter varying from 2-9 m and are suitable for low discharges in the order of 1-5 liters per second. The yield of the well is limited as the groundwater storage is limited. An open well irrigates small area and its cost per hectare is generally more than that of a tube well.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "The most widely used type of a deep state tube well in India is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cavity well",
            "b) strainer tube well",
            "c) slotted pipe gravel packed tube well",
            "d) both cavity and strainer tube well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strainer type tubewell is a bored hole in which a metal pipe with suitable perforations is inserted. A strainer type tubewell is suitable when water-bearing stratum is available at less depth and there is a possibility of tapping water through sides. It is generally unsuitable for fine sandy strata.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "The general average yield from standard tube wells is of order of____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 L/sec",
            "b) 50 L/sec",
            "c) 500 L/sec",
            "d) 5000 L/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tube well irrigation is very suitable where the subsoil formation is suitable for storing water. The general average yield from the standard deep tube-wells is of the order 40 to 50 liters/sec. Shallow tube-wells may yield as high as 15-20 liters/sec if located at proper places.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following tubewell is suitable when a deep bearing stratum lies below an impervious layer and water contribution can take place through bottom only?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strainer type tubewell",
            "b) Abyssinian tubewell",
            "c) Cavity type tubewell",
            "d) Slotted type tubewell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A strainer type tubewell is suitable when water-bearing stratum is available at less depth and there is a possibility of tapping water through sides. The slotted type tubewell is intermediate to the strainer and cavity type tubewell and is used where both the above cannot be used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "What is the measure of the fineness of an aquifer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average grain size",
            "b) Effective diameter",
            "c) Mean particle size",
            "d) Uniformity coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cavity-type tubewell, water contribution to the bored hole takes place through the bottom layer only as is done by screen well. The flow in a cavity well is essentially spherical. In strainer type tubewell, water enters into the well from the sides and the flow is radial.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "What is Pack Aquifer Ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D50 of the gravel / D50 of the aquifer",
            "b) D50 of the aquifer / D50 of the gravel",
            "c) D60 of the aquifer material / D10 of the aquifer material",
            "d) D60 of the gravel / D10 of the aquifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Effective diameter is an index of the measure of the fineness of an aquifer. It is used for designing various intake components of a tubewell. For permeability D10 (i.e. 90% grains retained on the sieve) is taken as the effective size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "According to the Central Board of Irrigation and Power, the PA ratio for graded aquifer should be _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9 – 12.5",
            "b) 12 – 15.5",
            "c) > 15.5",
            "d) < 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gravel pack is usually designed on the basis of Pack Aquifer (PA) ratio. It is usually defined as the ratio of D50 size of the gravel pack material to the D50 size of the aquifer material. It should be designed before designing the size of the slots to be made in the well-screens.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "For good design, the uniformity coefficient (Cu) of the gravel material should preferably be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) > 2.0",
            "b) < 2.0",
            "c) > 2.5",
            "d) < 2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Central Board of Irrigation and Power suggested the following criteria for PA ratio.\ni. For uniform aquifers (having Cu < or = 2.0), the PA ratio should be in between 9 – 15.5\nii. For graded aquifers (having Cu > 2.0), the PA ratio should be in between 12 – 15.5.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "The efficiency of the centrifugal pumps commonly used for lifting water from wells may be of the order of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30%",
            "b) 65%",
            "c) 90%",
            "d) 95%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The uniformity coefficient was proposed by Hazen. The value of the coefficient of the gravel material is preferably kept to be equal to or less than 2.5. A higher value may cause segregation of the gravel during pouring which will result in poor efficiency of the well.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "A tube well is suitable when the subsoil formation is made up of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cracked and faulted rock",
            "b) alluvium",
            "c) alluvium and various layers of sandy soil, clayey soil, and gravel",
            "d) clayey soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Jet pumps have low efficiency of the order of 35% as compared to 65-85% for other centrifugal pumps. It is not used for irrigation tube-wells.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Bored tube wells in rocky consolidated formations as are encountered in the South Indian States of our country are usually drilled by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary drilling rigs",
            "b) percussion drilling rigs",
            "c) down the hole hammer (DTH) rigs",
            "d) cable method of drilling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India most of the land especially the Indo-Gangetic plains, Narmada valley consists of deep alluvial soils. The sub-soil water slowly penetrates and is stored in porous sand and gravel beds which are extensively found in India. Tube wells can be easily installed in such lands and are useful for irrigation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of the following drilling method is unsuitable in loose formations such as unconsolidated sand and gravel or quicksand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Percussion drilling",
            "b) Wash boring method",
            "c) Rotary boring method",
            "d) Reverse rotary method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In rocky areas, down the hole hammer rigs (DTH rigs) are used to drill isolated holes of 10 to 15 cm in diameter. They are usually in the depth range of 100 m and mostly been constructed in southern states of India. This type of wells usually depends on joints and fissures in the rocks for their water supply.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Which drilling method is best suited for underground formations made of gravel, sand and clayey deposits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Percussion drilling",
            "b) Wash boring method",
            "c) Rotary boring method",
            "d) Reverse rotary method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Percussion method of drilling the well hole is also known as the cable method of drilling. It is ineffective in loose material because of slumping and caving of the material around the drilling bit. This method is useful for cutting consolidated rocks from soft clay to hardest rocks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Which is the fastest method of drilling and especially useful in unconsolidated formations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cable tool method",
            "b) Water-jet boring method",
            "c) Hydraulic Rotary method",
            "d) Reverse Rotary method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Percussion method is suitable for soft and fissured rock formations. The rotary boring method can be successfully used for rock as well as unconsolidated formations. The reverse rotary method is used for soft unconsolidated formations made of sand, silt or soft clay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "A household tube well is called Abyssinian tube well falls under _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) strainer type",
            "b) cavity type",
            "c) slotted type",
            "d) both cavity and slotted type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abyssinian tube well is the most common type of tubewell used for household purposes. It is also a strainer type of the tube well and the length of the strainer used here is about 2 meters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Duty of wells expressed in hectares the well can irrigate to bring a crop to maturity because of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) well irrigation is a minor scheme",
            "b) well water is lifted immediately and cannot be expressed in ha/m3/sec",
            "c) well is situated in the middle of the commanded area",
            "d) wells are owned by cultivators and so the source of supply is a private one"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In well irrigation water is lifted intermittently. The duty of a well is the area of land in hectares the well can irrigate annually and fully to bring a crop to maturity. It cannot be expressed in hectares/m3/sec for a base period of a crop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Which of the following strainer is used for shallow irrigation tube wells particularly in deltaic regions of developing countries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous slot type of strainer",
            "b) Louver type of strainer",
            "c) Pipe strainer with fine mesh jackets",
            "d) Coir rope strainers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Coir rope strainers are low-cost strainers and are generally used for shallow irrigation tube wells. The main disadvantage of such a strainer is its short life of 3 to 5 years. The rusting of the iron bars of the supporting frame and the loosening of the coir rope which expands on wetting are the causes of its failure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Rewhiding the well involves ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) heavy pumping of well",
            "b) starting and stopping of pumping intermittently",
            "c) forcing of the well water back into the aquifer",
            "d) jetting with water at high velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rewhiding involves starting and stopping of pumping intermittently. It provides a relatively rapid change in the head of the well and can be done with any type of pump. However, the turbine pump installed with a foot valve is the most effective.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an effective method for the development of well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surging",
            "b) Pumping",
            "c) Well development by compressed air",
            "d) Jetting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Development of well by high velocity jetting is one of the most effective methods. In this method, the fine particles are washed out of the aquifer due to the shooting of high-velocity water stream through the screen openings. These fines get back into the well due to the turbulence created by the jet. The entire surface of the screen can be covered by gradual raising, lowering and slowly rotating the jetting tool.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "The appropriate life of a tubewell in India is of the order of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 year",
            "b) 2 years",
            "c) 5 years",
            "d) 15 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A normal tubewell lasts for about 15 to 20 years in Northern India. It may fail due to incrustation and corrosion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Incrustation of the tubewell pipes may lead to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduced discharge from the tubewell",
            "b) excessive discharge of sand with water",
            "c) discharge of highly alkaline water",
            "d) increased pumping rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deposition of alkali salts on the inside walls of the pipe is called incrustation. It reduces the effective diameter of the well pipe and hence reduces the discharge of the tubewell. It cannot be completely eliminated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Corrosion of tubewell pipes may cause _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduced discharge from the tubewell",
            "b) excessive discharge of sand with water",
            "c) discharge of highly alkaline water",
            "d) increased pumping rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to the action of acidic water on the pipe, it is gradually destroyed by corrosion. The aquifer sand surrounding the well pipe comes out through the worn-out pipe walls bringing sand along with water. It results in the excessive withdrawal of sand along with the well water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Which of the following pump can effectively lift water under the maximum suction head of 6 to 8 meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A single-stage centrifugal pump",
            "b) Submersible pumps",
            "c) Turbine pumps",
            "d) Jet pumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A centrifugal pump works effectively under the maximum suction head of 6 to 8 m. Such pumps can be used at places where the fluctuations in water table plus the depression head are limited to a maximum of 8 m. The borehole type pump is used for larger values.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives an indication of the chemical quality of the groundwater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geological logs",
            "b) Resistivity logs",
            "c) Sonic logs",
            "d) Thermal logs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Delta in well irrigation is the total depth of water required to mature a crop in meters or centimetres. The delta of well water is about 66% of canal water because conveyance losses are minimum and well water is used at the right time in the right quantity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which of the following pumps is also used for testing or development of wells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical turbine pump",
            "b) Submersible motor pump",
            "c) Jet pump",
            "d) Airlift pump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Resistivity surveys are based on the fact that water increases the conductivity of the rocks and thereby reducing their resistivity. Resistivity logs indicate the values of electrical resistivity of the rocks at different depths.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Which log represents the type of strata existing at different depths and encountered during digging or boring of the wells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Well logs",
            "b) Resistivity logs",
            "c) Radiometric logs",
            "d) Sonic logs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basic principle in well development is to cause reversals of flow that will rearrange the aquifer particles through the screen openings. This breaks down the bridging of the groups of particles. When the flow is in one direction small particles bridge between large particles across the screen openings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Aswan dam on Nile River in Egypt was perhaps the first modern dam of the world. Its construction was completed in the year _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1664",
            "b) 1798",
            "c) 1902",
            "d) 1931"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first modern dam of the world was completed in 1902 and is constructed on the Nile River in Egypt at Aswan. It was designed primarily to control the flooding of the Nile River, to promote irrigation and for navigation along the river.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the only modern dam that has failed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Koyna dam in India",
            "b) Vega de Tera dam in Spain",
            "c) Mauvoision dam in Switzerland",
            "d) Trinity dam in California, USA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vega de Tera Dam in Spain was wrecked by heavy rains resulting in the failure of the structure due to faulty design and poor construction. The koyna dam in India was on the verge of failure due to earthquake (in 1968).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Earthen dams are _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rigid dams",
            "b) non-rigid dams",
            "c) overflow dams",
            "d) diversion dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Earthen dams, Rock-fill dam, and combined earth and rockfill dam are all non-rigid dams. Timber dam, Steel dam, Arch dam, Buttress dam, and solid gravity dam are all rigid dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "The prominent modern dam which has changed its name several times is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nagarjuna dam",
            "b) Hoover dam",
            "c) Bhakra dam",
            "d) Idukki dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name of the Hoover dam was a political issue and it was first of all named as Boulder dam. Later it was changed to Hoover dam when Herbert Hoover became the President of America. In 1933, President Roosevelt changed this name again to Boulder dam for 14 years and then once again the name was changed to Hoover dam by Republicans which still exists today.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The famous Roosevelt dam in USA is of the type __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock-fill dam",
            "b) Solid Masonry Gravity Dam",
            "c) RCC arch bridge",
            "d) A hollow masonry gravity dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Roosevelt dam was completed in 1911 on the Salt River of Arizona (U.S.A). It was constructed with the solid blocks of concrete which were of the type known as Solid Masonry Gravity Dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "A _________________ dam is generally called as a weir or barrage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) storage dam",
            "b) detention dam",
            "c) diversion dam",
            "d) rigid dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A small dam constructed only to raise the water level on the upstream side for diverting it to the canals is called a diversion dam. Nangal Dam is an example of a diversion dam. It is actually called a weir or a barrage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Multiple arch dam is an example of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arch dam",
            "b) Shell-arch dams",
            "c) Buttress dams",
            "d) Coffer dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In buttress dams, the load is mainly transferred to the supporting buttresses. The most common types of this dam are Deck slab type and multiple arch types. The multiple arch dams are used for higher dam heights.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which type of dam design gives a wider choice of materials including earth-fill and rock-fill dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-overflow dams",
            "b) Overflow dams",
            "c) Rigid dams",
            "d) Non-rigid dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Non-overflow dams are not designed to be overtopped. Sometimes it is combined together with the overflow dam to form a composite single structure. Overflow dams are designed to pass the surplus water over their crest and are often called as spillways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "The highest concrete gravity dam of the world is the Grand Dixene dam in Switzerland whose height is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 325 m",
            "b) 317 m",
            "c) 285 m",
            "d) 272 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This dam is a concrete gravity dam and is the highest gravity dam in the World with a height of 285 m. The primary purpose of the dam is hydroelectric power generation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as a debris dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage dam",
            "b) Detention dam",
            "c) Diversion dam",
            "d) Rigid dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The small dams which are constructed to delay and detain the flow of floodwater are called detention dams. They are called check dams also. It is sometimes constructed to trap sediments and is often called debris dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Topography dictates the first choice of the type of dam. A narrow U-shaped valley would suggest a ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) concrete overflow dam",
            "b) spillway",
            "c) arch dam",
            "d) earth dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the topography of the dam site is the first criterion of the selection process. For deep gorges, a concrete dam is an obvious choice whereas an embankment dam with a separate spillway is generally preferred for\nbroad valleys in plains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "A narrow V-shaped valley indicates the choice of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) concrete overflow dam",
            "b) spillway",
            "c) arch dam",
            "d) earth dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The choice of an arch dam is suggested for a narrow V-shaped valley. A separate site for the spillway must also be available and it is generally preferred to have the top width of the valley less than 1/4 of its height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Which of the following foundations are suitable for earthen and rock-fill dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid rock foundation",
            "b) Gravel foundation",
            "c) Silt and fine sand foundation",
            "d) Clay foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gravel foundations are suitable for earthen and rock-fill dams as the coarse sands and gravels are unable to bear the weight of high concrete gravity dams. However, low concrete gravity dams up to a height of 15 m may also be suggested.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Which foundation suggests the adoption of an earth dam or very low gravity dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid rock foundation",
            "b) Gravel foundation",
            "c) Silt and fine sand foundation",
            "d) Clay foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silt and fine sand foundation suggest the adoption of earth dams or low gravity dams up to a height of 8 m and a rock-fill dam is not suitable on such foundation. Seepage and settlement through such foundation may be excessive and must be properly designed to avoid dangers\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Which foundation is not fit for concrete gravity dam or for rock-fill dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid rock foundation",
            "b) Gravel foundation",
            "c) Silt and fine sand foundation",
            "d) Clay foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to enormous settlement, unconsolidated and high moisture clays are not fit for concrete gravity dams or for rock-fill dams. It can be accepted for earthen dams but only after special treatment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Which dam is a better choice when the raw materials are not available and have to be transported from far off distances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthen dam",
            "b) Rock-fill dam",
            "c) Concrete gravity dam",
            "d) Hollow concrete dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Availability of construction materials sometimes dictates the choice. A buttress (hollow concrete dam) is a better choice if the material has to be transported from far off distances. If they are easily available it naturally calls for a concrete gravity dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "For any width of the valley with any foundation and low height of water to be stored, the best-suited dam is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) steel dam",
            "b) buttress dam",
            "c) timber dam",
            "d) solid gravity dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For any width of the valley with good foundation steel dam is the most suited and if the low height of the water is to be stored for any width of the valley with any foundation timber dam is suited. If gorge with the rocky bed is available soli gravity dam is suited.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Arch dams are constructed in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) wide valleys with flat side slopes",
            "b) narrow valley with weak abutments",
            "c) moderate valleys with strong abutments",
            "d) narrow valleys with strong abutments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An arch dam is very suitable for the narrow valley provided with good rock abutments are available. They are best suited at sites where the dam must be extremely high and narrow but the presence of sound abutments is an important requirement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect regarding the selection of dam site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For economy, the length of the dam should be as small as possible",
            "b) For a given height, it should store the maximum volume of water",
            "c) The river valley at the dam site should be narrow but should open out upstream to provide a large basin for a reservoir",
            "d) The general bed level at the dam site should preferably be lower than that of the river basin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The general B.L should preferably be higher than that of the river basin which facilitates drainage problem and will reduce the height of the dam. The water storage should be largest for the minimum possible height and length and site should be located in a narrow valley.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Which structures are best suited to resist earthquake shocks without danger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthen dams",
            "b) Concrete gravity dams",
            "c) Timber dam",
            "d) Both earthen and concrete gravity dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design must include the earthquake forces if the dam is to be situated in an earthquake zone and the safety is ensured by considering the worst-case against the increased stress induced by high intensity. The best-suited dams are earthen dams and concrete gravity dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Nangal Dam is an example of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) diversion dam",
            "b) storage dam",
            "c) detention dam",
            "d) arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nangal Dam is a subsidiary dam which is 95 feet high on the downstream of Bhakra on Satluj. This dam heads up the water of the river and then diverts it to off-taking canals from the banks. Bhakra dam and Talwara dam are storage dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is partly earthen and partly rockfill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tehri dam",
            "b) Koyna dam",
            "c) Sardar Sarovar dam",
            "d) Bhakra dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Koyna dam is a rubble-concrete dam built on Koyna river in Satara district Maharashtra. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is a gravity dam that is built on the river Narmada in Gujrat. Bhakra Dam is a concrete gravity dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Bhakra dam of India is located in the state of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Punjab",
            "b) Himachal Pradesh",
            "c) Uttar Pradesh",
            "d) Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bhakra Dam is a concrete gravity dam which is 225 m high across Sutlej river in Himachal Pradesh. The main functions of the dam are flood control, Irrigation, Electricity and fish development.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The highest concrete gravity dam of India which is also the 2nd highest such dam of the world is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indira Sagar Dam",
            "b) Cheruthoni Dam",
            "c) Bhakra Nangal dam",
            "d) Tehri Dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bhakra Nangal is the highest gravity dam in India with a height of 225 meters. It is built across the Sutlej river in Himachal Pradesh. Cheruthoni dam and Indira Sagar dam is also a concrete gravity dam whereas Tehri dam is earthen and rockfill dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the highest stone masonry gravity dam of India as well as of the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ramganga dam",
            "b) Nagarjuna Sagar dam",
            "c) Hirakud dam",
            "d) Mettur dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ramganga dam is earthen and rockfill dam which is 128 m high. Nagarjuna Sagar Dam is 125 m high, Hirakud dam is 59 m high, and the Mettur dam is 70 m high; they all are stone masonry gravity dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Which project ranks first in the man-power utilization among the gigantic projects of its own kind in the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nagarjuna Sagar Project",
            "b) Bhakra Nangal Project",
            "c) Damodar Valley Project",
            "d) Indira Gandhi Canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main feature of the Nagarjuna Sagar Dam is the adoption of stone masonry that resulted in a large saving and created huge employment potential for the large labour force. It was designed and executed entirely by Indian Engineers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a stone masonry dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bhakra dam",
            "b) Nagarjuna Sagar Dam",
            "c) Hirakud dam",
            "d) Tehri dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hirakud dam is a composite dam of earth, concrete, and stone-built across the Mahanadi River in Odisha. Bhakra Dam is a concrete gravity dam built across Sutlej River in Himachal Pradesh. Tehri Dam is a rock and earth-fill embankment dam in Uttarakhand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "The only arch dam of India is Idukki dam across Periyar River in Kerala state whose height is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 81 m",
            "b) 143 m",
            "c) 149 m",
            "d) 169 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Idukki dam is a double curvature arch dam built across the Periyar river in Kerala. It is one of the highest arch dams in Asia with a height of 169 meters. The main purpose of the dam is power generation and is owned by Kerala State Electricity Board.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "The highest dam of India is built on _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jhelum River",
            "b) Musi River",
            "c) Kaveri River",
            "d) Bhagirathi River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The highest dam of India is Tehri Dam with a height of 261 m which is built across Bhagirathi River, Uttarakhand. It is a rock and earth-fill embankment dam and is used for irrigation and power generation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The oldest dam of India is built on which river?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Krishna River",
            "b) Kaveri River",
            "c) Damodar River",
            "d) Kallada River"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The oldest dam of India is Kallanai (also known as Grand Anicut) is built across the Kaveri River and is situated near Salem (Tamil Nadu state). It was constructed by the Chola king Karikala.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Gravity dam is most suitable when the foundation is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) weak",
            "b) strong",
            "c) with heavy overburden",
            "d) rocky but cracked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A gravity dam is the one in which the stability against external load is achieved by the weight of the dam itself. This type of dam requires minimum maintenance. It can be constructed on any site where the natural foundation is strong enough to bear the weight of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of dam is built in areas where the foundation is not strong enough to bear the weight of concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock-fill dam",
            "b) Earth dam",
            "c) Gravity dam",
            "d) Arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An earth dam is built up by compacting successive layers of the earth with vibrating or heavy machinery. It is built in areas where the earth is more easily available as compared to concrete or stone or rock.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is partly earthen and partly rockfill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tehri dam",
            "b) Koyna dam",
            "c) Sardar Sarovar dam",
            "d) Bhakra dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Koyna dam is a rubble-concrete dam which is built on Koyna River near Satara district in Maharashtra. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is a gravity dam on the Narmada River, Gujrat and Bhakra dam is also a concrete gravity dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Idukki dam is a type of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rockfill dam",
            "b) a hollow masonry gravity dam",
            "c) arch dam",
            "d) steel dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Idukki dam is a double curvature arch dam constructed across the Periyar River and has a height of about 170 m. It is one of the highest arch dams in Asia and it was constructed and owned by Kerala State Electricity Board.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "In which of the following dam the weight of water is carried by a deck of RCC or by arches that share the weight burden?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earth dams",
            "b) Rockfill dams",
            "c) A hollow masonry gravity dam",
            "d) Timber dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Hollow Masonry Gravity dam contains less concrete or masonry (about 35 to 40%) than solid masonry gravity dam. They are difficult to build and the labor cost is too high to build its complex structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "It is possible to construct steel dam only up to a height of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 m",
            "b) 10 m",
            "c) 20 m",
            "d) 50 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Steel dams are not in common use and it is possible to build the dam up to a height of 18 to 20 m. They are used as coffer dams for the construction of permanent dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "The temporary structures that are built to enclose certain worksite is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) storage dam",
            "b) coffer dam",
            "c) timber dam",
            "d) steel dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coffer dams are temporary structures that are used to divert the flow to enable construction activity in the main river channel. It is also used to enclose certain work site. Steel and timber dams are also used as coffer dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is suitable for narrow valleys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arch dam",
            "b) Steel dam",
            "c) Coffer dam",
            "d) Timber dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An arch dam is that dam in which stability of the dam against external forces is obtained partly due to the weight of the dam and partly due to transferring horizontal pressure to the abutments. The presence of sound abutments is an important requirement and is suitable for narrow valleys.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "When sand and gravel foundation strata are available at a proposed dam site of moderate height, the dam may be of the type ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) earthen or rockfill dam",
            "b) masonry gravity dam",
            "c) concrete gravity dam",
            "d) double arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The piles of loose rocks and boulders in the river bed are nothing but rockfill. On the upstream face of the dam, a slab of reinforced concrete is often laid to make it watertight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "According to the Hydraulic design, the dams are classified as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) diversion and detention Dams",
            "b) storage and diversion dams",
            "c) overflow and non-overflow dam",
            "d) arch and buttress dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dams are classified as Over-flow dam and Non-over flow dam according to the hydraulic design. When water flows over the crest of the dam it is known as the overflow dam. The dams which do not allow water to flow over the crest of the dam is called non-overflow dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "A dam reservoir which is not provided with gate controls on its spillway and other sluices is called ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) detention dam",
            "b) storage reservoir",
            "c) retarding basin",
            "d) flood control reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Storage reservoir is the one having gates and valves installed at its spillway and at its sluice outlets. The retarding basin is the one with uncontrolled and ungated outlets. The cost of gate installation is saved and there are no gates hence, the possibility of human error and negligence in their operation is eliminated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "A hydel power project has been envisaged to serve the water supply and irrigation needs of the area at its inception stage. The dam reservoir so constructed is known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) multipurpose reservoir",
            "b) single-purpose reservoir",
            "c) distribution reservoir",
            "d) retarding reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A reservoir planned and constructed to serve various purposes together is a multipurpose reservoir. It is designed to protect the downstream areas from floods, to conserve water, irrigation, industrial needs, hydroelectric purposes, etc. Bhakra dam and Nagarjuna Sagar dam are important multipurpose dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "A dam reservoir catering to flood control, irrigation, and water supply basically designed for irrigation alone is a _______________-",
        "Options": [
            "a) multipurpose reservoir",
            "b) single-purpose reservoir",
            "c) distribution reservoir",
            "d) retarding basins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A reservoir planned, designed and constructed for one purpose is called a single purpose reservoir whereas a reservoir planned and constructed to serve various purposes together is a multipurpose reservoir. A small storage reservoir constructed within a city water supply system is called distribution reservoir\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which reservoir is also known as Mitigation reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conservation reservoir",
            "b) Flood control reservoir",
            "c) Multipurpose dam",
            "d) Storage reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A flood control reservoir protects the downstream areas by storing a portion of the flood flows to minimize the flood peaks. The entire inflow entering the reservoir is discharged or gradually released to recover the capacity for the next flood. It is also called as a mitigation reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "A reservoir having gates and valves installation at its spillway and at its sluice outlets ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) storage reservoir",
            "b) retarding basin",
            "c) both storage and retarding reservoir",
            "d) distribution reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Storage reservoir is the one having gates and valves installed at its spillway and at its sluice outlets whereas retarding basin is the one with uncontrolled and ungated outlets. It provides more flexibility in operation and better control.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Which reservoir is helpful in permitting the pumps or the water treatment plants to work at a uniform rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage reservoir",
            "b) Detention reservoir",
            "c) Multipurpose reservoir",
            "d) Distribution reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A small storage reservoir constructed within a city water supply system is called a distribution reservoir. It stores water during hours of no demand or less demand and supply water from their storage during the critical time of maximum demand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "In which of the following reservoir the flood crest downstream can be better controlled and regulated properly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distribution reservoir",
            "b) Multipurpose reservoir",
            "c) Storage reservoir",
            "d) Retarding reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Storage reservoirs are preferred on large rivers and require better control. It is provided with gated spillway and sluiceways for more flexibility of operation, better control and to increase the usefulness of the reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What are the types of flood control reservoirs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multipurpose reservoir and Single purpose reservoir",
            "b) Storage reservoir and retarding reservoirs",
            "c) Distribution reservoir and Storage reservoir",
            "d) Distribution reservoir and multipurpose reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two basic types of flood-mitigation reservoirs i.e. storage reservoir and retarding reservoirs. Storage reservoir is the one having gates and valves installed at its spillway and at its sluice outlets whereas the retarding basin is the one with uncontrolled and ungated outlets.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "What is the most important physical characteristic of a reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage capacity",
            "b) Annual Yield",
            "c) Average yield",
            "d) Reservoir water level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main function of a reservoir is to store water and thus to stabilize the flow of water therefore, the most important physical characteristic is its storage capacity. It is determined from the contour maps of the area. The planimeter is used to measure the area enclosed within each contour.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "In general practice adopted for capacity computations is to actually survey the site contours only at vertical distances of __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 m or more",
            "b) Less than 5 m",
            "c) 0.5 m or more",
            "d) Less than 0.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The area of the intervening contours at smaller intervals of 0.5 m or so and at vertical distances of 5 m or so. It is then interpolated by taking the square root of the surveyed contours. It is also assumed that the square root of the interpolated ones varies in exact proportion to their vertical distances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following method does not give more than 3% error in the determination of the capacity of a reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prismoidal formula",
            "b) Trapezoidal method",
            "c) Average formula",
            "d) Integration method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surveyed area at large intervals is plotted on a graph and area-elevation curve is drawn. The equation of this curve can be obtained by statistical methods. It can be integrated to obtain the equation of the capacity-elevation curve to obtain storage capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "The surcharge storage in a dam reservoir is the volume of water stored ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) between the minimum and maximum reservoir levels",
            "b) between the minimum and normal reservoir levels",
            "c) between normal and maximum reservoir levels",
            "d) below the minimum pool level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The capacity of the reservoir can be determined by surveying only a few contours by using this method. When it is cross-checked with the capacity worked out by surveying a large number of contours this method gives less than 3% error. Since the areas of contours are not very precise figures this error is not considered much.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "The useful storage in a dam reservoir is the volume of water stored __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) between the minimum and maximum reservoir levels",
            "b) between the minimum and normal reservoir levels",
            "c) between normal and maximum reservoir levels",
            "d) below the minimum pool level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surcharge storage is uncontrolled storage which is the volume of water stored between the normal pool level and the maximum pool level. It is that portion above the crest of the dam’s spillway which cannot be regulated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The dead storage in a dam reservoir is the available volume for collection of silt and sediment between _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bed level of the reservoir and minimum reservoir level",
            "b) bed level of the reservoir and the silt level in the reservoir",
            "c) bed level of the reservoir and the normal pool level",
            "d) above the minimum pool level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Useful storage can be defined as the volume of water stored in a reservoir between the minimum pool and normal pool level. Conservation storage and flood-mitigation storage are the two sub-divisions of useful storage in a multi-purpose reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Bank storage in a dam reservoir _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases the compound reservoir capacity",
            "b) decreases the computed reservoir capacity",
            "c) sometimes increases and sometimes decreases the computed reservoir capacity",
            "d) has no effect on computed reservoir capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Useful storage can be defined as the volume of water stored in a reservoir between the minimum pool and normal pool level. Dead storage is the water stored in the reservoir below the minimum pool level. It is not of much use in the operation of reservoirs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "The maximum level to which the water rises during the worst design flood is known as _________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) full Reservoir level",
            "b) maximum conservation level",
            "c) minimum pool level",
            "d) surcharge storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The certain amount of water that seeps into the permeable reservoir banks when the reservoir is filled up is known as bank storage. This water comes out as soon as the reservoir gets depleted and it effectively increases the capacity of the reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula can be used to determine the storage when three consecutive sections at equal height are taken?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prismoidal formula",
            "b) Trapezoidal method",
            "c) Average formula",
            "d) Integration method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective storage for flood mitigation is equal to the useful storage plus surcharge storage minus valley storage i.e. storage corresponding to the rate of inflow in the reservoir. The actual net increase in the storage is equal to the storage capacity of the reservoir minus the natural valley storage. Thus, the available storage is reduced for flood mitigation reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Average yield of a storage reservoir is the arithmetic average of its ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) firm yields over a long period",
            "b) secondary yields over a long period",
            "c) firm and secondary yields over a long period",
            "d) reservoir yield over a long period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Firm yield is the yield corresponding to the most critical year on record. Secondary yield is the water available in excess of the firm yield during years of higher inflows. Average yield is the average of both firm yield and secondary yield.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "While planning a water supply reservoir as compared to an irrigation reservoir the design yield may be kept __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) higher",
            "b) lower",
            "c) equal",
            "d) lower or higher as per designers discretion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dependability percentage value will depend upon the risk which can be absorbed for the proposed use of water. The city water supply projects can absorb lesser risk as compared to the irrigation projects. Hence, higher percentage values are considered.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Yield of a reservoir represents ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the inflow into the reservoir",
            "b) the capacity of the reservoir",
            "c) the outflow demand on the reservoir",
            "d) the optimum value of catchment yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The yield of the catchment is the long-range runoff from a catchment. It helps in designing the capacity of the reservoir. The outflow from the reservoir (reservoir yield) is represented by the mass demand line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Design yield of a storage reservoir is kept _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) higher than its firm or safe yield",
            "b) lower than its firm or safe yield",
            "c) equal to its firm or safe yield",
            "d) higher or lower than the firm yield depending upon the designer’s intuition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An intermediate dependability percentage such as 50% to 75% is used to compute the design yield or dependable yield. This value will depend upon the risk which can be absorbed for the proposed use of water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Who did the first effort to give empirical relations for converting the yearly rainfall value into the yearly runoff for the given catchment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mr. W L Strange",
            "b) Alexander Binnie",
            "c) Mr. T.G Barlow",
            "d) Sir Inglis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first effort made in India was from Sir Alexander Binnie to connect the long-range rainfall and the yield. The observations were made on two rivers in the central provinces for the entire monsoon period. He worked out certain percentages to connect the monthly rainfall with the monthly yield which was further adjusted by Mr. Garret.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "In which of the following method, the catchments were categorized as good, bad and average catchments to account for the general characteristics of the catchment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binnie’s percentages",
            "b) Strange’s tables",
            "c) Barlow’s tables",
            "d) Inglis formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strange’s tables was an improvement over Binnie’s tables. The catchments prone to producing higher yield were good catchments and that of low yields were bad catchments. Average catchments were the intermediate types.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "What is the value of Barlow’s runoff percentage (K) for hills and plains with little cultivation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 15",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For Flat, cultivated, and adsorbent soils, the runoff percentage is taken as 10 and for flat, partly cultivated stiff soils, it is taken as 15. For average catchment, the value is taken as 20 and for hills and plains with little cultivation, the value of the runoff percentage is 25.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "What is the value of Lacey’s monsoon duration factor for a good year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1.2",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 1.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The monsoon duration factor (m) for a bad year is 0.5 and that of the normal year the value is 1.2. For a good year, the monsoon duration factor is 1.5.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following yield formula is used for the catchments of West Maharashtra state of India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inglis formula",
            "b) Khosla’s formula",
            "c) Lacey’s formula",
            "d) Barlow’s table"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inglis formula was given by Sir Inglis derived his formula for catchments of Maharashtra state of India. He divided the areas into ghat areas (Sahyadri ranges) and non-ghat areas depending upon the rainfall intensity and gave the formula to determine the yield.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula for calculating yield can be applied to all catchments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inglis formula",
            "b) Khosla’s formula",
            "c) Lacey’s formula",
            "d) Barlow’s table"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Khosla formula is based upon the recent research work conducted in the field. It is a simple and useful formula and can be applied to the entire country. The formula is given as-\nYield (Q) = P – 0.48 Tm where Q = the yield in cm, P = rainfall in cm, and Tm = mean annual temperature of the area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "According to the Inglis formula, the non-ghat areas are the one where rainfall is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 cm or more",
            "b) 200 cm or less",
            "c) 100 cm or more",
            "d) 100 cm or less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ghat area is the one where rainfall is 200 cm or more and in non-ghat areas the rainfall is less than 200 cm. The formulas are-\nFor ghat areas, Yield = (0.85P – 30.48)\nFor non-ghat areas, Yield = [P (P – 17.78)] / 254 where P is the rainfall in cm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "The design annual rainfall for the catchment of a proposed reservoir has been computed to be 99 cm. The catchment area contributing to the proposed reservoir is 1000 sq.km having a mean annual temperature of 20°C. Calculate the annual design catchment yield for the reservoir using Khosla’s formula.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 89.4 M.m3",
            "b) 8.94 M.m3",
            "c) 894 m3",
            "d) 894 M.m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Using Khosla’s formula –\nQ = P – 0.48 Tm where, Rainfall (P) = 99 cm and Mean annual temperature (Tm) = 20°C\nQ = 99 – 0.48 x 20 = 89.4 cm = 0.894 m\nThe total yield produced from the given catchment = 0.894 x 1000 x 106 = 894 M.m3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "With the reduction in reservoir capacity over the passage of time, the trap efficiency ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) remains unaffected",
            "d) may increase or decrease depending upon the reservoir characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reservoir capacity is fixed at a value which is lesser of the value of –\ni. The accessed gross storage required to meet the demand\nii. The accessed dependable yield for the reservoir site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Trap efficiency of a storage reservoir is defined as the ratio of ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) total annual sediment inflow to the reservoir capacity",
            "b) total sediment deposited in a given period to the total sediment inflow in that period",
            "c) total annual sediment deposited in the reservoir to the dead storage capacity of the reservoir",
            "d) reservoir capacity to the total annual sediment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the reservoir capacity reduces with constant inflow value, the trap efficiency reduces. Hence, for small reservoirs having small capacity on large rivers having large inflow rates, the trap efficiency is extremely low.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Capacity inflow ratio for a storage reservoir is defined as the ratio of  _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reservoir capacity to the average annual flood inflow",
            "b) reservoir capacity to the average annual sediment inflow",
            "c) the dead storage capacity of the reservoir to the average annual sediment deposited",
            "d) total annual sediment inflow to the reservoir capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trap efficiency of a storage reservoir is defined as the ratio of the total sediment deposited in a given period to the total sediment inflow in that period. It can be defined as the percentage of sediment deposited in the reservoir in spite of taking precautionary control measures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "The capacity-inflow ratio for a reservoir _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) is a constant factor overtime",
            "b) increases with time",
            "c) decreases with time",
            "d) may increase or decrease with time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacity-inflow ratio can be defined as the ratio of the reservoir capacity to the total inflow of water. The trap efficient is a function of the capacity-inflow ratio which is represented by a graph between them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "A sequent peak algorithm is a plot between __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accumulated flow v/s time",
            "b) Discharge v/s time",
            "c) (Cumulative Inflow – Cumulative Outflow) v/s time",
            "d) Mass outflow v/s time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The silting rate in the reservoir will be more in the beginning as its capacity reduces due to silting, the silting rate will also reduce. The trap efficiency is a function of capacity. The capacity reduces when trap efficiency reduces and lesser sediment is trapped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "A flow duration curve is a curve plotted between ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accumulated flow v/s time",
            "b) Discharge v/s time",
            "c) (Cumulative Inflow – Cumulative Outflow) v/s time",
            "d) Streamflow v/s Percent of time the flow is equaled or exceeded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is a plot between time on X-axis and cumulative net flow on Y-axis. It is an excellent alternative to the mass-curve method of determining reservoir capacity. The positive value of cumulative net flow indicates a surplus of inflow and a negative value indicates a deficit of inflow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "A steep slope of the flow duration curve indicates a stream with _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) highly variable discharge",
            "b) small variability of flow",
            "c) considerable base flow",
            "d) large flood plains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A flow-duration curve is a curve plotted between the streamflow and the percent of the time the flow is equaled or exceeded. It is also called a discharge-frequency curve and it represents the cumulative frequency distribution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "The economical height of a dam is that height for which the ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cost per unit of storage is minimum",
            "b) benefit-cost ratio is maximum",
            "c) net benefits are maximum",
            "d) benefit-cost ratio is minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cost per unit storage of the dam initially decreases reaches to a certain minimum value and then increases when the height of the dam is increased. This lowest point on the curve gives the economical height for which the cost per unit storage is minimum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "If 20% of the reservoir capacity is earmarked for dead storage in a storage reservoir of 30 M.cum and the average annual silt deposition in the reservoir is 0.1 M cum, then the useful life of the reservoir will start reducing after ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 years",
            "b) 120 years",
            "c) 240 years",
            "d) 300 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height of the dam corresponding to which the cost of the dam per unit storage is minimum is the economical height of the dam. The cost per unit storage of the dam initially decreases reaches to a certain minimum value and then increases when the height of the dam is increased.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "According to the Central Water Commission, the average annual evaporation loss is estimated to be _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 cm",
            "b) 125 cm",
            "c) 225 cm",
            "d) 250 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Given, Reservoir capacity = 30 M.cum\nDead storage is 20% of the reservoir capacity = 0.2 x 30 = 6 M.cum\nTime during which 6 M cum is filled by sediment @0.1 M.cum/yr = 6/0.1 = 60 years.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "Windbreakers, Integrated operation of reservoirs and Use of underground storage are all methods of ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) evaporation control",
            "b) estimation of absorption losses",
            "c) estimation of absorption losses",
            "d) estimation of reservoir leakage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Central Water Commission in 1990 has estimated the average annual evaporation loss to be 225 cm on the basis of a review conducted on 130 sample reservoirs. The estimated total water loss from all the existing reservoirs to be 27000 Mm3 per annum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as WERs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hexa decanol",
            "b) Octa decanol",
            "c) Docosanol",
            "d) Cyclohexanol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The following are some of the methods of evaporation control such as Windbreakers, Reduction in the exposed water surface, Use of underground storage rather than surface storage, Integrated operation of reservoirs, and Use of chemical for retarding the evaporation rate from the reservoir surface. Use of Water Evapo-Retardants (WERs) is considered to be an only practical solution for the conservation of freshwater in spite of its limitations and disadvantages.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is situated in the seismologically inactive zone in Peninsular India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Koyna dam",
            "b) Hirakud dam",
            "c) Tehri dam",
            "d) Idukki dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fatty alcohols like Cetyl alcohol (popularly known as Hexa decanol), Stearyl alcohol (also called Octadecanol), and Behenyl alcohol (also called docosanol) are found to be quite suitable. A mixture of these chemicals have also been generally used and the chemicals should be 99% pure for getting the desired properties of the monolayer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which of the following measure does not prevent or reduce the intensity of the earthquake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filling the reservoir up to a limited safe level",
            "b) Draining out water from weaker adjoining rocks",
            "c) Active exploration of the dam site for the absence of inactive faults before selecting the same",
            "d) Increasing the pore pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A very strange phenomenon has been observed in several dams of the world, the reservoir basins which were seismologically inactive started showing seismic activities when the reservoir was filled up with water. Koyna dam (Maharashtra) is an important example of such a case.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Which of the following guideline is incorrect for the selection of a suitable site for a reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The geological formation should be such that it entails minimum leakage",
            "b) The cost of the dam is a controlling factor",
            "c) Too much silt-laden tributaries should be avoided as far as possible",
            "d) The reservoir basin should have a shallow wide opening in the valley"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Earthquakes occur due to increased pore-pressure in the adjoining rocks which lowers their shearing strength resulting in the release of tectonic strain. Draining out water from weaker adjoining rocks actually reduces pore pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "The vertical component of the earthquake wave which produces adverse effects on the stability of a dam when is acting in ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) upward direction",
            "b) downward direction",
            "c) both upward and downward direction",
            "d) any direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the vertical acceleration is acting downward the foundation try to move downward away from the dam body. This reduces the effective weight and the stability of the dam. It is the worst case for design.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "The horizontal component of an earthquake wave producing instability in a dam is the one which acts __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) towards the reservoir",
            "b) towards the dam",
            "c) away from the reservoir",
            "d) away from the dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrodynamic pressure and horizontal inertia force are caused by the horizontal acceleration of an earthquake wave acting towards the reservoir. As the foundation and dam accelerate towards the reservoir there is an increase in the water pressure which is resisted by water, the extra pressure is hydrodynamic pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "The vertical downward earthquake acceleration av = 0.1g acting on a gravity dam will ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase the resisting weight of the dam by 10%",
            "b) decrease the resisting weight of the dam by 10%",
            "c) increase the uplift by 10%",
            "d) decrease the uplift by 10%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The net effective weight of the dam is given as W [1 – Kv] and vertical acceleration av = Kv.g = 0.1.g i.e 10%\nwhere W is the total weight of the dam and Kv is the fraction of gravity adopted for vertical acceleration.\nThis is considered as the worst case for design as the foundation tries to move downward away from the dam body when there is downward vertical acceleration. This reduces the effective weight and the stability of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "A gravity dam is subjected to hydrodynamic pressure caused by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the rising waves of the reservoir when a flood wave enters into it",
            "b) the rising waves in the reservoir due to high winds",
            "c) the increase in water pressure momentarily caused by the horizontal earthquake acting towards the reservoir",
            "d) the increase in water pressure momentarily caused by the horizontal earthquake acting towards the dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrodynamic pressure is the extra pressure exerted when the horizontal acceleration of an earthquake wave is acting towards the reservoir. As the foundation and dam accelerate towards the reservoir there is an increase in the water pressure which is nothing but hydrostatic pressure acting at a height of 3H/4π above the base. Mathematically, this value is given by Von-Karman equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "In a concrete gravity dam with a vertical upstream face the stabilising force is provided by the ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) weight of the dam",
            "b) the water supported against the upstream slope",
            "c) uplift pressure",
            "d) water pressure at the tail end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The major resisting force is the weight of the dam body and its foundation. A unit length of the dam is considered in the 2D analysis of a gravity dam. The resultant of all the downward forces will represent the total weight of the dam acting on it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "What is the value of horizontal destabilizing force caused by the formation of waves in a storage reservoir having a fetch of 52 km due to high wind of 172 km/h?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 KN",
            "b) 60 KN",
            "c) 130 KN",
            "d) 180 KN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When F > 32 km, the wave height is given by hw = 0.032 (V.F)1/2\nhw = 0.032 (172 x 52)1/2 = 3.02 m\nThe force caused by waves is given by the equation – Pw = 19.62 hw2 KN/m run of the dam\nPw = 19.62 x 3.022 = 179.69 KN.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of free-board that should be provided for a reservoir having a wind velocity of 92 km/h and it extends up to 18 km upstream.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 m",
            "b) 1.6 m",
            "c) 2.25 m",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When F < 32 km, the wave height is given by – Hw = 0.032(V.F)1/2 + 0.763 – 0.271 F1/4\nHw = 0.032(92 x 18)1/2 + 0.763 – 0.271 (18)1/4 = 1.5 m\nFree board is generally provided equal to 1.5 Hw = 1.5 x 1.5 = 2.25 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "The upward acceleration of dam due to seismic activity will ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase the base pressure",
            "b) decrease the base pressure",
            "c) not affect the effective weight of the dam",
            "d) increase the horizontal dynamic force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vertical acceleration can be resolved in two parts i.e. upward vertical accelerations and downward vertical accelerations. The effective weight of the dam increases when there is an upward vertical acceleration as it brings the foundation closer to the dam. In downward acceleration, the effective weight reduces and is considered as the worst design case.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "What is the average value of acceleration that is sufficient for high dams in seismic zones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1g to 0.15g",
            "b) 0.05g to 0.1g",
            "c) 0.3gs",
            "d) 0.15g (where g is the acceleration due to gravity)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An average value of acceleration equal to 0.1 to 0.15 g is sufficient for high dams in seismic zones and for areas not subjected to extreme earthquake ah = 0.1 g and av = 0.05 g may be used. These forces are neglected in areas of no earthquake or very less earthquake.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "What is Von Karman’s formula for hydrodynamic force (Pe)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pe = 0.726 pe H",
            "b) Pe = 0.424 pe H",
            "c) Pe = 0.555 pe H",
            "d) Pe = 0.555.Kh. Yw H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Von-Karman, the hydrodynamic force is given by –\nPe = 0.555. Kh. ϒw H2 where, ϒw is the unit weight of water, H is the depth of water and Kh is a fraction of gravity adapted for horizontal acceleration which acts at the height of 4H/3π above the base. In addition to this, an inertia force is also produced by the horizontal acceleration into the body of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "The factor of safety against overturning generally varies between ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 3",
            "b) 1.5 to 2",
            "c) 0.5 to 1.5",
            "d) 1 to 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Factor of safety against overturning can be determined by the ratio of righting moments about the toe to the overturning moments about the toe. The value generally varies between 2 to 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "What is the maximum permissible tensile stress for high concrete gravity dam under worst conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500 KN/m2",
            "b) 500 kg/cm2",
            "c) 5 kg/m2",
            "d) 50 KN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The masonry and concrete gravity dams are usually designed in such a way that no tension is developed anywhere in the structure. The maximum permissible tensile stress for high gravity dams is taken as 500 KN/m2 under worst conditions. If subjected to such tensile stresses crack develops near the heel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Which failure occurs when the net horizontal force above any plane in the dam or at the base of the dam exceeds the frictional resistance developed at that level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overturning",
            "b) Crushing",
            "c) Sliding",
            "d) BY development of tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sliding should always be fully resisted. At any horizontal section of the dam, the factor of safety against sliding is –\nFOS = u Ph / Pv where u = coefficient of friction, Ph = Sum of horizontal forces causing sliding and Pv = Algebraic sum of vertical forces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Which failure occurs when the minimum stress exceeds the allowable compressive stress of the dam material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overturning",
            "b) Crushing",
            "c) Sliding",
            "d) By development of tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The compressive stress produced if exceeds the allowable stresses then the dam material may get crushed, a dam may fail by the failure of its own material. The allowable compressive stress of concrete is generally taken as 3000 KN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Tension cracks in the dam may sometimes lead to the failure of the structure by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sliding of the dam at the cracked section",
            "b) Overturning about the toe",
            "c) Crushing of concrete starting from the toe",
            "d) Both overturning and crushing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When tension prevails, cracks develop near the heel and uplift pressure increases, reducing the net salinizing force. This crack by itself does not fail the structure but it leads to failure of the structure by producing excessive compressive stresses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "The major principal stress at the toe of a gravity dam under full reservoir condition neglecting the tailwater effect is given by ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pv",
            "b) Pv tanQ2",
            "c) Pv secQ2",
            "d) Pv sinQ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When there is no tailwater, the principal stress in such a case is Pv secQ2 where Pv is the intensity of vertical pressure. This value of principal stress should not be allowed to exceed the maximum allowable compressive stress of dam material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Which of the following criteria has to be satisfied for no tension at any point on a gravity dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The resultant of all the forces must always pass through the mid-point of the base of the dam",
            "b) The resultant force for all conditions of loading must pass through the middle third of the base",
            "c) The resultant of all the forces must pass through the upstream extremity of the middle third of the base",
            "d) The resultant of all the forces must pass through the downstream extremity of the middle third of the base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum vertical stress Pmin is equal to zero in order to ensure that no tension is developed anywhere. If Pmin = 0, e = B/6 i.e. the maximum value of eccentricity that can be permitted on either side of the center is equal to B/6. This concludes the fact that the resultant of all forces must lie within the middle third of the joint width.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "The bottom portion of a concrete or a masonry gravity dam is usually stepped in order to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase the overturning resistance of the dam",
            "b) increase the shear strength",
            "c) decrease the shear strength",
            "d) increase the frictional resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The foundation is stepped at the base to increase the shear strength at the base and at other joints and measures is taken to ensure a better bond between the dam and the rock foundation. By ensuring a better bond between the surfaces the shear strength of these joints should be made as good as possible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "The governing compressive stress in a concrete gravity dam which should not be allowed to exceed the permissible value of about 3000 KN/m2 while analyzing full reservoir case is ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the vertical maximum stress at the toe",
            "b) the major principal stress at toe",
            "c) the shear stress at the toe",
            "d) the principal stress at the heel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In reservoir full case, the resultant is nearer to the toe and hence, maximum compressive stress is produced at the toe. The vertical direct stress distribution at the base is the sum of the direct stress and the bending stress and is given by the equation –\nPmax = V/B [1 + 6e/B] where V is the total vertical force, e is the eccentricity of the resultant force from the center of the base and B is the base width.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "When the reservoir is empty, the single force acting on it is the self-weight of the dam which acts at a distance of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) B/2 from the heel",
            "b) B/6 from the heel",
            "c) B/3 from the heel",
            "d) B/4 from the heel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The only single force on the dam when the reservoir is empty is the self-weight of the dam acting at a distance of B/3 from the heel. It provides maximum possible stabilizing moment about the toe without causing tension.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "When the reservoir is empty, the maximum vertical stress equal to ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) At heel = 2W/B and at toe = 0",
            "b) At heel = 0 and at toe = 2W/B",
            "c) At heel = toe = zero",
            "d) At heel = toe = 2W/B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical stress distribution at the base when the reservoir is empty is given as –\nPmax/min = V/B [1 + 6e/B] and V/B [1 – 6e/B] where e = B/6 and V = total vertical force = weight W\nPmax = 2W/B and Pmin = 0.\nThe maximum vertical stress at the heel is equal to 2W/B and at the toe is zero.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of minimum base width for an elementary triangular concrete gravity dam supporting 72 m height of reservoir water and full uplift? (Take specific gravity of concrete as 2.4 and coefficient of friction as 0.7)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36.28 m",
            "b) 39.77 m",
            "c) 51.5 m",
            "d) 73.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transverse joints in the dam body are generally not grouted in U-shaped valleys but are keyed together in V-shaped valleys. In V-shaped valleys, the entire length of the dam acts monolithically as a single body. The assumption that the dam is considered to made up of a number of cantilevers of unit width each may involve errors here.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "For usual values of permissible compressive stress and specific gravity of concrete, a high concrete gravity is the one whose height exceeds ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48 m",
            "b) 70 m",
            "c) 88 m",
            "d) 98 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Using formula –\nCase 1: B = H / (Sc – c)1/2 (For full uplift c = 1 and specific gravity of concrete = 2.4 )\n= 72/ (2.4 – 1)1/2 = 60.85 m\nCase 2: B = H/μ (S – 1) where μ = coefficient of friction taken as 0.7\nB = 72 / 0.7 x 1.4 = 73.46 m\nThe highest among the two base width value is to be selected i.e. B = 73.46 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "For triangular dam section of height H for just no tension under the action of water pressure, self-weight and uplift pressure, the minimum base width required is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H / (S-1)",
            "b) H / S1/2",
            "c) H / (S – 1)-1",
            "d) H / (S-1)1/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The limiting height is – Hmax = f / (Sc + 1) ϒw Permissible strength of concrete = 3000 KN/m2, Sc = specific gravity of concrete = 2.4\nHmax = 3000/[(2.4 + 1) x 9.81] = 89.9 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "If the eccentricity of the resultant falls outside the middle third, the ultimate failure of the dam occurs by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tension",
            "b) crushing",
            "c) sliding",
            "d) overturning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum base width (B) of a gravity dam having an elementary profile –\nB = H / (S – 1)-1 where S is specific gravity of concrete and H is the height of water.\nIf uplift is not considered – B = H/S1/2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "What is the value of eccentricity for no tension condition in the dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) e < B/6",
            "b) e > B/6",
            "c) e > B/3",
            "d) e < B/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When eccentricity is greater than B/6 (eccentricity falls outside the middle third), tension may develop. When tension prevails, cracks develop near the heel and uplift pressure distribution increases reducing the net salinizing force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "What is the formula for limiting height of a gravity dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hmax = f / (Sc + 1) γw",
            "b) Hmax = f / (Sc – 1) γw",
            "c) Hmax = f / (Sc + C) γw",
            "d) Hmax = f / (Sc – 1) γw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resultant of all the forces i.e hydrostatic water pressure, uplift pressure and self-weight of the dam should always lie within the middle third of the base for no tension. When e < B/6, the value of stress intensity at toe and heel are positive i.e compression on both sides.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "Calculate the top width of the dam if the height of water stored is 84m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 m",
            "b) 2.5 m",
            "c) 5.55 m",
            "d) 7.75 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical height or limiting height of a dam having elementary profile is –\nHmax = f / (Sc + 1) γw where f = allowable stress of the dam material, Sc = Specific gravity of concrete and γw = unit weight of water.\nThis limiting height draws a dividing line between a low gravity dam and a high gravity dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "For full reservoir condition in a gravity dam, the critical combination of vertical and horizontal earthquake accelerations to be considered for checking the stability is ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertically upward and horizontally downstream",
            "b) vertically downward and horizontally downstream",
            "c) vertically upward and horizontally upstream",
            "d) vertically downward and horizontally upstream"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The safety against sliding should be checked only for friction in case of low dams and in high dams, the shear strength of the joint (i.e. an additional shear resistance) is also considered for economical design. The dam section is given an extra slope or batter on the U/s or D/s side as per requirements for achieving stability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "The base width of a solid gravity dam is 35 m and the specific gravity of dam material is 2.45. What is the approximate allowable height of the dam having an elementary profile without considering the uplift?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 64.68 m",
            "b) 54.80 m",
            "c) 164 m",
            "d) 80 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Horizontal inertia force should be considered to be acting at the center of the gravity of the mass regardless of the shape of cross-section and it acts horizontally downstream in worst cases under full reservoir case. This force would produce the worst results is it is additive to the hydrostatic water pressure (acting towards the downstream).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "A low gravity dam of elementary profile made up of concrete of relative density 2.57 and safe allowable stress of foundation material 4.2 MPa. What is the maximum height of the dam without considering the uplift force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 m",
            "b) 217 m",
            "c) 279 m",
            "d) 325 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The base width at bottom is given by B = H/Sc1/2 (c = 0 since uplift is not considered).\nB = 35 m and Sc = 2.45\nAllowable height of the dam H = 35 x 2.451/2 = 54.8 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "The vertical stress at the toe was found to be 3.44 MPa at the base of the gravity dam section. If the downstream face of the dam has a slope of 0.617 horizontal: 1 vertical, the maximum principal stress at the toe of the dam when there is no tailwater is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7 MPa",
            "b) 2.4 MPa",
            "c) 3.6 MPa",
            "d) 4.8 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum possible height of low gravity dam is H = f / ϒw (Sc + 1) where f = allowable stress of dam material = 4.2 MPa, Sc = 2.57, and ϒw = 9.81 KN/m2.\nH = [4.2 / (9.81 x 3.57)] x 1000 = 119.92 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "What is the recommended value of shear friction factor against sliding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than unity",
            "b) Less than unity",
            "c) More than 3 to 5",
            "d) Less than 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The principal stress at the toe is given by Pat toe = Pv. secΦ2 (without considering the tailwater) where Pv = 3.44 MPa and tan Φ = 0.617/1 i.e.Φ  = 31.67°\nPat toe = 3.44 x sec(31.67°)2 = 4.74 MPa.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "The small openings made in the huge body of a concrete gravity dam such as sluices and inspection galleries can be assumed to be causing only local effects without any appreciable effect on the distribution of stresses as per the principle of_____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laplace",
            "b) St. Venant",
            "c) Reynold",
            "d) St. Francis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shear Friction Factor is given by –\nSFF = sliding factor (SF) + B.q / ∑Ph where B = width of joint or section area = B x 1, q is the shear strength of the joint, and Ph is the sum of horizontal force causing sliding. SF must be greater than 1 and SFF must be greater than 3 to 5. This analysis is carried out for a full reservoir case as well as an empty case.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "A concrete gravity dam having a maximum reservoir level at 200 m and the RL of the bottom of the dam 100 m. The maximum allowable compressive stress in concrete is 3000 KN/m2 and the specific gravity of concrete is 2.4. Calculate the height of the dam and check whether it is a high dam or low dam.",
        "Options": [
            "a) H = 90 m High gravity dam",
            "b) H = 90 m Low gravity dam",
            "c) H = 214.2 m High gravity dam",
            "d) H = 214.2 m Low gravity dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Small openings made in the dam only produce local effects as per St. Venant’s principle. They do not affect the general distribution of stresses. This is one of the most important assumptions made in the two-dimensional analysis of gravity dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "The axis of a gravity dam is the ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) line of the crown of the dam on the downstream side",
            "b) line of the crown of the dam on the upstream side",
            "c) centre-line of the top width of the dam",
            "d) line joining mid-points of the base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The limiting height of the dam is given by-\nH = f / ϒw (Sc + 1) where f = allowable stress of dam material = 3000 KN/m2, Sc = 2.4, and ϒw = 9.81 KN/m2.\nH = 3000 / 9.81 x 3.4 = 89.9 m.\nThis value is more than the height of the dam so it is a high gravity dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Presence of tail-water in a gravity dam ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases the principal stress and decreases the shear stress",
            "b) increases both the principal stress and the shear stress",
            "c) decreases the principal stress and increases the shear stress",
            "d) decreases both the principal stress and the shear stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The axis of the dam is taken as the reference line which is defined separately in the plan and in the cross-section of the dam. In plan, it is the horizontal trace of the U/s edge of the top of the dam. In the cross-section, the vertical line passing through the U/s edge of the top of the dam is considered as the axis of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "The provision of drainage gallery in a gravity dam helps in reducing ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrostatic pressure",
            "b) seepage pressure",
            "c) silt pressure",
            "d) both hydrostatic pressure and seepage pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An opening or passage left in the dam which runs longitudinally is called the gallery. This is to provide space for drainage of water percolating through the upstream face of the dam or seeping through the foundation. It is also used for inspection purposes and for the mechanical equipment used in the operation of gates in spillways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Transverse joints in concrete gravity dams are the ___________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal construction joints at each lift height",
            "b) vertical construction joints of full height and width",
            "c) diagonal construction joints for torsion",
            "d) longitudinal construction joints of full width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a gravity dam, the grout curtain is provided near the toe to reduce the exit gradient. A drainage gallery with its drainage pipe system provided in gravity dam reduces the uplift pressure at all levels below the upstream water level. Vertical cut-off walls are the most effective to reduce seepage flow and uplift force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Leakage through the transverse joints in a gravity dam is prevented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear keys",
            "b) keyways",
            "c) water stops",
            "d) galleries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transverse joints are vertical joints that run through the entire height and extend through the full width of the dam section. These joints are continuous from the upstream face to the downstream face.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "In order to reduce uplift on a gravity dam, the type of grouting done is ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) curtain grouting near the heel",
            "b) consolidation grouting near the heel",
            "c) curtain grouting near the toe",
            "d) consolidation grouting near the toe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water bars or water stops are provided in the transverse as well as horizontal joints in concrete adjacent to the upstream face of the dam. The openings of the joints are sealed properly with water stops to avoid passage of seepage of water through the body.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "The general value of lift for concrete is taken as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 m",
            "b) 2.5 m",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Curtain grouting helps in forming a principal barrier against the seepage through the foundations and thus reduces the uplift pressure. This grouting can be accomplished from the foundation gallery or from other galleries within the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "The horizontal joints that extends through the entire width of the dam section and are developed at each lift height is called as ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transverse joints",
            "b) longitudinal joints",
            "c) construction joints",
            "d) contraction joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The concrete is poured from a certain height in the first attempt and this height is called a lift. Maximum height of single pour of concrete is usually about 1.5 m. If this is reduced, more horizontal joints will get developed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Which of the following joints justifies the two-dimensional analysis of gravity dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinal joints",
            "b) Transverse joints",
            "c) Construction joints",
            "d) Contraction joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The longitudinal joint is developed at each lift height and extends through the entire width of the dam section. These joints shall run through the entire length of the dam but are staggered between transverse joints.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "The foundation pressure used in the pressure grouting is equal to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.0 D N/cm2",
            "b) 2.5 D N/cm2",
            "c) 5.0 D N/cm2",
            "d) 3.0 D N/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transverse joints are vertical joints that divide the dam length into a number of vertical cantilevers each of which is independent of the other. It runs through the entire height and extends through the full width of the dam section. Hence, it justifies the two-dimensional analysis of gravity dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Which of the following earth dam is suitable only on impervious foundation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zoned embankment type",
            "b) Homogenous embankment type",
            "c) Non-homogenous type",
            "d) Diaphragm type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Homogenous earth dam may be constructed of uniform and homogenous material when locally available. The percolation of water is not checked in such dams. It is suitable only on impervious foundations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following zone in Zoned type embankment prevents piping through cracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central core",
            "b) Transition zone",
            "c) Outer zone",
            "d) Core wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The outer zone is made of fairly pervious material like grit, gravel, and murrum. The innermost zone is done with fairly impervious material. The central core is covered by comparatively pervious transition zone which prevents piping through the cracks which may develop in the core.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Which of the following soil material is most preferred for the central core material of zoned embankment type dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly impervious clay",
            "b) Sands or silty clays",
            "c) Coarse sands",
            "d) Gravels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clay shrinks and swells and is highly impervious is not suitable. It is sometimes mixed with fine sand or fine gravel so as to make it a suitable material for the impervious central core. Coarse sands and gravels are used in the outer shell.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Which embankment has the thickness of the diaphragm at an elevation less than 10 meters or the height of the embankment above the corresponding elevation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diaphragm type dam",
            "b) Zoned type dam",
            "c) Non-homogenous earth dam",
            "d) Homogenous earth dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thickness of the core differentiates the diaphragm embankment from the zoned type embankment.\n\n\nEmbankment type\nThe thickness of core or diaphragm\n\n1. Diaphragm-type embankment\n< 10 m or\n< the height of embankment \n\n\n2. Zoned-type embankment\n≥ 10 m\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "The blanket in earth dam is provided ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) at the ground level on u/s side",
            "b) at the ground level on the d/s side",
            "c) at the ground level of the D/s side of the dam",
            "d) on the D/s slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A blanket of relatively impervious material may be placed on the upstream face. Since homogenous earth dam poses the problems of seepage, a homogenous section is generally added with an internal drainage system. This keeps the seepage line well within the body of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct with reference to earthen dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These dams are very costly as compared to other types",
            "b) Gravity dams are less susceptible to failure as compared to rigid dams",
            "c) These dams are suitable for construction on almost every type of foundation",
            "d) Highly skilled labor is generally not required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Earthen dams are suitable for any type of foundation but there has to be a separate provision for the spillway location. The mode of failure is sudden and requires high maintenance and the overall life is not so long. It requires low to moderately skilled labors and moderate capital cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "During the construction of an earthen dam by hydraulic fill method, development of pore pressure becomes important in the __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) central impervious core",
            "b) pervious outer shell",
            "c) transition zone",
            "d) both central core and outer shell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, an embankment is created by water and earth slurry which is discharged inwards to form a central pool at site. When water is pumped to the site it spreads the coarser material drops out first and the finest at last. Thus the core material settles within the central pool forming a zoned embankment and high pore pressures develop in the core.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "The process of laying and compacting earth in layers by power rollers under OMC for construction of earthen dams is known as ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolled fill method",
            "b) Hydraulic fill method",
            "c) OMC method",
            "d) Compaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the rolled-fill method, the embankment is constructed by placing suitable soil materials in thin layers and compacting the layers with rollers. Power-operated rollers are used for dams and ordinary road rollers can be used for low embankments. The best compaction can be obtained at the optimum moisture content (OMC).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "The central core of the zoned embankment type earth dam ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) checks the seepage",
            "b) prevents piping",
            "c) gives stability to the central impervious fill",
            "d) distribute the load over a large area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The central core or hearting is done with fairly impervious material and it checks the seepage. The transition zone of mediocre permeability prevents piping through cracks. The outer zone gives stability to the central fill.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Which type of dam is suitable on shallow pervious foundations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zoned embankment type",
            "b) Homogenous embankment type",
            "c) Both Non-homogenous type and homogenous type",
            "d) Diaphragm type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zoned earth dam is also called a non-homogenous or heterogeneous earth dam and it is suitable on shallow pervious foundations. This dam is widely constructed and the materials of the zone are selected depending upon the availabilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "What is the U.S.B.R recommended value for freeboard when the height of the dam is more than 60 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 m to 3 m",
            "b) 2.5 m above the top of gates",
            "c) 3 m above the top of gates",
            "d) More than 3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For controlled spillway, if the height of the dam is less than 60 m, the minimum recommended freeboard value is 2.5 m above the top of gates. If the height of the dam is more than 60 m, the minimum freeboard value is 3 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "What is the recommended formula for top width of a very low dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H + 3",
            "b) 0.2H + 3",
            "c) 0.2 H",
            "d) H + 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The top width (A) is generally governed by minimum roadway width requirements in case of small dams. The top width of the earth dam for very low dams is given by –\nA = H/5 + 3 where H is the height of the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "What is the Terzaghi’s recommended value of U/s side slope for earth dam of height less than 15m of homogenous silty clay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2: 1",
            "b) 2.5: 1",
            "c) 3: 1",
            "d) 3.5: 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For earth dams of homogenous silty clay of height less than 15 m, the recommended u/s slope is 2.5: 1 and d/s slope is 2: 1. For height more than 15 m, u/s slope value is 3: 1 and d/s slope is 2.5: 1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "If the height of the dam is 10 m, then the value of top width (A) according to Strange’s recommendations is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.85 m",
            "b) 2.5 m",
            "c) 3.0 m",
            "d) 4.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the height of the dam is up to 7.5 m then the top width value according to Strange’s recommendation is 1.85 and if the height is in between 7.5 to 15 m, then the recommended value is 2.5. If the height is in between 15 to 22.5 m then the top width is 3.0 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "When the height of the dam is in between 7.5 to 15, the Strange’s recommended value for maximum freeboard of low earth dams is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 to 1.5",
            "b) 1.5 to 1.8",
            "c) 1.85",
            "d) 2.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the height of the dam up to 4.5 m, the maximum freeboard is 1.2 to 1.5 m and for the height range 4.5 to 7.5 m, the maximum freeboard is 1.5 to 1.8 m. If the height of the dam is in between 7.5 to 15 m, the maximum value is 1.85 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Calculate the top width (A) of the earth dam of height 50 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.0 m",
            "b) 4.75 m",
            "c) 6.10 m",
            "d) 3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For dams higher than 30 m, the top width (A) is given by the following formula-\nA = 1.65 (H + 1.5)1/3 where H is the height of the dam.\nA = 1.65 (50 + 1.5)1/3 = 6.13 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "A phreatic line in seepage analysis is defined as the line on which pressure is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal to the atmosphere",
            "b) greater than atmosphere",
            "c) lower than atmosphere",
            "d) varying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The line which joins the points in a dam section at which pressure is equal to the atmospheric pressure is called phreatic line. It is also called as line of seepage or saturation line. There is capillary fringe i.e zone of capillary which has negative hydrostatic pressure above this line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Provision of horizontal berms at suitable vertical intervals may be provided in the downstream face of an earthen dam in order to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) allow the movement of cattle",
            "b) allow the inspection of vehicles to move",
            "c) reduce the erosion caused by the flowing rainwater",
            "d) increase the erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The provision of berms serves the following purposes –\n\nIt behaves like a good lining for reducing losses and leakage.\nThey provide protection against erosion and breaches due to wave action.\nThey help the channel to attain regime conditions as they help in providing a wider waterway.\nIt can be used as borrow pits for excavating soil to be used for filling.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "During seepage through an earthen mass, the direction of seepage is ________________ to the equipotential lines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) perpendicular",
            "b) parallel",
            "c) not defined",
            "d) diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The seepage through a pervious soil material for 2-D flow is given by Laplacian equation and the graphical solution suggests that the flow through the soil can be represented by flow-net. It consists of 2 sets of curves equipotential line and streamlines which is mutually perpendicular to each other.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "The upstream face of the earth dam is considered as _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equipotential line",
            "b) streamline",
            "c) streak line",
            "d) path line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equipotential lines are the lines of equal energy. Every point on the upstream face of an earth dam will be under equal total energy, this line acts as an equipotential line. Similarly, the upstream floor of a weir acts as an equipotential line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Which of the following line acts as a dividing line between dry (or moist) and submerged line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equipotential line",
            "b) Path line",
            "c) Seepage line",
            "d) Streak line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When there is appreciable flow through the dam body below the phreatic line, it reduces the effective weight of the soil and also the shear strength of the soil due to pore pressure. The capillary tension in water leads to increased intergranular pressure as the insignificant flow through the fringe leads to greater shear strength. Hence, the effects are neglected.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Stone pitching or riprap is generally provided to avoid _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) over-topping",
            "b) erosion of U/s and d/s face",
            "c) cracking due to frost action",
            "d) gully formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The waves developed near the top surface due to the winds notch out the soil from the U/s face and the D/s toe of the dam may get eroded due to the cross currents and due to tailwater. Stone pitching or riprap should be provided to avoid such failures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Which of the following is/are correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) i and v",
            "b) ii and iii",
            "c) iv and v",
            "d) i and iv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Over-topping of the dam generally occurs due to insufficient free-board, inadequate spillway capacity, and clogging of the spillway, etc. Frost causes heaving and cracking of the soil with seepage and consequent failure, an additional freeboard allowance of about 1.5 m should be provided as an additional safety measure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "The collection and removal of water before it acquires high downward velocities is ensured by provision of ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) berms",
            "b) freeboard",
            "c) burrow pits",
            "d) spoil banks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rainwater that acquires high downward velocities causes consequent erosion which can be reduced by the provision of berms.\nThe provision of berms serves the following purposes –\n• It behaves like a good lining for reducing losses and leakage\n• They provide protection against erosion and breaches due to wave action\n• They help the channel to attain regime conditions as they help in providing a wider waterway\n• It can be used as borrow pits for excavating soil to be used for filling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "In order to prevent the possibility of the cross-flow towards the earthen embankments, it is necessary to provide _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) counter berms",
            "b) sides walls of sufficient height and length",
            "c) spoil banks",
            "d) sufficient freeboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cross-currents that may come from the spillway buckets is one of the reasons for the d/s toe erosion. To prevent the possibility of cross-flow towards the earthen embankment, sidewalls of the spillway also called diaphragm walls of sufficient height and length is provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Sloughing is the process of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) progressive erosion",
            "b) subsequent removal of soil grains from within the dam",
            "c) uncontrolled seepage through the dam body",
            "d) progressive removal of soil from the D/s face"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The progressive erosion and the subsequent removal of soil grains from within the dam or from the foundation is piping. The progressive removal of soil from the d/s face is sloughing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "In foundation slide failure___________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) top of embankment gets cracked and lower slope moves outward forming large mud waves near the heel",
            "b) top of embankment gets cracked and lower slope moves inward forming large mud waves near the heel",
            "c) bottom of embankment gets cracked and lower slope moves outward forming large mud waves near the heel",
            "d) bottom of embankment gets cracked and lower slope moves inward forming large mud waves near the heel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The entire dam may slide or just one face slides over the foundation when the foundation of earth dams is made of soft soils. Then the foundation bulges out on the side of the movement. The top of the embankment gets cracked and lower slope moves outward forming large mud waves near the heel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "What is the most critical condition of slide of the U/s slope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sudden drawdown of the reservoir",
            "b) Reservoir full condition",
            "c) Steady seepage condition",
            "d) Sudden drawdown and reservoir full condition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the upstream slope is steep and when the soil used in the construction of the dam is poor and compaction is not adequate, the sudden drawdown of water causes sliding of the upstream face. This failure seldom leads to catastrophic failures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "When the reservoir is full, the slope which is most likely to slide is _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the upstream slope",
            "b) the downstream slope",
            "c) both upstream and downstream slope",
            "d) no effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The D/s slope is most likely to slide when the reservoir is full. For downstream face also, when the slope is steep and soil used is poor with inadequate compaction, saturation and softening of soil due to rainfall and seepage causes sliding of the downstream face.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "In order to keep the saturation line in a canal embankment well within the toe, it is necessary to provide _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) spoil bank",
            "b) counter berm",
            "c) freeboard",
            "d) berm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The saturation gradient line may cut the downstream end of the bank even after providing sufficient section for bank embankment. By the provision of counter-berms, the saturation line can be kept covered at least by 0.5 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Which of the following failures generally occur due to the development of unaccounted pore pressures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic failures",
            "b) Piping through the dam body",
            "c) Sliding in embankments",
            "d) Sloughing of the d/s toe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excessive pore pressure developed due to consideration of clay embedded between sands or silts may reduce the shear strength of the soil. It becomes incapable of resisting the induced shear stresses leading to the failure of dam foundation without warning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is also called as the Slices method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fellenius method",
            "b) Swedish slip circle method",
            "c) Bishop’s simplified method",
            "d) Spencer’s method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Swedish circle method is also called as the method of slices and Fellenius method is a modified version of it. Swedish circle method assumes the condition of plain strain with failure along a cylindrical arc. The location of the center of possible failure arc is assumed and the earth mass is divided into slices.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "In Fellenius method for small values of angle of internal friction of soil, the critical arc passes ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) through the toe of the slope",
            "b) above the toe of the slope",
            "c) below the toe of the slope",
            "d) anywhere near the toe of the slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The critical arc passes below the toe of the slope for small values of angle of internal friction of the soil (0° to 15°) if the angle of inclination is less than 53°. For large values of internal friction angle, the critical arc passes through the slope.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression of equivalent liquid unit weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ϒeq.tan2 [45 – Φ/2] ",
            "b) ϒeq.tan2 [45 + Φ/2] ",
            "c) ϒeq.tan [45 – Φ/2] ",
            "d) ϒeq.tan [45 + Φ/2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This term is used in the analysis of the stability of the foundation against shear. It is based on the assumption that soil has an equivalent liquid unit weight which would produce the same shear stress as the soil itself.\nϒeq.tan2 [45 – Φ/2] \nwhere ϒeq = the equivalent unit weight of dry soil in foundation and dam and Φ = the equivalent angle of internal friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Calculate the maximum shear-stress induced if the horizontal average shear stress induced in u/s portion of the dam at the base is 36.45 kN/m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43.74 kN/m2",
            "b) 47.38 kN/m2",
            "c) 51.03 kN/m2",
            "d) 54.67 kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By Photoelastic studies, the maximum intensity of shear stress is equal to 1.4 times the average shear intensity at a distance 0.6 B from the heel.\nꞆmax = 1.4 Ꞇavg = 1.4 x 36.45 = 51.03 kN/m2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Calculate the factor of safety at the point of maximum shear if unit shearing resistance is 97.9 kN/m2 and the maximum shear-stress induced is 55.72 kN/m2. Check whether the dam is safe or unsafe.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F.O.S = 1.93 and safe",
            "b) F.O.S = 1.75 and unsafe",
            "c) F.O.S = 0.569 and safe",
            "d) F.O.S = 1.75 and safe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: F.O.S will be the ratio of the unit shearing resistance to the maximum shear stress developed.\nF.O.S = 97.9 / 55.72 = 1.75\nthis value should be more than unity, hence safe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "A rock toe and a horizontal filter is provided on the downstream base of an earthen dam in order to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) prevent piping action in the dam body",
            "b) prevent piping action in the dam foundation",
            "c) reduce the seepage quantity by blocking its flow",
            "d) collect and drain out the seepage flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Such provision reduces the pore pressure in the downstream portion of the dam and thus increases the stability of the dam permitting steep slopes. The seepage is collected through these drains and moved to a point where it can be safely discharged.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "What is provided in the form of a transition zone between the homogenous embankments-fill and rock toe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toe filter",
            "b) Horizontal blanket",
            "c) Chimney drain",
            "d) Trenches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The toe filter consists of three layers of fine sand, coarse sand, and gravel with the stone size or rock chips varying from 15 to 20 mm. It acts as a transition zone and prevents choking of the toe and height of the rock toe is kept between 1/3 to 1/4 of the dam height to achieve good results.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "The length of horizontal blanket should be equal to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 times the height of the dam",
            "b) 4 times the height of the dam",
            "c) 5 times the height of the dam",
            "d) 6 times the height of the dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blanket is a layer of impervious material laid at a natural ground level extending from the d/s end of the toe. A sufficient length equal to 3 times the height of the dam is provided as per the filter criteria to reduce the seepage pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "____________________ is provided when large scale stratification occurs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chimney drain",
            "b) Cut-off",
            "c) Relief wells",
            "d) Trenches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A vertical filter (or inclined u/s or d/s) is placed along with the horizontal as to intercept the seeping water effectively in case of large stratification. This arrangement is called a chimney drain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "The only provision among the following which can help control the seepage through the body of an earthen dam and thus to keep the phreatic line well within the dam width is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) upstream impervious cut-off",
            "b) drain trench along the downstream toe",
            "c) relief wells",
            "d) chimney drain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of large scale stratification a vertical filter is also provided along with the horizontal filter so as to effectively intercept the seeping water. This arrangement is nothing but is termed as chimney drain. It helps in keeping the phreatic line well within the dam body and also helps in rapid consolidation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "During the maintenance of an earthen dam, the apparent seepage through the foundation of the dam is best taken care of by providing ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chimney drain",
            "b) rock toe",
            "c) drain trench along the downstream toe",
            "d) upstream impervious cut-off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cut-off can be provided only during construction. If seepage appears afterward, a drain with an inverted filter along the toe line is provided to collect soil-free water to check piping action.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "The base width of a rock-fill dam in comparison to that of an earthen dam is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) much larger",
            "b) much smaller",
            "c) sometimes large sometimes smaller",
            "d) almost equal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rock-fill dams are less flexible than earthen dams, their foundation requirements are more rigid than those of earthen dams which can be constructed on any type of foundation. Since the steeper slopes are used in rock-fill dams and the base width is quite less.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "On moderate foundations and particularly in seismic areas, the type of dam which can preferably be considered for construction is ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) masonry gravity dam",
            "b) earthen dam",
            "c) rock-fill dam",
            "d) arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rock-fill dams provide high resistance to seismic forces due to their flexible character. They are liable to large settlements which may lead to cracking of concrete membrane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "According to Terzaghi, the ratio of D15 of filter to D15 of base material should be _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) > 5",
            "b) < 4",
            "c) 4 to 5",
            "d) < 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Terzaghi provided a rational approach to the design of filters. The following filter criteria should be satisfied-\nD15 of filter / D85 of base materials < 4 to 5 < D15 of filter/ D15 of base materials\nThe filters should be such that neither the embankment nor the foundation material can penetrate and clog the filters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not provided in order to control the possibility of sand boiling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relief wells",
            "b) Drain trenches",
            "c) Vertical cut-offs",
            "d) Berms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is a possibility that the water may boil up near the toe of the dam when large scale seepage takes place through the pervious foundation overlain by a thin less pervious layer. Relief wells or drain trenches and d/s berms beyond the toe of the dam are all provided to control sand boiling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "The seepage forces within the filter are controlled up to permissible small magnitudes when the ratio of D15 of filter to D15 of base material is ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) between 5 to 40",
            "b) less than 5",
            "c) between 5 to 20",
            "d) less than 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the ratio does not exceed 4 to 5, the base material is prevented from passing through the pores of the filter. When this ratio is more than 5 and less than 40, the seepage forces within the filter are controlled up to permissible small magnitudes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "The safety valve of a dam is its __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) drainage gallery",
            "b) inspection gallery",
            "c) spillway",
            "d) outlet sluices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A spillway is essentially a safety valve for the dam and must be properly designed. It should have adequate capacity to dispose off the entire surplus water from upstream to downstream at the time of the arrival of the worst design flood.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "An ungated spillway starts functioning as soon as the water level in the reservoir crosses the __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum reservoir level",
            "b) minimum reservoir level",
            "c) maximum conservation level",
            "d) full Supply level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maximum conservation level is nothing but normal pool level which is the maximum elevation to which the reservoir water surface will rise during normal operating conditions. This is equivalent to the elevation of the spillway crest or the top of the spillway gates, such uncontrolled spillways are only guided by the available water head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simplest type of spillway and may be constructed on small bunds or thin arch dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight drop spillway",
            "b) Ogee spillway",
            "c) Shaft spillway",
            "d) Siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Straight drop weir or Overfall spillway is a low weir and simple vertical fall type structure. It is the simplest type of spillway and can be constructed on small bunds, thin arches, etc. The downstream face of the spillway may be kept vertical or slightly inclined.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "The spillway can be best built independently of the dam when there is _________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) deep narrow gorge with steep slopes",
            "b) deep narrow gorge with gradual slopes",
            "c) wide gorge with a gradual slope",
            "d) wide valley with moderate slopes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spillway can be best built independently of the dam where there is a deep narrow gorge with steep banks separated from a flank by a hillock with its level above the top of the dam. A concrete or an earthen dam can be constructed across the main valley and a spillway can be constructed independently into the saddle under such circumstances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a secondary safety arrangement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Safety valves",
            "b) Spillway gates",
            "c) Subsidiary spillway",
            "d) Energy dissipaters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If at the worst condition the water rises above the maximum reservoir level it will overtop such an embankment. A secondary safety arrangement known as subsidiary dam or emergency spillway or breaching section is generally provided on large dams for the disposal of excess water, especially on earthen and rock-fill dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Which of the following spillway is least suitable to earthen dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ogee spillway",
            "b) Chute spillway",
            "c) Side-channel spillways",
            "d) Shaft spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is an improvement over the free over-fall spillway. It is mostly suitable for concrete gravity dams especially when the spillway is located within the body of the dam in the same valley.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "If the operating head on an ogee spillway is more than the design head then ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the pressure on the crest will be zero",
            "b) the pressure on the crest will be negative causing cavitation",
            "c) the pressure on the crest will be positive",
            "d) the discharge coefficient of the spillway will be reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lower nappe of the falling jet may leave the ogee profile when the operating head of the spillway is more than the design head. This generates negative pressure at the point of separation which leads to the formation of cavities in the water resulting in cavitation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "In the functioning of an ogee spillway, the operating head ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) frequently exceeds the design head",
            "b) rarely exceeds the design head",
            "c) never exceeds the design head",
            "d) has no connection with the design head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An ogee spillway is designed for maximum head up to RL of maximum reservoir level; there are almost no chances of operating head exceeding the design head. Under rare emergency as in excessive floods, it may become necessary to allow the reservoir level to go even above the MRL in such case the operating head may exceed the design head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Which of the following spillway is an improvement over free overflow spillway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight drop spillway",
            "b) Open channel spillway",
            "c) Overflow spillway",
            "d) Siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ogee spillway is an improvement over free overflow spillway and is widely used with concrete, arch and buttress dam. The profile is made such that the shape of the lower nappe of a freely falling jet over a duly ventilated sharp-crested weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "If the head of the water over the spillway is less than the design head, then ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the pressure on the crest will be zero",
            "b) the pressure on the crest will be negative causing cavitation",
            "c) the discharge coefficient of the spillway is increased",
            "d) the discharge coefficient of the spillway will be reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the head of water over the spillway is less than the design head, the falling jet would adhere to the crest of the ogee spillway. This causes positive hydrostatic pressure and thereby reduces the discharge coefficient of the weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "The spillway which can be called as an overflow spillway is essentially ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) an ogee spillway",
            "b) a shaft spillway",
            "c) a chute spillway",
            "d) a syphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ogee spillway is also called as overflow spillway and is an improvement over straight drop spillway. In this spillway, the water jet falls clearly away from the face of the spillway and the gap between the jet and the face is kept ventilated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "According to US Army Corps, the u/s profile of ogee spillway extends up to _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) x = 1.27 Hd",
            "b) x = -1.27 Hd",
            "c) x = 0.431 Hd",
            "d) x = -0.431 Hd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of K and n depends on the upstream slope. For vertical u/s face of the spillway, K is 2.0 and n is 1.85 and for slope 1H : 3V, K = 1.936 and n = 1.836. For slope 1H : 1 1/2V, K = 1.939 and n = 1.810.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Which of the following plot is useful in determining the clearance for the spillway deck bridge and the top levels of walls on the side of the spillway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The coordinates of the lower nappe",
            "b) The coordinates of the upper nappe",
            "c) Both the coordinates of upper and lower nappe",
            "d) The origin or apex of crest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The profile for an Ogee spillway having a vertical upstream face can be determined on the basis of its WES profile. The upstream profile extends up to x = -1.27 Hd Where Hd is the design head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "What is the satisfactory radius for the reverse bottom curve which is provided at the downstream end of the spillway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One-fourth of the spillway height",
            "b) Equal to the spillway height",
            "c) Half the value of the spillway height",
            "d) One-third of the spillway height"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The crest profile is determined by the coordinates of the lower nappe. The plotting of the upper nappe is useful in determining the clearance for the spillway deck bridge and the top levels of the training walls on the side of the spillway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "What is Bazin’s profile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Profile for the lower nappe of a free-falling jet",
            "b) The profile obtained for the upper nappe of a free-falling jet",
            "c) Crest profile",
            "d) Profile of both upper and lower nappe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A smooth gradual reverse curvature is provided at the bottom of the downstream face after the plotting of the profile of the spillway. The curve turns the flow into the discharge channel. The satisfactory radius of the curve is taken as one-fourth of the spillway height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "The discharge passing over an ogee spillway per unit length of its apex line is proportional ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H",
            "b) H2",
            "c) H1/2",
            "d) H3/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The discharge passing over the ogee spillway is given by the formula –\nQ = C. Le. H3/2 where Le is the effective length of the spillway crest, C is the coefficient of discharge and H is the total head over the crest including the velocity head.\nIt is clear from the discharge equation that the discharge is proportional to H3/2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "When the crest of an ogee spillway is designed to be in accordance with the lower nappe of a free-falling water jet over a duly ventilated sharp-crested weir then theoretically",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pressure on the spillway crest will be zero at design head only",
            "b) The pressure on the spillway crest will always be zero",
            "c) The pressure on the spillway crest will always be negative",
            "d) The pressure on the spillway crest will be always positive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In actual practice development of negative pressure takes place beneath the nappe due to the removal of air by the falling jet. This causes the danger of cavitation and induces fluctuation and pulsation effects. To control this aeration pipes may be provided along spillway face.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "The velocity of approach has found to be negligible effect upon discharge if ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the ratio H/Hd is more than 1.33",
            "b) the ratio H/Hd is less than 1.33",
            "c) the ratio H/Hd is equal to zero",
            "d) the ratio H/Hd is more than 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The extra concrete is required for thickening of the section at the d/s end which can be saved by shifting the curve of the nappe in a backward direction until it becomes tangential to the d/s face. It can be affected by providing a corbel on u/s face.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "If a flood enters a dam reservoir at F.R.L, the efficiency of its ogee spillway will ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase with the increasing head",
            "b) reduce with the increasing head",
            "c) remain constant with the increasing head",
            "d) vary with the increasing head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The velocity of approach has been found to have a negligible effect upon discharge when the height of the weir is more than 1.33 times the design head. When this ratio is less than 1.33 as in low spillways, the velocity is having an appreciable effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "The downstream apron of the ogee spillway is found to have a negligible effect on the coefficient of discharge when the value of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Hd + d) / He is less than 1.7",
            "b) (Hd + d) / He exceeds 1.7",
            "c) (Hd + d) / He is equal to 1",
            "d) (Hd + d) / He is less than 1.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of discharge increases with the increasing head above the full reservoir level till it becomes about 2.2 at full design head i.e. MRL. Since the spillway starts working when the water level just crosses FRL, the coefficient of discharge is about 77% at full design head. As the water level increases from F.R.L to M.R.L, the efficiency increases from 77% to 100%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "What is the value of the pier abutment coefficient for pointed nose piers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.02",
            "c) 0.01",
            "d) 0.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The d/s apron is found to have a negligible effect on the coefficient of discharge when the value of (Hd + d) / He exceeds 1.7. where d is the tailwater depth, Hd is the design head and He is the Design head including the velocity head. There can be a decrease in the coefficient due to tailwater submergence.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "What is the value of abutment contraction coefficient for square abutment with headwall perpendicular to the direction of flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2",
            "b) 0.1",
            "c) 0.02",
            "d) 0.01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of pier contraction coefficient depends upon the shape of the piers.\n\n\nS.NO.\nPier Shape\nContraction Coefficient\n\n\n1\nSquare nosed piers without any rounding\n0.1\n\n\n2\nRounded nose piers and 900 cut water nosed piers\n0.01\n\n\n3\nPointed nose piers\n0.0\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "What is the assumption that is taken during the entire design of an overflow spillway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The upper and lower nappe is subjected to negative pressures",
            "b) The upper and lower nappe is subjected to full atmospheric pressure",
            "c) The upper and lower nappe is subjected to zero atmospheric pressure",
            "d) The upper and lower nappe is subjected to both positive and negative pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For square abutment with headwall at 90° to the direction of the flow, the abutment contraction coefficient is 0.2. For rounded abutment with headwall at 90° to the direction of flow, the value is taken as 0.1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Calculate the effective length of the spillway which consists of 6 spans having a clear width of 10 m each. The thickness of each pier may be taken as 2.5 m and the total design head on the crest including velocity head is 16.3 m. Assuming 90° cut water nose piers and rounded abutments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 55 m",
            "b) 60 m",
            "c) 65 m",
            "d) 75 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In actual practice, the development of negative pressure due to insufficient aeration takes place beneath the nappe due to the removal of air by the falling jet. But the entire design has been done with the assumption that the upper and lower nappe is subjected to full atmospheric pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simplest type of spillway which can be provided independently and at low costs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ogee spillway",
            "b) Trough spillway",
            "c) Siphon spillway",
            "d) Saddle spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trough or chute spillway is adaptable to any type of foundations and is the simplest type of spillway. It can be easily provided independently at low costs but it requires ample room adjacent to the dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "If the spillway is constructed in continuation to the dam at one end, it may be called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) saddle weir",
            "b) flank weir",
            "c) waste weir",
            "d) temporary weir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Saddle weir is the one when the spillway is constructed in a natural saddle in a bank of the river separated from the main dam by a high ridge. Flank weir is the one when the spillway is constructed in continuation to the dam at one end.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "The spillway which can be adopted with ease on gravity as well as earthen dams is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ogee spillway",
            "b) chute spillway",
            "c) both ogee and chute spillway",
            "d) straight drop spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Straight drop spillway is a low weir and simple vertical fall type structure which may be constructed on thin arch dams or small bunds etc. An ogee spillway is most suitable for concrete gravity dams. Chute spillway can be provided easily on earth and rock-fill dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "The famous Bhakra dam of India is provided with ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) trough spillway",
            "b) ogee spillway",
            "c) shaft spillway",
            "d) siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bhakra Dam is a concrete gravity dam on the Sutlej River in Himachal Pradesh of the total height of 226 m approximately. It forms the Gobindsagar Reservoir with controlled overflow chute or trough spillway and four spillway gates for an emergency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "The surplus reservoir water after spilling over the crest of the spillway flows on the chute is __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel to the crest in a trough spillway",
            "b) parallel to the crest in a side-channel spillway",
            "c) perpendicular to the crest in a side-channel spillway",
            "d) obliquely to the crest in a chute spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In chute spillway, after crossing over the crest of the spillway water flows at right angle shoots down a channel or a trough to meet the river channel downstream of the dam. The water after spilling over the crest flows parallel to the crest in a side-channel spillway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "Whenever the slope of chute changes from steeper to milder ____________________ curve shall be provided.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a concave vertical curve",
            "b) a convex vertical curve",
            "c) a hyperbolic curve",
            "d) a parabolic curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A concave vertical curve is provided whenever the slope changes from steeper to milder. The radius of this curve should be less than 10 times the depth of water (in meters).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "The side slope of approach channel of chute spillway is ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:1",
            "b) 1:1 \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) ",
            "c) 1:3",
            "d) 1:2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An entrance channel also called as an approach channel is trapezoidal in shape with side slopes 1:1. It is constructed so as to lead the reservoir water up to the control structure or low ogee weir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "The spillway which may sometimes be called as a waste weir is ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) an ogee spillway",
            "b) a trough spillway",
            "c) a shaft spillway",
            "d) a siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A chute or trough spillway is sometimes called as a waste weir. It is called as chute spillway because after crossing over the crest of the spillway water flow shoots down a channel or trough to meet the river channel downstream of the dam. The trough is taken straight from the crest to the river.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "The portion of a chute spillway which is known as its control structure is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) low ogee weir",
            "b) chute channel",
            "c) approach channel leading the water from the reservoir to the ogee weir",
            "d) silting basin at its bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Low ogee weir is required as a control structure in the chute spillway. The entire chute spillway is divided into the entrance channel, control structure, Chute channel or discharge channel, and energy dissipation arrangements in the form of silting basin at the bottom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "The type of spillway which is provided on narrow valleys where no side flanks are available is ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ogee spillway",
            "b) chute spillway",
            "c) side-channel spillway",
            "d) straight drop spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The side channel spillway is suitable when the valley is too narrow. When there is no room for provision of chute spillway (as side flanks of sufficient width are required), this type is adopted as it requires limited space. The situation required for the chute spillway and side-channel spillway is mostly the same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "Which of the following curve is provided when the slope of the chute changes from milder to steeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concave vertical curve",
            "b) Hyperbolic curve",
            "c) Convex vertical curve",
            "d) Straight plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A convex vertical curve shall have to be provided when the slope of the chute changes from milder to steeper. The curvature should approximate to a parabolic shape. A concave vertical curve is provided whenever the slope changes from steeper to milder.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "Calculate the freeboard for the top levels of the side walls if the mean velocity of water in the chute reach is 3.5 m/s and the mean depth of water in the chute reach under consideration is 4.7 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.60 m",
            "b) 1 m",
            "c) 0.85 m",
            "d) 0.55 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The freeboard to be provided above the top nappe of side walls is generally given by the equation:\nF.B = 0.61 + 0.04 Vm. dm1/3 where ‘Vm‘ is the mean velocity of water in the chute reach and ‘dm’ is the mean depth of water in the chute reach under consideration.\nF.B = 0.61 + 0.04 x 3.5 x 4.71/3 = 0.84 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "The minimum slope of the chute is governed by the condition that _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the subcritical flow must be maintained",
            "b) the supercritical flow must be maintained",
            "c) a critical flow must be maintained",
            "d) maybe supercritical or subcritical flow is possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water flows through the chute channel after spilling over the control structure and the minimum slope is governed by the condition that the supercritical flow must be maintained. The slope should be sufficient to meet the flow requirement from the crest without endangering the stability or heavy excavations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "What is the approximate percentage of light reinforcement that is provided in the top of the reinforced concrete slabs at the base?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.50% of the concrete area",
            "b) 0.45% of the concrete area",
            "c) 0.30% of the concrete area",
            "d) 0.25% of the concrete area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The base of the channel is usually made of reinforced concrete slabs 25 to 50 cm thick and light reinforcement of about 0.25% of the concrete area is also provided in both the directions. The chute is sometimes narrowed for the economy and then widened near the end to reduce the discharging velocity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "A shaft spillway is located _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) inside the body of a gravity dam",
            "b) inside the upstream reservoir",
            "c) inside the downstream reservoir",
            "d) on the side flanks of the main dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape of the shaft spillway is just like a funnel. The lower end of the funnel is turned at right angles and then taken out below the dam horizontally. Water spills over the circular crest and then enters the vertical shaft and comes out of the dam through the horizontal tunnel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "The siphons installed within a gravity dam to spill the surplus reservoir water are known as ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hooded type siphon spillway",
            "b) tilted outlet type siphon spillway",
            "c) both hooded and titled type siphon spillway",
            "d) shaft spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The siphon pipe is installed within the body of the dam and an air vent may be connected with it. The outlet is submerged to avoid the entry of the air in the siphon from the d/s end. When the air enters the siphon through the vent, siphoning action cannot take place and the flow will stop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "The siphons installed over overflow dams constitute what are known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hooded type siphon spillway",
            "b) tilted outlet type siphon spillway",
            "c) discharge carriers",
            "d) baby siphons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In hooded type spillway, a reinforced concrete hood is constructed over an ordinary overflow section of a gravity dam. The inlet is kept submerged to prevent the entry of debris, ice, etc. A small de-priming hood is kept above the main hood and they are connected by an air vent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "The only spillway among the following through which the discharge does not increase as fast as it increases in all others is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chute spillway",
            "b) side-channel spillway",
            "c) ogee spillway",
            "d) shaft spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A shaft spillway is generally adopted when the possibility of an overflow spillway and a trough spillway has been ruled out. The discharge does not increase at such a high rate as in weir type spills. Hence, it may not prove as useful as a weir type spills if unestimated high floods occur.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "The only spillway among the following through which the discharge is almost at its capacity rate even from the start of its functioning is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chute spillway",
            "b) side-channel spillway",
            "c) ogee spillway",
            "d) siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the change in the effective head is small as compared to the corresponding change in head over an ogee spillway. When once the water level has risen above the normal pool level, the discharge through the siphon is always at its capacity. This makes it advantageous in disposing of sudden surges of water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "An air vent is provided at FRL to break the siphoning action at that level in a ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hooded type of siphon spillway",
            "b) tilted outlet type of siphon spillway",
            "c) saddle siphon spillway",
            "d) volute siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the water level falls to FRL an air vent is provided on the crown to break the siphoning action. Air enters the lower limb through the air vent and siphonic action is stopped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Which of the following spillway is designed in India by Ganesh Iyer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saddle siphon spillway",
            "b) Saddle spillway",
            "c) Glory hole spillway",
            "d) Volute Siphon spillway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Volute siphon spillway consists of a vertical shaft circular in the section provided with a cap covering. It has low priming depth and higher discharge efficiency. It can be provided with an earth dam also.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "The crest of a siphon spillway is fixed at ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) full reservoir level",
            "b) dead storage level",
            "c) maximum water level",
            "d) top of the dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The crest of a siphon spillway is fixed at FRL. When the water level in the reservoir rises above FRL the sheet of water starts spilling over the crest. When the waterfalls to FRL, air enters the vent and siphonic action is stopped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "The allowable maximum negative head on an average is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 m or so",
            "b) 5 m or so",
            "c) 7.5 m or so",
            "d) 10 m or so"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The discharge through the siphon is given by the equation-\nQ = Cd. A. (2gH)1/2 where Cd is the coefficient of discharge, A is the area of the cross-section and H is the effective head i.e. the difference of the water level in the reservoir and the tailwater level for a submerged outlet. The discharge through the spillway is affected to a very less extent is the water surface in the reservoir rises.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "The structure which is not used in a shaft spillway is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tunnel",
            "b) bridge",
            "c) radial gates",
            "d) radial piers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vertical distance from the crown of the siphon down to the discharging point or HGL should not exceed a value of 7.5 m under average conditions. This is necessary to avoid cavitation.\nLimiting vaccum pressure = Atmospheric pressure – Vapour pressure = 10 – 2.5 = 7.5 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "Morning glory is the _____________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) special flared inlet of the shaft spillway of a dam of very small height",
            "b) special flared inlet of the shaft spillway of a large dam project",
            "c) a horizontal tunnel constructed in a shaft spillway across the body of a gravity dam to carry surplus reservoir water to the d/s river",
            "d) a horizontal tunnel constructed in a shaft spillway of an earthen dam through its foundation to carry surplus reservoir water to the d/s river"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The radial gates consists of steel plates with struts which are pinned at the center of the circular plate. When the water level rises above FRL the gates are raised by hoisting arrangement to allow the flood water to discharge freely. Each gate is separately housed between two piers constructed on the crest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "For a saddle siphon, the maximum operative head is 4.53 m. The width and height of the throat of the siphon are 5 m and 2.25 m respectively. The coefficient of discharge is 0.90. How many units are required to pass a flood of 350 cumecs? (Assume g = 10 m/s2)",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In shaft spillway of large heights, RCC may be used and for smaller heights, no special inlet design is necessary. A flared inlet called morning glory is often used in large projects. The horizontal tunnel is either taken through the dam body or below the foundations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "A siphon spillway in a concrete gravity dam is in the shape of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) U-shape",
            "b) Inverted U-shape",
            "c) Horizontal bend through the abutment",
            "d) Any straight line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The discharge through the siphon is given by the equation:\nQ = Cd. A. (2gH)1/2 Where Cd = 0.9, H = 4.53 m and A = 5 x 2.25 = 11.25 m2\nQ = 0.9 x 11.25 x (2 x 9.81 x 4.53)1/2 = 95.45 m3/sec\nNo. of units of saddle siphon = 350 / 95.45 = 3.66 units. = 4 units.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "The energy dissipation at the toe of the spillway is affected basically by the use of hydraulic jump in _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) roller bucket",
            "b) a ski-jump bucket",
            "c) a sloping apron below the downstream river bed",
            "d) both roller and ski-jump bucket"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most of the kinetic energy is destroyed by creating a condition suitable for the formation of a hydraulic jump. Sometimes the depth of tail-water may be more than that necessary to create the hydraulic jump. The depth of water can be reduced to create a hydraulic jump by providing a sloping apron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "When the tail-water depths in the river downstream of a spillway are quite low such that the tail-water curve at all discharges lies below the post jump depth curve, then the energy dissipation can be affected best by ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a roller bucket",
            "b) a ski-jump bucket",
            "c) either roller or ski-jump bucket",
            "d) a sloping apron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most ideal condition for jump formation is when TWC coincides with JHC at all discharge. To ensure protection in the region of a hydraulic jump, a simple concrete apron of apron length 5 (y2 – y1) is provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "The device which does not help in energy dissipation at the bottom of a hydraulic structure over which water spills is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chute block",
            "b) dentated sill",
            "c) morning glory",
            "d) baffle piers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Energy dissipation bucket called ski-jump bucket is used when the tail-water depth is insufficient or low at all discharge. It requires sound and rocky river bed. Water may shoot up out of the bucket and fail harmlessly into the river at some distance downstream of the bucket.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "The formation of hydraulic jump at the foot of a spillway is one of the common methods of energy dissipation because ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) it destroys more than 90% of total energy by the turbulence produced in the jump",
            "b) it reduces the kinetic energy by increasing the depth of flow",
            "c) its action is not understood",
            "d) it reduces the kinetic energy by decreasing the depth of flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A flared inlet called morning glory is often used in large projects. The horizontal tunnel is either taken through the dam body or below the foundations. Chute blocks, dentated sills and baffle piers are all auxiliary devices which help in energy dissipation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "A ski-jump bucket is also known as _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) flip bucket",
            "b) solid roller bucket",
            "c) slotted roller bucket",
            "d) flexible bucket"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydraulic jump is generally accompanied by large scale turbulence dissipating most of the kinetic energy of the super-critical flow. It is the most suitable method because the energy is lost in the impact of the water against water. Most of the kinetic energy is destroyed by creating a condition suitable for the hydraulic jump.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "Which of the following stilling basin help in stabilizing the flow and improve the jump performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) dentated sills",
            "b) chute blocks",
            "c) baffle piers",
            "d) friction blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A ski-jump bucket is also called flip bucket is used for energy dissipation when tail-water depth is insufficient or low at all discharge. A part of energy dissipation takes place by impact and some of the energy is dissipated in the air by diffusion or aeration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "What is the expected solution for the case when the T.W.C is lying above the J.H.C curve at all discharges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By providing a simple concrete apron of length 5(Y1 – Y2)",
            "b) By providing a sloping apron above the river bed",
            "c) By providing a sloping apron below the river bed",
            "d) Provision of a ski-jump bucket"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy dissipation in the jump depends upon the Froude number, if this Froude number is higher, the greater energy dissipation can take place. \n\n\nS NO.\nFroude number\n% loss in energy\n\n\n1.\n2.5\n17\n\n\n2.\n4.5\n45\n\n\n3.\n9.0\n70\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "A sloping apron is provided partly above the river bed and partly below the river bed in case of ____________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) when TWC coincides with the JHC at all discharges",
            "b) when TWC lies above the JHC at all discharges",
            "c) when TWC lies below the JHC at all discharges",
            "d) when TWC lies above the JHC at low discharges and below the JHC at high discharges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chute blocks are a row of small projections like teeth of saw and are provided at the entrance of the silting basin. It produces a shorter length of jump and stabilizes the flow. Hence, they improve jump performance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "A troublesome and oscillating hydraulic jump is normally met in cases of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) weirs and barrages",
            "b) overflow spillways of dams",
            "c) weirs",
            "d) large spillways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the Froude number lies in the range of 2.5 to 4.5, the jump is troublesome and oscillating as in case of weirs and barrages. There is an oscillating jet entering the jump bottom to the surface and back again which produces a large wave of irregular period doing unlimited damage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "A very steady and stable hydraulic jump is usually formed in the flows involving the approaching Froude number in the range of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 2.5",
            "b) 2.5 to 4.5",
            "c) 4.5 to 9.0",
            "d) more than 9.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the Froude number is in the range of 4.5 to 9.0, the jump performs at its best and is called steady jump. The length of the jump is almost constant and equal to 6 y2 where y2 is the post jump depth. The dissipation of energy ranges from 45 to 70%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "Standard USBR stilling basin-II is useful for energy dissipation at the bottom of the overflow structure, if the approaching Froude number is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 4.5",
            "b) more than 4.5",
            "c) less than 2.5",
            "d) more than 2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: USBR has standardized stilling basins for different Froude numbers. USBR stilling basin- II is recommended for large structures when the Froude number is more than 4.5. The dissipation of energy will be 45 to 85%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "When the Froude number is in the range of 2.5 to 4.5, the jump is ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) weak and energy loss is low",
            "b) troublesome and oscillating",
            "c) steady jump",
            "d) strong jump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the Froude number is in the range of 2.5 to 4.5, the jump is troublesome and oscillating. This gives rise to the heavy waves on the surface and wave suppressors are needed in this range.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "Which of the following stilling basin is applicable to only rectangular cross-sections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) U.S.B.R stilling basin-II",
            "b) U.S.B.R stilling basin-IV",
            "c) U.S.B.R stilling basin-I",
            "d) U.S.B.R stilling basin-III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: USBR stilling basin-IV is used for Froude number varying between 2.5 and 4.5 which generally occurs in canal weirs, canal falls, diversion dams, etc. They are tried to be controlled by providing large chute blocks since oscillating waves are generated in this range. This is applicable only to rectangular cross-sections.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "The Froude number of a hydraulic jump is 5.5. The jump can be classified as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a weak jump",
            "b) an oscillating jump",
            "c) rough and choppy jump",
            "d) steady jump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the Froude number is in the range of 4.5 to 9.0, the jump is steady. This is generally the case of dams and spillways. The oscillating jump occurs between the range of 2.5 to 4.5 and when Froude number is less than 2.5, the jump is weak and when it is more than 9.0, the jump is rough and choppy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "Standard stilling basin is provided at the toe of a dam spillway for energy dissipation is usually provided with auxiliary devices like chute blocks and dentated sills for the basic purpose of reducing the length of the stilling basin from about ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 y2 to 4 y2",
            "b) 4 y2 to 2 y2",
            "c) 6 y2 to 2 y2",
            "d) 3 y2 to y2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of dams and spillways, the jump is steady and the length of the jump is almost constant and is equal to 6 y2 where y2 is the post jump depth. The length of the basin is related to Froude number as the economy in the length of the basin up to about 35% i.e. 4.3 y2 is thus obtained for auxiliary devices.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "In the case of dam spillways, the approaching Froude number usually lies in the range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 2.5 m",
            "b) 2.5 – 4.5",
            "c) 4.5 – 9.0",
            "d) more than 9.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Froude number varying between 2.5 and 4.5 generally occurs in canal weirs, canal falls, diversion dams, etc. For dams and spillways, the Froude number is in between 4.5 and 9.0 i.e. steady jump and the jump is well balanced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "_____________________ are suitable only for low spillways or weirs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chute blocks",
            "b) Sloping aprons",
            "c) Baffle wall or friction blocks",
            "d) Roller buckets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Baffle piers or walls are blocks placed within the basin across the basin floor and they help in breaking the flow and dissipate the energy mostly by the impact. They generally give away under high-velocity jets due to their cavitation effects. It is unsuitable for large works.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "Which of the following helps in dissipating the residual energy and to reduce the length of the jump or the basin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dentated sills",
            "b) Chute blocks",
            "c) Roller bucket",
            "d) Baffle piers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chute blocks help in stabilizing the flow and thus improve the jump performance. Baffle piers help in breaking the flow and dissipate energy mostly by the impact. Dentated sills are generally provided at the end of the stilling basin and diffuse the residual portion of high-velocity jet reaching the end of the basin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "In a fixed roller of a spillway gate, the rollers are attached to the __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gate",
            "b) groove gate",
            "c) either gate or groove gate",
            "d) guide grooves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rollers are generally attached to the gate and ride in tracks on the downstream side of the groove guide. The openings between the upstream leaf plate and the sides of the pier grooves are sealed using rubber seals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "In the vertical Stoney spillway gate, the rollers are placed between the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gate and u/s groove guide",
            "b) gate and the d/s groove guide",
            "c) u/s and d/s groove guide",
            "d) attached to the gate and groove guides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A train of the roller is generally placed in between the gate and the d/s guide. These rollers may be placed independent of the gate and the guide thus eliminating the axle friction but rolls vertically between the two when the gate is moved.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "The spillway gate which when lowered cannot be seen from a distance is of the type ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sliding gate",
            "b) Roller gate",
            "c) Tainter gate",
            "d) USBR drum gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The system of drum gates consists of a segment of a cylinder which may be raised or lowered into the recess made into the top of the spillway. Whenever the drum is lowered, the surface becomes coincident with the designed ogee shape of the crest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "An ogee spillway of a concrete gravity dam having FRL of 328 m and MWL of 340 m is provided with vertical gates between piers erected on the spillway. The effective length of the spillway is 60 m. The discharge through the spillway when gates are opened up to the actual reservoir level of 331.0 m will be_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 850 cumecs",
            "b) 1700 cumecs",
            "c) 2800 cumecs",
            "d) 1000 cumecs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The discharge is given by the equation –\nQ = Cd. A. (2gH)1/2\nWhere Cd is the coefficient of discharge through the orifice\nA is the area of the opening = 60 x 6 =360 m2\nH is the water head over the centre line of the opening = RL (331 – 328) = 3m\nQ = 0.62 x 360 x (2 x 9.81 x 3)1/2 = 1700 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "The most common vertical lift gates in modern days is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sliding gates",
            "b) free-roller gates",
            "c) stoney gates",
            "d) fixed wheel gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design and construction of free-roller gate are difficult as the rollers are not attached to the gate and the guide. Therefore, the rollers are attached to the gate. Large vertical lift gates are broken into two horizontal sections to reduce the load on the hoisting mechanism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "Which of the following gate is also called flush boards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dropping shutters",
            "b) Tainter gates",
            "c) Drum gates",
            "d) Vertical lift gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a rectangular gate fixed with rollers and it moves up and down along the upstream vertical face of the spillway. The gate is suspended by means of chains which pass over the pulleys and to the other end of the chains a counterweight is attached.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "Which one of the following gate is not suitable for curved crests?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flush boards",
            "b) Tainter gates",
            "c) Drum gates",
            "d) Vertical lift gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dropping shutters are also called permanent flush boards. They are generally used to raise the water level by 1 to 1.25 m. This type consists of shutters or plates made of steel which are hinged at the bottom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "Which of the following gate works on the principle of counterweights against the water pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dropping shutters",
            "b) Stop logs and needles",
            "c) Stoney roller gate",
            "d) Drum gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In flush boards, the shutters are hinged at the bottom and are supported by struts. Whenever the water level rises above the top of the shutters they dropdown. Hence they are not suitable for curved crests.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "________________ are used only for very minor works.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dropping gates",
            "b) Stop logs and needles",
            "c) Rectangular gates",
            "d) Drum gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In dropping shutters, the shutters are hinged at the bottom and are supported by struts and these shutters can be raised or lowered from an overhead cableway or a bridge. They work on the principle of counterweights against the water pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "Which of the following gate is not suitable for smaller spillways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drum gates",
            "b) Radial gates",
            "c) Needles and stop logs",
            "d) Fixed roller gates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A Stop log consists of wooden beams and planks placed on to one another and leakage between them is a big problem. Needles are wooden logs kept side by side and it is very difficult to handle these logs at the time of flow. Hence they are not used on any major works.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "The bar screens used to cover the dam outlets to prevent entry of debris, or ice into the spillway conduits are called __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gate controlled ports",
            "b) projecting collars",
            "c) trash racks",
            "d) intakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The trash racks are made from steel bars at a spacing of about 5 to 15 cm c/c in both the directions. The floating objects like debris, ice get collected on these racks and can be removed by manual labor as well as automatic power-driven system. The spacing depends upon the maximum size of debris required to be excluded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "Projecting collars are provided on sides of a rectangular tunnel of length L made through an earthen dam to increase the seepage path. Their projection length (X) and numbers (N) are decided so as to provide increased seepage path equal to 2NX where 2NX should generally be ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than L/4",
            "b) greater than L/3",
            "c) greater than L/2",
            "d) greater than L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The seepage is reduced by increasing the length of the seepage path by at least 25%. The increase in seepage path must generally be greater than L/4.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Question": "The outlet provided in a dam body to release water for the downstream water demand is known as ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) spillway",
            "b) sluiceway",
            "c) under-sluice",
            "d) waterway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A sluiceway is a pipe or a tunnel that passes through the body of the dam or through some hillside at one end of the dam and discharges into the stream below. The sluiceways are preferred to place outside the limits of the embankments in case of spillways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 901,
        "Question": "A 2 m diameter sluiceway at RL 300 m is provided through a concrete overflow dam section to release water to the downstream where tail water level is not more than 275 m. The discharge through this outlet when the water level in the reservoir is at FRL of 330 m is of the order of_________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 cumecs",
            "b) 40 cumecs",
            "c) 50 cumecs",
            "d) 80 cumecs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The discharge passing through the dam outlet is given by using the equation-\nQ = Cd. A. (2gHL)1/2 where Cd is the coefficient of discharge = 0.62 for free over-fall, H = Water head over centre line of sluice = 330 – 300 = 30 m and A = π/4 x 4 = 3.14 m2\nQ = 0.62 x 3.14 x (2 x 9.81 x 30)1/2 = 47.23 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 902,
        "Question": "A 4 m diameter tunnel has been constructed through an earthen dam with a bell mouth entry. The water levels on the U/s and D/s sides of the dam are at RL 226 m and 210 m respectively. What will be the discharge through this outlet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 64 cumecs",
            "b) 104 cumecs",
            "c) 165 cumecs",
            "d) 216 cumecs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The discharge through the outlet is given by –\nQ = Cd. A. (2gHL)1/2  where HL = 226 – 210 = 16 m\nQ = 0.8 x (π/4 x 16) x (2 x 9.81 x 16) = 164 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 903,
        "Question": "Which of the following entrance of the sluiceway is most superior?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A square-edged entrance",
            "b) A Bell-mouthed entrance",
            "c) A rectangular entrance",
            "d) A circular entrance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As compared to Bell-mouthed or other entrance, a square edge entrance is likely to cause more separation of flow and more danger of consequent cavitation. The shape of the bell-mouthed entrance is generally elliptical and the extra cost involved I shaping this entrance is usually justified except for small projects under low heads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 904,
        "Question": "What is the correct Douma’s equation for rectangular tunnels or conduits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X2 + 10.4 Y2 = d2",
            "b) 4X2 + 10.4 Y2 = d2",
            "c) 4X2 + 44.4 Y2 = d2",
            "d) X2 – 10.4 Y2 = d2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Douma has suggested the following equation –\ni. For circular conduits: 4X2 + 44.4 Y2 = d2 where d is the diameter of the circular conduit\nii. For rectangular tunnels or conduits: X2 + 10.4 Y2 = d2 where d is the width or height of the conduit depending on whether the sides or top and bottom curves are being designed. Where X and Y are the coordinates of any point on the curve and d is the width or height of the conduit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 905,
        "Question": "What is the value of head loss for the fully open gate and butterfly valves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 V2 / 2g",
            "b) V2 / 2g",
            "c) 0.2 V2 / 2g",
            "d) 0.04 V2 / 2g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The head loss depends upon the type of gate and valves. For fully open gates and butterfly valves, a loss of about 0.2 V2 / 2g (where V is the flow velocity through the conduit) may be taken and is taken as nil for ring follower gates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 906,
        "Question": "River intakes is usually situated on ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the convex side of the curve",
            "b) the concave side of the curve",
            "c) straight reach",
            "d) the downstream side of a sewer outfall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The structure may vary from a simple concrete block supporting the end of the conduit pipe to huge concrete towers. It is constructed at the entrance of the conduit. The basic function is to help in safely withdrawing water from the reservoir over a predetermined range of pool levels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 907,
        "Question": "Which of the following intake structure is widely used in small works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sluiceways",
            "b) Simple submerged intakes",
            "c) Wet intake towers",
            "d) Dry intake towers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main disadvantage of simple submerged intakes is that they are not easily accessible for repairing of their gates etc. But, these are economical and do not obstruct navigation and are widely used in small works. These are particularly suitable as water-supply intakes from small rivers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 908,
        "Question": "A trash rack is not required at the entrance of a ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) siphon spillway",
            "b) drum gate installation",
            "c) morning glory spillway",
            "d) high-head gate installation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Drum gates can control the reservoir level upstream to precise levels automatically and without the assistance of mechanical power. It is completely enclosed on all three sides as well as on the ends forming a water-tight vessel and is hinged at the upstream end.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 909,
        "Question": "Bar screens used to cover dam outlets to prevent entry of debris or ice into the sluiceway conduits are called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gate controlled ports",
            "b) projecting collars",
            "c) trash racks",
            "d) outlets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The trash rack is generally provided as a cover for the entrance to intakes and dam outlets so as to prevent the entry of debris, ice, etc into the conduit. These are bar screens made from steel bars spaced at 5 to 15 cm center to center in both directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 910,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water can be withdrawn from any selected level of the reservoir using dry intake towers",
            "b) Intake towers have to be designed for the worst combination of hydrostatic wind earthquake and wave forces",
            "c) Dry intake towers are lighter in construction as compared to wet intake towers",
            "d) In dry intake tower, the water is directly drawn into the withdrawal conduit through the gated entry ports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The water through the entry ports with gates is directly drawn into the withdrawal conduit in a dry intake tower. Dry intake towers is heavier in construction as it is subjected to additional buoyant forces even if the gates are closed. There are separate gate controlled openings for the conduit in a wet intake tower and openings are also made into the shaft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 911,
        "Question": "The flow through the penstocks and pressure conduits is generally ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) laminar",
            "b) turbulent",
            "c) both laminar and turbulent",
            "d) unpredictable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Penstocks are the huge diameter pipe which carries water under pressure and the structural design is similar to that of pressure pipes. Since there is a possibility of sudden load changes in penstocks which changes the pressure and flow velocity which characterizes the turbulent flow in fluid dynamics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 912,
        "Question": "The head loss in the flow of water through a penstock pipe of given length ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases with the increase in flow velocity",
            "b) decreases with the increase in flow velocity",
            "c) decreases with the increase in the roughness of the pipe surface",
            "d) decreases with time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The head loss (HL) by pipe friction is given by Darcy-Weisbach equation –\nHL = f’. V2. L / 2gd where L is the length of pipe in meters, d is the diameter of the pipe, V is the velocity of the pipe and f’ is the friction factor which depends on Reynold’s number and the relative roughness of the pipe.\nIt is clear from the given equation that the head loss is directly proportional to the length of the pipe hence the head loss increases with the increase in the length of the pipe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 913,
        "Question": "Hoop’s reinforcement is provided in cement concrete pressure pipes in order to counteract the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) water hammer pressure",
            "b) internal hammer pressure",
            "c) stresses caused by the external backfills",
            "d) both water hammer pressure and internal hammer pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hoop’s tension is the internal pressure exerted on the walls of the pipe by flowing water and the circumferential tensile stress (T1) is given by –\nT1 = p1 d/2t where p1 is the internal static pressure, d is the diameter of the pipe and t is the thickness of the pipe shell.\nSimilarly, the circumferential tensile stress caused by water hammer pressure is given by –\nT2 = p2 d/2t where p2 is the maximum water hammer pressure developed in pipelines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 914,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of pressure conduits is preferably used for large heads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCC pipes",
            "b) Cast iron pipes",
            "c) Pre-stressed concrete pipes",
            "d) Asbestos pipes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a liquid is flowing in a pipeline is abruptly stopped by the closing of the valve, it destroys the momentum and retards the velocity of water column behind. This exerts a thrust on the valve, an additional pressure on the pipe shell and it may be so high as to cause bursting of the pipe shell. The more rapid is the closure of the valve, the more rapid is the change in momentum and hence, greater hammer pressure is developed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 915,
        "Question": "Which head loss formula is also applicable to turbulent flow in pressure conduits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darch-Weisbach equation",
            "b) Manning’s formula",
            "c) Hazen-Williams formula",
            "d) Both Darch-Weisbach and Manning’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pre-stressed concrete pipes have more strength than RCC pipes and are more economical. The strength can be achieved by circumferential pre-stressing so as to increase the tensile stress. The main advantage is that they offer a cost advantage over other pipes for large diameter and higher pressures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 916,
        "Question": "__________________ joint is often used for connecting cast iron pipes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible joint",
            "b) Expansion joint",
            "c) Collar joints",
            "d) Bell and spigot joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Manning’s formula is also applicable to the turbulent flow in pressure conduits. It yields good results provided the roughness coefficient is accurately determined. The head loss is expressed as –\nHL = n2. V2. L / R4/3 where, n = manning’s rugosity coefficient, L is the length of pipe, V is the flow velocity through pipe and R is the hydraulic mean depth of the pipe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 917,
        "Question": "Which of the following conduits is used when large diameter pipes of smaller wall thickness are required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast iron conduits",
            "b) Galvanized steel pipes",
            "c) Hume steel conduits",
            "d) Centrifugal type RCC pipe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pipes which are to be joined are made in such a way that one end is enlarged (also called socket or bell) and the other end is normal (i.e. spigot). The spigot end is inserted into the bell and the remaining space is filled with molten lead which gets solidified and thus making a water-tight joint.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 918,
        "Question": "A special flexible joint called simplex joint is generally used to join _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vitrified clay conduits",
            "b) galvanised iron pipes",
            "c) asbestos conduits",
            "d) hume steel conduits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Galvanised steel pipes (with circumferential corrugations) are much stronger than ordinary steel pipes. These are usually manufactured in various sizes varying from 20 cm to 2 meters in diameter. They are lighter and can be more easily transported at distances and are widely used where large pipes of smaller wall thickness are required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 919,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel conduits are lighter than cast iron pipes",
            "b) RCC pipes are generally made from 1:2:4 cement concrete with a maximum size of aggregates as 6 mm",
            "c) RCC pipes and Hume steel conduits are heavy and difficult to handle",
            "d) Riveted pipes are smoother and stronger than welded pipes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Asbestos conduits are highly flexible and may permit as much as 120 deflections in laying them around curves. Expansion joints are not required as the coefficient of expansion is low and the joints are also flexible i.e. simplex joint. Its assembly consists of pipe sleeve and two rubber rings which are compressed between the pipe and the interior of the sleeve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 920,
        "Question": "Which of the following pipes is used for carrying hot water in the interior of the building?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wrought iron pipes",
            "b) Copper pipes",
            "c) Galvanised iron pipes",
            "d) Plastic pipes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Steel is strong in tension and even large size diameter pipes can be made of thin shells. They are therefore lighter than cast iron pipes. Welded pipes are smoother and stronger than riveted pipes. But steel pipes get rusted easily and are protected on the inside as well as outside by protective coatings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 921,
        "Question": "A hydropower plant developed at the site of a drop in an irrigation canal is of the type ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) runoff river plant",
            "b) storage plant",
            "c) pumped storage plant",
            "d) tidal plant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the Run-off river installation, power is generated on the basis of day to day flow in the river. To maintain the water level at a pre-determined level, a weir or a barrage across the river is sometimes constructed. The excess water during the peak-off hours is temporarily stored on u/s side of the barrage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 922,
        "Question": "A nuclear power development scheme is essentially a _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thermal power scheme",
            "b) hydropower scheme",
            "c) both thermal and hydropower scheme",
            "d) atomic power scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nuclear power station is the one where atomic fuel is used to produce steam. The steam is produced in water boilers in case of an ordinary thermal power station and in atomic power station, the boiler is replaced by a nuclear reactor and steam generator. This electric power generation scheme is called thermal power scheme.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 923,
        "Question": "Fossil fuels are used in _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a nuclear power plant",
            "b) an ordinary thermal power plant",
            "c) a hydropower plant",
            "d) atomic power plant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fossils fuels like coal, gas, oil, etc and atomic fuel are used to generate steam. Thermal power station or ordinary thermal power station is the one where the conventional type of fuels i.e. fossil fuels is used to produce steam for running the turbine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 924,
        "Question": "A runoff river plant for hydropower generation is essentially a ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high head scheme",
            "b) medium head scheme",
            "c) low head scheme",
            "d) any of the schemes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Run-off river plant is essentially a low head scheme. The plant installed on main rivers or on diversion canals is usually provided with small storage to meet the short term fluctuations of the water requirement of the plant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 925,
        "Question": "A storage hydro plant essentially involves ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a barrage or a weir",
            "b) a dam",
            "c) either barrage or a dam",
            "d) check dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A dam is constructed across the river and the powerhouse may be located at the foot of the dam. The powerhouse may sometimes be located much away from the dam at the end of the tunnels which carry water away from the reservoir.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 926,
        "Question": "The natural high waterfalls may be used for generation of ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydro-power",
            "b) water-power",
            "c) both hydropower and water power",
            "d) thermal power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydroelectricity can be generated from naturally existing waterfalls while most hydroelectric plants generate water from human-made waterfalls. The naturally available high falls can also be developed for generating electric power and the common examples are Jog falls in India and Niagara falls in the USA.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 927,
        "Question": "Which among the following is an example of a tidal plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rance power station in France",
            "b) Ganguwal powerhouse located on Nangal hydel channel in India",
            "c) Sarda powerhouse located on Sarda canal in UP in India",
            "d) Mohammad Pur and Pathri powerhouses on Ganga Canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water that runs back to the ocean during low tides is also utilized to generate electric power and special turbines are provided for the same. Rance power station is an example of such tidal plants. The tidal range is about 11 meters and this powerhouse contains 9 units of 38,000 KW.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 928,
        "Question": "When the powerhouse is located near the dam as is done in the low head installations, it is known as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) concentrated fall hydroelectric development",
            "b) divided fall hydroelectric development",
            "c) concentrated fall thermal power development",
            "d) divided fall thermal power development"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Divided fall development is the one where the water is carried to the powerhouse at a considerable distance from the dam through a canal. Concentrated fall hydroelectric development is the one when powerhouse is located near the dam as in low head installations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 929,
        "Question": "Which of the following plants utilize the minimum flow in a river having no appreciable pondage on its upstream side?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage plant",
            "b) Run-off river plant",
            "c) Pumped storage plants",
            "d) Tidal plants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Run-off river plants utilize the minimum flow in a river having no appreciable pondage on its upstream side. The excess water is temporarily stored in the pond on u/s side when the discharge at the site is more than the demand i.e. peak-off hours. It is then utilized during peak hours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 930,
        "Question": "Which among the following plant generates power during peak hours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage plant",
            "b) Run-off river plant",
            "c) Pumped storage plants",
            "d) Tidal plants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During off-peak hours, the water is pumped back from the tailwater pool to the headwater pool for future use. The pumped storage plant is primarily meant for assisting an existing thermal plant or some hydel plant. They generate power during peak hours only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 931,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is not an example of High head scheme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bhakra dam in Punjab",
            "b) Rihand dam In UP",
            "c) Hoover Dam in the USA",
            "d) Sarda canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This scheme uses a water head of more than 60 m or so. The common examples are Bhakra dam in Punjab, Rihand dam in UP and the Hoover Dam in the USA. Sarda powerhouse on Sarda canal is under low to the medium head scheme.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 932,
        "Question": "Pondage in a hydropower station is _________________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pond level",
            "b) temporary storage to meet peak demands",
            "c) excess runoff to last for years",
            "d) excess runoff for a few hours only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pondage takes care of the hour to hour fluctuations over a day or occasionally day to day fluctuations over a weekly cycle. It ensures that the desired instantaneous rate of flow into the turbines under day to day changing conditions of power load as well as of inflow. It may also be provided for weekly demands.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 933,
        "Question": "Which of the following plant uses a reversible turbine that can work at relatively high efficiencies and helps in reducing the cost of such a plant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Run-off river plant",
            "b) Storage plant",
            "c) Pumped storage plant",
            "d) Tidal plant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A weir or a barrage is constructed to raise the level and the powerhouse is constructed either in the continuation or at some distance downstream of the barrage. The water is taken through an intake canal called the power canal or the diversion canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 934,
        "Question": "As per estimate made by the Central Electricity Authority, the potential of the country is accessed at 84 GW at load factor value of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40%",
            "b) 60%",
            "c) 80%",
            "d) 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This equivalent to about 440 billion units + KWh of annual energy generation at a power factor of 0.6. 60% load factor means that the installed machines are run on an average to give output capacity equal to 60% of the station capacity. Machines will not always work at the installed capacity but on an average of 60% of this capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 935,
        "Question": "The first power station of India was installed at _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mysore",
            "b) Bombay",
            "c) Darjeeling",
            "d) Bangalore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first hydropower station in India dates back to the year 1897 when a small power station of 200 KW capacities was constructed in Darjeeling. Then it was followed by a 50 MW Tata Electric project of Bombay in 1914.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 936,
        "Question": "What is the correct expansion of DAE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Department of Atomic Energy",
            "b) The Discipline of Atomic Energy",
            "c) The Division of Atomic Energy",
            "d) The Domain of Atomic Energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This department directly runs under the Prime Minister of India with headquarters in Mumbai, Maharashtra. The main aim of the department is to increase nuclear power production from 3% to 8% of the total electricity generation in the next 15 years.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 937,
        "Question": "In India, the nuclear power generation is about ____________ of the total power generation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3%",
            "b) 4%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 6%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nuclear power generation is only about 3% of the total power generation including hydropower, thermal power, nuclear power, etc. The Indian Department of Atomic Energy is planning to boost its generation in the next 15 years from 3% to 8% of the total electricity generation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 938,
        "Question": "Which one is the first nuclear power plant in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tarapur atomic power station",
            "b) Kaiga atomic power station",
            "c) Rawatbhata Atomic power station",
            "d) Narora atomic power station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tarapur Atomic power station 320 MW is located in Tarapur, Maharashtra and it was the first commercial nuclear power station. The construction began in 1961 and went operational in 1969. It has two 160 MW water boiling reactors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 939,
        "Question": "Convert the hydropower potential of 84 GW at 60% load factor into Trillion watts hour.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 441 TWh",
            "b) 735 TWh",
            "c) 553 TWh",
            "d) 345 TWh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 1 TW (Trillion watt) = 1000 GW (Giga watt)\n84 GW is equivalent to = 84 x 365 x 24 = 735,840 GW hour\nAt 60 % load factor = 735,840 x 0.6 = 441,504 GW hour = 441 TWh or 441 b KWh.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 940,
        "Question": "The minimum power which a hydropower plant can generate throughout the year is called as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) power plant capacity",
            "b) power plant load",
            "c) firm power",
            "d) water power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The firm power is the net amount of power which is continuously available from a plant without any break on a guaranteed basis. The consumers can always be sure of getting this power and this power is available under the most adverse hydraulic conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 941,
        "Question": "If the peak load for a power plant equals the plant capacity then the ratio of the capacity factor to load factor will be _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) < 1",
            "d) > 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Load factor = Average load over a certain period / Peak load during that period\nCapacity factor = Average load over a given time period / Plant capacity\nSince, Plant capacity = Peak load\nRatio of CF / LF = 1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 942,
        "Question": "If the peak load on a power plant having a capacity of 100 MW is 70 MW during a given week and the energy produced is 58, 80,000 kWh, the capacity factor for the plant for the week will be ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 70%",
            "d) 65%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacity factor = Average load/ Plant capacity\nAverage load = Energy produced / Time (in hours) = 58,80,000 / 7 x 24 = 35000 kW\nC.F = 35 MW / 100 MW = 0.35 (or 35%).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 943,
        "Question": "During a certain week a power plant turns out 84,00,000 kWh and the peak load during the week is 100,000 kW. What is the load factor during the week?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40%",
            "b) 45%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 60%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Load factor can be defined as the ratio of average load to the peak load over a given period.\nAverage load = 84,000,000 / (24 x 7) = 50,000 kW\nL.F = Average load / Peak load = 50,000 / 100,000 = 0.5 or 50%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 944,
        "Question": "A canal drop is 6 meters and discharges available through the turbine is 50 cumec. Find the electrical energy available.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2352 KW",
            "b) 2352 MW",
            "c) 2.352 kW",
            "d) 235.2 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electrical energy (in kW) = 7.84 Q H (using 80% efficiency) where H is the design head in meters and Q is the design discharge in cumecs.\nElectrical energy = 7.84 x 50 x 6 = 2352 kW.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 945,
        "Question": "The ratio of maximum power utilised to the maximum power available is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) power factor",
            "b) plant use factor",
            "c) reserve capacity",
            "d) capacity factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plant use factor is nothing but utilization factor which can be defined as the ratio of maximum power utilized to the maximum power available if the water head is assumed to be constant. The value usually varies from 0.4 to 0.9 for a hydel plant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 946,
        "Question": "The net amount of power which is continuously available from a plant without any break is known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) firm power",
            "b) secondary power",
            "c) power factor",
            "d) utilization factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Secondary power is the excess power available over firm power during peak-off hours. It is supplied to consumers as and when available basis. Power factor is the ratio of actual power (in kW) to the apparent power (in kilo volt-ampere).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 947,
        "Question": "The value of power factor is generally _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal to unity",
            "b) less than unity",
            "c) greater than unity",
            "d) equal to zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of power factor depends upon the relationship between the inductance and resistance in the load and it can never be greater than unity. The usual system load has a power factor varying from 0.8 to 0.9. But if various induction motors are installed in the load, the value will be 0.5.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 948,
        "Question": "To ensure maximum overall plant efficiency, the rated head should be equal to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the design head",
            "b) the gross head",
            "c) the operating head",
            "d) effective head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Rated head is the head at which the turbine functioning at full gate opening will produce a power output. It is nothing but the specified head that is in the nameplate of the turbine. This is equal to the design head of the turbine so as to ensure maximum overall plant efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 949,
        "Question": "The difference of head at the point of entry and exit of turbine is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) design head",
            "b) gross head",
            "c) effective head",
            "d) rated head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Design head is the net head under which the turbine reaches peak efficiency. The difference in the water level elevations at the point of diversion of water for the hydel scheme and the point of return of water back to the river is called a gross head. The rated head is the head that is specified in the name-plate of the turbine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 950,
        "Question": "The load on a hydel plant varies from a minimum of 10,000 kW to a maximum of 35,000 kW. Two turbo-generators of capacities 20,000 kW each have been installed. Calculate Plant factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 51%",
            "c) 56.2%",
            "d) 59.7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plant factor can be defined as the ratio of the energy actually produced (Average load) to the maximum energy that can be produced at a particular time.\nSince two turbo generators are installed, the total installed capacity = 40000 kW\nP.F = [(10000 + 35000) / 2] / 40000 = 56%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 951,
        "Question": "Calculate utilisation factor if the maximum power utilised is 40,000 kW and two turbo generators installed each of capacity 23,000 kW.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 73%",
            "b) 87%",
            "c) 57.5%",
            "d) 63%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Utilisation factor = Maximum power utilised / Maximum power available\nU.F = 40,000 / (2 x 23000) = 86.9% (since two generators are installed).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 952,
        "Question": "If the peak load on a power plant having a capacity of 100 MW is 70 MW during a given week. Calculate the utilization factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.35",
            "b) 0.50",
            "c) 0.70",
            "d) 0.60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The utilization factor is the ratio of the maximum power utilized to the maximum power available.\nU.F = Max power utilised/ Max power available = 70 / 100 = 0.7.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 953,
        "Question": "400 cumecs of water are being released from dam storage to meet the downstream demand through the turbines of the connected hydro plant. The effective head of water acting on the turbines is 50 m. The efficiency of the hydro plant is 0.8. The electrical power generated from this plant is __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,56,800 MW",
            "b) 156.8 M kW",
            "c) 156.8 MW",
            "d) 156.8 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Using 80% efficiency, Electrical energy = 7.84 QH where H is the design head in meters and Q is the design discharge in cumecs.\nElectrical energy = 7.84 x 400 x 50 = 1, 56,800 kW = 156.80 MW.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 954,
        "Question": "What is the highest elevation of water level that can be maintained in the reservoir without any spillway discharge either with gated or non-gated spillway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal Water level",
            "b) Minimum Water level",
            "c) Weighted average level",
            "d) Operating head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minimum water level is that elevation of water level which produces minimum net head on the power units i.e. 65% of the design head. The weighted average level is the level above and below which equal amounts of power are developed during an average year. Operating head is the difference of elevation of entrance and the tail-race exit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 955,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of an impulse turbine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton turbine",
            "b) Francis turbine",
            "c) Kaplan turbine",
            "d) Propeller turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the impulse turbine, all the potential energy or head is converted into kinetic energy or velocity head by passing the water through a contracting nozzle or by guide vanes before it strikes the buckets. Some types of impulse turbine are Pelton wheel, Turgo impulse wheel, and Girard turbine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 956,
        "Question": "Which of the following is turbine is used for medium heads ranging from 25 to 150 meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton turbine",
            "b) Kaplan turbine",
            "c) Francis turbine",
            "d) Propeller turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For high heads over 150 meters, a low-speed turbine like Pelton wheel is suitable. Francis turbine is used for medium heads varying from 25 to 150 meters and for low heads, Kaplan and propeller turbines are used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 957,
        "Question": "An impulse turbine is essentially a __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) low-speed turbine and is used for high heads",
            "b) low-speed turbine and is used for low heads",
            "c) high-speed turbine and is used for high heads",
            "d) high-speed turbine and is used for low heads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a low-speed wheel and is relatively used for high heads over 150 meters. It works under high heads so comparatively less quantity of water is required. Pelton’s turbine is an important example of an impulse type of turbine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 958,
        "Question": "An impulse turbine like a Pelton’s turbine is __________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) an open body exposed to the atmosphere",
            "b) a closed body not exposed to the atmosphere",
            "c) a partially open and partially closed body",
            "d) depends on the design requirements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Kaplan turbines have an additional arrangement of adjusting the inclination of the runner blades or vanes on the hub. This causes the Kaplan turbine to give higher efficiency even under part-load conditions although both the turbines look alike and behave hydraulically in a similar fashion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 959,
        "Question": "In a reaction turbine like a Francis turbine or a Kaplan turbine ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the potential head of water is totally changed into the kinetic head",
            "b) the potential head of water is partially changed into the kinetic head",
            "c) the potential head of water is not at all changed into the kinetic head",
            "d) the change of potential head of water totally or partially depends on other factors as well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water through a contacting nozzle or by guide vanes is made to strike on a series of buckets. The wheel revolves free in the air and the water is in contact with only a part of the wheel at a time and the pressure is atmospheric. A casing is provided in order to prevent splashing and to guide the water discharged from the buckets to the tail-race.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 960,
        "Question": "For a hydropower plant having 150 m head of stored water behind the dam. The water in the reservoir is clear and load on the powerhouse is not likely to fluctuate much. Which type of turbine will be suitable for the same?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton turbine",
            "b) Francis turbine",
            "c) Kaplan turbine",
            "d) Propeller turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a reaction turbine, only part of the available potential energy is converted into velocity head at the entrance to the runner. The balance portion remains as a pressure head. In Francis turbine, there is an inward radial flow of water and in Francis turbine, there is a mixed flow of water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 961,
        "Question": "For a hydropower plant working on 150 m head, the water is sandy and the load on the plant is highly variable. Which type of turbine will generally be recommended?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton Turbine",
            "b) Francis turbine",
            "c) Kaplan turbine",
            "d) Propeller turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Francis turbine, the water enters radially inward but leaves in a parallel direction to the shaft at the center, it is called mixed flow. In the case of a reaction turbine like Francis turbine, a draft tube is used to connect the outlets of the runner to the tailrace.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 962,
        "Question": "If two identical pumps each capable to deliver a discharge Q against a head H are connected ___________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) in parallel, the resulting discharge is 2Q against a head H",
            "b) in parallel, the resulting discharge is Q against a head of 2H",
            "c) in series, the resulting discharge is 2Q against a head H",
            "d) in series, the resulting discharge is Q against a head 2H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Francis turbines are cheaper than Pelton’s turbine and there is no special need for Pelton’s turbine because variable loads are not likely to come and water is not sandy which may certainly need Pelton’s turbines. Hence, Francis turbine will suffice to our needs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 963,
        "Question": "If the specific speed in revolution per minute of a turbine is in between 60 to 300, the type of the turbine is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton turbine",
            "b) Francis turbine",
            "c) Propeller turbine",
            "d) Kaplan turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For variable loads (part loads) and sandy water, Pelton’s wheel is most suitable. These are preferred where the available water source has a relatively high head at low flow rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 964,
        "Question": "Pick the correct choice of turbine required to generate 10,000 HP under a head of 81 m while working at a speed of 500 rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelton",
            "b) Kaplan",
            "c) Bulb",
            "d) Francis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Water pumps are installed in parallel as in the case of pumping water from a sump well using more than one pump. The head remains constant and the combined discharge of the two pumps is equal to the sum of the individual discharges for a specific head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 965,
        "Question": "Which of these statements are correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) i and ii",
            "b) ii and iii",
            "c) i and iv",
            "d) ii and iv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific speed of a Pelton turbine ranges from 10 to 30. Francis turbine has a specific speed between 60 to 300 and the specific speed of Kaplan and propeller turbine lies in between 300 to 1000.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 966,
        "Question": "Forebay provides temporary storage before the water goes to the turbine. Following perform the function of forebay ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) river",
            "b) tailrace channel",
            "c) reservoir",
            "d) approach channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reservoir itself acts as a forebay when it is constructed by building a dam. The water is taken to the powerhouse directly from the reservoir through penstocks. Following are some functions of forebay:\n• To temporarily store water and to meet the instantaneous demand\n• Absorbs the short interval variations and fluctuations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 967,
        "Options": [
            "a) i and ii",
            "b) ii and iii",
            "c) iii and iv",
            "d) i, ii and iii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cylindrical chamber which is connected to the penstocks and open to the atmosphere is the simplest one. It serves the following functions i.e. to reduce the pressure fluctuations in the pipe and helps in eliminating additional water hammer pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 968,
        "Question": "Identify the correct statement in regard to hydropower.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydropower stations are generally labour-oriented",
            "b) The gestation period for hydro-power plant is usually small",
            "c) The hydro generators give high efficiency over a wide range of load",
            "d) In a hydropower scheme, the firm power is usually high as compared to tidal power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydroelectric power plants are the most efficient means of producing energy and the efficiency of today’s hydroelectric plant is about 90%. Large hydropower plants usually have a gestation period of about 7 years whereas for smaller plants it is 2 to 5 years.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 969,
        "Question": "To avoid the possible damage to the wicket gates and turbine runners _________________ is provided.",
        "Options": [
            "a) trash racks",
            "b) surge chamber",
            "c) floating boom",
            "d) racks and trolley arrangement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intakes should be provided with trash racks so as to prevent the entry of debris into the penstocks or to prevent choking up of the nozzles of the impulse turbines. Trash racks are made up of thin flat steel bars placed 10 to 30 cm apart and the permissible velocity of water entering these is 0.6 to 1.6 m/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 970,
        "Question": "In case of long penstocks, ___________________ is generally provided so as to absorb water hammer pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) trash racks",
            "b) surge chamber",
            "c) floating boom",
            "d) racks and trolley arrangement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The surge tank is mostly employed in a water power plant or in a large pumping plant to control the pressure variations resulting from rapid changes in the flow. It is done by admitting a large mass of water in the surge tank otherwise it would have flown out of the pipeline and returns to the tank due to closure of pipe end.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 971,
        "Question": "The retarding and accelerating heads are developed more promptly in ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) simple surge tank",
            "b) restricted orifice surge chamber",
            "c) differential surge chamber",
            "d) multi surge chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sharp bends cause loss of head and requires special anchorages. It may be buried under the ground or kept exposed. The penstock can be replaced by constructing a tunnel through a hill if a considerable saving in length can be gained.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 972,
        "Question": "The correct sequence in the direction of the flow of water for installations in a hydropower plant is _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reservoir, Surge tank, Turbine, Penstock",
            "b) Reservoir, Penstock, Surge tank, Turbine",
            "c) Reservoir, Penstock, Turbine, Surge tank",
            "d) Reservoir, Surge tank, Penstock, Turbine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The differential surge chamber has a central riser pipe in addition to the main outer tank and the retarding and accelerating heads are developed more promptly. The capacity of a different type of surge chamber may be less than that of a simple elementary type for a given amount of stabilizing effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 973,
        "Question": "What is the minimum depth of water required for safe and economical navigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 m",
            "b) 2 m",
            "c) 2.7 m",
            "d) 4.2 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The availability of sufficient water depth in the waterway is the chief requirement for navigations and for safe and economical navigation, a minimum depth of 2.7 m is generally required. Lesser depth in the rivers completely eliminates the possibility of towing the ships and causes an increase in the unit cost of transport and a depth of 3.7 m is generally desired in the final development.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 974,
        "Question": "The belt conveyor forming an essential part of a ladder dredger used for excavating river sand deposits is used for _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) excavation of sand",
            "b) transporting excavated sand to the surface over small distances",
            "c) transporting excavated sand to the surface over large distances",
            "d) transporting excavated sand to the surface over all distances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flow velocities should be low as high velocity causes a substantial reduction in the true speed for tows moving upstream. This increases the time of transit and cost of transport per kilometer. The speed of the barge tows in still water is almost 2.8 m/sec.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 975,
        "Question": "The dredger which excavates sand deposits of a river and discharges the excavated material with water over long distances is called a _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ladder dredger",
            "b) suction dredger",
            "c) dipper dredger",
            "d) upper dredger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ladder dredger has an endless chain of buckets for bringing the excavated material up to the surface and the cuttings carried by buckets are discharged on a belt conveyor. The material is then disposed of through a stacker conveyor at the rear of the dredger which is limited in length to about 100 m or so.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 976,
        "Question": "Lock and dams constructions for creation of a series of slack-water pools along a river for promoting its navigability is adopted only when ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the river is perennial",
            "b) the river carries heavy sediment load",
            "c) the available water in the river is quite less",
            "d) the available water in the river is quite large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dipper dredgers are used on small projects and are merely floating power shovels. Ladder dredger is used when the excavated materials are to be discharged at a considerable distance from the dredge. The disadvantage of the suction dredge is that it cannot operate in rocky or Shoulder River reaches.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 977,
        "Question": "Timber is generally transported in our country through ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rail routes",
            "b) road routes",
            "c) air routes",
            "d) water routes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This arrangement is generally adopted where existing site conditions are not favorable for adopting open channel methods. The water is required for lockage, sanitary releases, evaporation, percolation, etc and the requirement is much less than that of open channel procedures. Hence, it is adopted when the water available is less.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 978,
        "Question": "What is the oldest and cheapest mode of transporting cargo?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rail routes",
            "b) Road routes",
            "c) Air routes",
            "d) Water routes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Very heavy items like cargo are also packed on wagon trains or trucks is lifted and transported through water transport. Besides the fact that it is the cheaper mode of transport, it is also used for recreational boating. The imports and exports are done by means of water routes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 979,
        "Question": "Ships or steamers can pay to carry cargo in Indian waterways extending to about ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500 km",
            "b) 2500 km",
            "c) 10,000 km",
            "d) 40,000 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water transport is cheaper because the coefficient of friction on the water is small. On the water, one horsepower can pull 4 tonnes while on road and rail, it can move approximately 0.15 tonne and 0.5 tonnes respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 980,
        "Question": "The alignment of the waterway should be________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) straight",
            "b) circular",
            "c) parabola",
            "d) irregular alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is about 15,000 km length of navigable waterways in India and most of them are in bad conditions due to poor silting and maintenance. Most of it is fit only for boating and the streamers can ply only for about 2500 km length. For the total navigable length of about 15,000 km, about 8000 km is on rivers and 7000 km is on canals and backwaters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 981,
        "Question": "Which of the following dredger is not suitable for rocky or boulder river reaches?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suction dredger",
            "b) Ladder dredger",
            "c) Dipper dredger",
            "d) Both ladder and dipper dredger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A highly irregular alignment increases the circuitry or length in excess pf airline distance which the barge tow must travel. The existing channels generally have a length of about 50% greater than the air-line distances. Hence, the alignment should be as straight as possible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 982,
        "Question": "The depth of water stored in an irrigation tank rarely exceeds ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 m",
            "b) 8 m",
            "c) 12 m",
            "d) 16 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most of the existing tanks possess a maximum depth of 4.5 m, only a few tanks are as deep as 7.5 to 9 m. Only in the exceptional cases, the depth exceeds 11 m in depth. The tank is generally referred to as a reservoir when the depth of the tank exceeds 12 m or so.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 983,
        "Question": "The storage created on the upstream side of a smaller stream by the construction of low earthen bunds is technically known as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) a reservoir",
            "b) a tank",
            "c) a lake",
            "d) a pond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The storage irrigation scheme utilizes the stored water on the upstream side of a smaller earth dam i.e. bund. These earthen bund reservoirs are called as tanks. Such works are very common in South India but this terminology is limited to India only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 984,
        "Question": "The cubic meters of water that can be stored in an irrigation tank between full tank level and sill level of the lowest supply sluice is known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the gross capacity",
            "b) effective capacity",
            "c) the specific capacity",
            "d) total capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A breaching section is a length kept lower and weaker than the remainder of the bound so as to localize a breach in that length only. A breach occurring in a tank supplements the surplus power to a reasonable degree to the greater security both of the tank itself and those below it in the group.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 985,
        "Question": "If A1 represents the area of a tank bed at bottom and A2 is the area of the tank at F.T.L, then the storage capacity of the tank of height H is given as ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H [A1 + A2 + A1.A2] ",
            "b) H/2 [A1 + A2 + A1.A2] ",
            "c) H/3 [A1 + A2 + A1.A2] ",
            "d) 2H [A1 + A2 + A1.A2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cubic content of water stored in the tank up to F.T.L is called the gross capacity of the tank. The cubic content of water stored between F.T.L and the bottom or sill level of the lowest supply sluice is the effective capacity of the tank. These capacities can be computed by using the contour plan of the area of the water spread.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 986,
        "Question": "The top-level of a tank weir in a tank bund scheme is kept at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum Water Level (M.W.L)",
            "b) Full Tank Level (F.T.L)",
            "c) Either M.W.L or F.T.L",
            "d) Full Supply Level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The effective cubic content of the tank may be computed as H/3 [A1 + A2 + A1.A2] where H is the height or difference in elevations between F.T.L and the sill level of the lowest sluice. This is based on the assumption that the water stored is in the shape of a frustum of a cone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 987,
        "Question": "The usual arrangement made in a tank-bund scheme to spill the surplus excess water is known as ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tank spillway",
            "b) tank sluice",
            "c) tank weir",
            "d) tank bunds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The top-level i.e. crest level of the tank weir is kept at F.T.L. The extra water is discharged over the surplus escape weir when the tank is full up to F.T.L. The design of the length or capacity of this surplus escape weir is such that the water level in the tank never exceeds the M.W.L.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 988,
        "Question": "If A1 and A2 represent the areas enclosed between two successive contours, then the cubic content between these contours is roughly taken as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (A1 + A2) x h/2",
            "b) A1.A2 x h/2",
            "c) A1 x h/2",
            "d) A2 x h/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To avoid overtopping of the tank bund in case of all dam reservoir projects, tanks are provided with arrangements for spilling the excess surplus water. These arrangements may be in the form of a surplus escape weir provided in the body or at one end of the tank bund. In the case of earth dam projects, some other arrangements like a siphon spillway can be provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 989,
        "Question": "The most adopted earthen section for tank bunds is of the type ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) homogeneous embankment type",
            "b) zoned embankment type",
            "c) diaphragm type",
            "d) both diaphragm and zoned type embankment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cubic content between two successive contours is computed as (A1 + A2) x h/2. The required storage capacity of the tank is the summation of all cubic contents between the successive contours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 990,
        "Question": "What is the approximate value of side slope of the bund for smaller tanks with water depths not exceeding 2.5 m in favorable soils such as red and white gravel, red and black loams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 H : 1 V",
            "b) \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) H : 1 V",
            "c) 2 \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) H : 1V",
            "d) 1 \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\) H : 1 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Homogeneous embankment has been constructed with the soils excavated from pits in the immediate vicinity of each bund and carried by the head load to the bund. Most of the tank bunds of South India belong to this type.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 991,
        "Question": "The usual difference between F.T.L and M.T.L is rarely allowed to exceed _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3 m",
            "b) 0.6 m",
            "c) 0.9 m",
            "d) 0.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This difference is fixed on a compromise basis in order to obtain the overall economy and efficiency. It is kept from 0.3 to 0.6 m for small and medium-sized tanks and is rarely allowed to exceed 0.9 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 992,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of tank weirs are provided with a number of vertical steps instead of horizontal or sloping downstream apron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type A: Masonry weir with a vertical drop",
            "b) Type B: Rock-fill weirs with a sloping apron",
            "c) Type C: Masonry weirs with a glacis",
            "d) Type D: Combination of Type A and Type C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Weirs of Type-D are called as weirs with stepped aprons as they are provided with a number of vertical steps as in case of a stepped fall instead of providing a horizontal or sloping downstream apron. Type-A and Type-D weirs are the most widely adopted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 993,
        "Question": "The width of the horizontal floors of type A and D weirs from the foot of the drop wall to the d/s edge of the floor should never be less than ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 (D + H)",
            "b) 3 (D + H)",
            "c) 2.5 (D + H)",
            "d) 2 (D + H)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The width of the horizontal floor of Type-A and Type-D weirs should not be less than 2(D + H) and in important works, the width can be increased to 3(D + H). where D is the height of drop wall and H is the maximum head of water over the wall. The rough stone apron forming a talus below the last curtain wall generally vary from 2.5(D+ H) to 5(D + H) depending upon the nature of the soil and the velocity and annual probable quantity and intensity of run-off.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 994,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a correct representation of Ryve’s formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qp = C1. A2/3",
            "b) Qp = C1. A1/3",
            "c) Qp = C1. L A2/3",
            "d) Qp = C1. A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All tank weirs generally in South India are designed on the basis of Ryve’s formula which is given by:\nQp = C1.A2/3 where Qp is the peak flood discharge, C1 is the Ryve’s coefficient, A is the catchment area\nThe formula is directly applicable for free catchments in all isolated tanks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 995,
        "Question": "The capacity of an irrigation tank is sometimes increased by installing a temporary stone wall over the top of the tank weir. This fixture is known as____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) saddle",
            "b) dam stone",
            "c) breast wall",
            "d) divide wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A common practice has been resorted to in South India is to fix dam stones at the crest wall of the weir. The dam stones cause obstruction to the discharge and if no dam stones or shutters are provided above F.T.L, the flood water will start spilling over the surplus work immediately after the tank water level exceeds F.T.L.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 996,
        "Question": "The discharge through the sluice of a small irrigation tank is usually controlled by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dam stone",
            "b) plug",
            "c) special balanced valves",
            "d) shutters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flat shutters working in grooves and regulated by screw spears are used in the case of large tanks where the quantity of water to be released is great. Special balanced valves or shutters moving on rollers are generally installed for heads over 9 m or so. A Dam stone causes obstruction to flow and is used sometimes to increase the capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 997,
        "Question": "What will the discharging capacity of a masonry waste weir of 55 m length and 1.5 m width provided in an earthen bund for passing a flood with 1.2 m water depth over its crest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 cumecs",
            "b) 254 cumecs",
            "c) 59.4 cumecs",
            "d) 65.8 cumecs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The discharge over the weir without any velocity of approach is given by –\nQ = C.L H3/2 where C = 1.66 when the width of rectangular crest > 0.9 m, L is the length of the weir and H is the head of water over the weir.\nQ = 1.66 x 55 x 1.23/2 = 120 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 998,
        "Question": "Pipe sluices are generally not adopted in tank bunds where the depth below F.T.L exceeds ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 m",
            "b) 1 m",
            "c) 2.5 m",
            "d) 5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pipe sluices are earthenware or cement or cast iron pipes which may be used in place of masonry culverts in case of very small slices. The earthenware pipes may get fractured or leakage through their joints may take place resulting in a breach. The pipes can neither be examined nor repaired easily without cutting open the bund. They are not adopted when the depth below F.T.L exceeds 2.5 m or so.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 999,
        "Question": "9. Calculate peak discharge for a combined catchment of a tank forming a constituent unit of a group with the following given data –<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"text\"><pre class=\"de1\">Combined catchment \t\t\t     = 26 sq. km\nIntercepted catchment \t\t\t     = 20 sq. km\nRyve’s coefficient for combined catchment    = 9.0\nRyve’s coefficient intercepted \t\t     = 1.8</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) 66 cumecs",
            "b) 59 cumecs",
            "c) 50 cumecs",
            "d) 69 cumecs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using Ryve’s equation –\nPeak flood discharge Qp = C1A2/3 – c1a2/3 where C1 = 9.0, c1 = 1.8, A = 26 sq.km and a = 20 sq.km\nQp = (9 x 262/3) – (1.8 x 202/3) = 65.9 cumecs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1000,
        "Question": "What is the approximate value of Ryve’s coefficient for combined catchment having limited areas near hills?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.5",
            "b) 8.5",
            "c) 10.2",
            "d) Up to 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For areas within 80 km from the east coast, the value of constant is taken as 6.5 and for areas within 80 to 160 km from the east coast; the value is taken as 8.5. In the case of limited areas near hills, the value of the coefficient is 10.2 and the actual observed values are always up to 40.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1001,
        "Question": "An arch dam looks like a single arch in _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plan",
            "b) front elevation",
            "c) side elevation",
            "d) both plan and front elevation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A solid wall curved in plan standing across the entire width of the river valley in a single span is an arch dam. The dam body is usually made of cement concrete. When multiple or number of arches are used supported between intermediate piers, the dam is known as buttress dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1002,
        "Question": "A non-vertical arch dam is known as a _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) buttress dam",
            "b) double curvature arch dam",
            "c) shell arch dam",
            "d) both double curvature and shell arch dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The economy in dam thickness is further increased by making the dam body not only curved in the plan but also in section. This non-vertical dam is known as the double curvature arch dam or shell-arch dam. These dams are designed as shell structures which are quite complex.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1003,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most economical type of arch dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant radius type",
            "b) Variable radius type",
            "c) Constant angle type",
            "d) Variable angle type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The curved wall will structurally behave as a cantilever retaining wall standing up from its base and partly the load will be transferred to the two ends of the arch span. The load on the cantilever wall reduces as it is distributed to the side walls which in turn reduces the thickness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1004,
        "Question": "A constant angle arch dam when compared to constant radius arch dam utilizes concrete quality of about ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43%",
            "b) 130%",
            "c) 230%",
            "d) 113%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A special type of variable radius arch dam in which the central angles of the horizontal arch rings are of the same magnitude at all elevations is called a constant angle arch dam. Such a dam proves to be economical as the design can be made by adopting the best central angle of 133°-34′.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1005,
        "Question": "Which among the following type of dam section is expected to be the thinnest and the most economical?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant angle arch dam",
            "b) Shell-arch dam",
            "c) Constant radius arch dam",
            "d) Concrete gravity dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The simplest in design as well as construction is a constant radius arch dam but uses the maximum concrete. An intermediate choice is a variable radius arch dam using around 58% of the concrete used by constant radius arch dam. A constant angle arch dam uses about 43% of the concrete used by a constant radius arch dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1006,
        "Question": "The most economical central angle of the arch rings of an arch dam can be adopted only at one place preferably at mid-height in an arch dam is of the type __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant angle arch dam",
            "b) constant radius arch dam",
            "c) both constant angle and constant radius arch dam",
            "d) variable radius arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shell arch dams are much more economical than the constant angle arch dams as their sections are quite thin. The Idduki dam in India is only 45 m thick at its base even with 170.7 m height whereas the famous Hoover dam of the USA which is a constant radius arch dam is 201m thick at its base with only 222 m in height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1007,
        "Question": "In an arch dam, the extrados curve refer to the arch rings corresponding to the ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the upstream face of the dam",
            "b) downstream face of the dam",
            "c) side face of the dam",
            "d) either upstream or downstream face of the dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most economical central angle is equal to 1330-34’ and such an angle can be adopted only at one place in constant radius arch dam since as there is considerable variation with height due to narrow V-shape of the valley. It is therefore considered to keep the economical angle of 1330-34’ at about mid-height and the angle at the top will be more than this value due to topographical conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1008,
        "Question": "A V-shaped valley with stronger foundations can suggest the choice of an arch dam is of the type ___________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant radius arch dam",
            "b) variable radius arch dam",
            "c) constant angle arch dam",
            "d) variable angle arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The arch rings corresponding to the upstream face is called the extrados curve. The arch rings corresponding to the downstream face are the intrados curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1009,
        "Question": "A constant radius arch dam is also sometimes called as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant centre arch dam",
            "b) constant angle arch dam",
            "c) variable angle arch dam",
            "d) variable centre arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The variable center arch dam is also preferred for V-shaped valleys as compared to constant radius arch dams. The constant radius arch dam may be preferred for comparatively wider U-shaped valleys.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1010,
        "Question": "The type of arch dam which generally requires overhangs at abutments is of ________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant radius type",
            "b) variable radius type",
            "c) constant angle type",
            "d) variable angle type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a constant radius arch dam, the centres of extrados, intrados as well as the centrelines of the horizontal arch rings lie on a straight vertical line at various elevations that passes through the centre of the horizontal arch ring at the crest. The centre of the arch rings is not at one point but lies along on vertical line at different heights where in variable centre arch dam the centres do not lie on the same vertical line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1011,
        "Question": "Which of the following forces is the least important in the design of arch dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reservoir water force",
            "b) Uplift pressure",
            "c) Temperature stresses",
            "d) Ice load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The uplift pressure in an arch dam is generally neglected because it is small due to the narrow base width of its body. Ice load, Temperature stresses and yield stresses are quite important in such dams and are thoroughly examined.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1012,
        "Question": "Which of the following theory is the most accurate method to design arch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The thin cylinder theory",
            "b) The theory of elastic arches",
            "c) The trial load method",
            "d) Creep theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thin cylinder theory can only be relied upon for rough estimation of dimensions of the arches. The Elastic theory does not take into account the thickness of arch rings and the restrictions at the abutments. The Trial load method removes the above objections and leads to an accurate estimation of the stresses in arches.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1013,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not an assumption of the ‘Trial Load Analysis’ method of design of arch dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plane sections normal to the axis remain plane after flexure",
            "b) Any horizontal arch ring is independent of the arch rings below and above",
            "c) Modulus of elasticity of concrete and rock foundation is equal for compression and tension",
            "d) Stresses are proportional to strains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Trial load method, the dam is divided into two systems of elements i.e. the horizontal arches and the vertical cantilevers. Each element is supposed to take a percentage of the load due to silt and water pressure. The actual distribution of the load between these elements is then arrived at by several trials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1014,
        "Question": "The thin cylinder theory for designing arch dams is based only on ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) temperature stresses",
            "b) ice pressures",
            "c) yield stresses",
            "d) hydrostatic water pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In thin cylinder theory analysis, the design is based only on hydrostatic water pressure. The theory does not take into account the shear and bending stresses in the arch, temperature stresses, and ice pressures which are quite important in arch dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1015,
        "Question": "The temperature stresses producing worst effects in the design of arch dams are caused by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rise in temperature",
            "b) fall in temperature",
            "c) both rise and fall",
            "d) no effect in the design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dam moves upstream during the summer and downstream during the winter due to the internal stresses caused by the temperature changes. In stress analysis, the low temperature becomes quite important since these stresses act additive to the reservoir water pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1016,
        "Question": "The stresses due to rib-shortening become quite important in the case of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) long thin arch dams",
            "b) thick arch dams of small angle",
            "c) both thin and thick arch dams",
            "d) all types of arch dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of an arch dam, the ends being fixed the distance between them does not change and this restriction of the change in the span causes additional stresses known as rib-shortening stresses. These stresses are small in a long thin arch but in the case of a thick arch of small-angle, they are appreciable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1017,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the basis for the design of an arch dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin cylinder theory",
            "b) Trial load theory",
            "c) Unit column theory",
            "d) Elastic theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arch dams are designed on the basis of any one of the following three methods–\n• Thin cylinder theory\n• Theory of Elastic arches\n• Trial load method\nOut of these methods, the trial load method is generally adopted nowadays and it gives precise results.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1018,
        "Question": "According to thin cylinder theory, the volume of concrete required for an arch dam would be minimum if the central angle is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 130° 34’",
            "b) 133° 34’",
            "c) 143° 34’",
            "d) 153° 34’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most economical central angle is equal to 133°-34’ and such an angle can be adopted only at one place in constant radius arch dam as there is considerable variation with height due to narrow V-shape of the valley. It is therefore considered to keep the economical angle of 133°-34’ at about mid-height for a minimum value of concrete.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1019,
        "Question": "The best design of an arch dam is when __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) all horizontal water loads are transferred horizontally to the abutments",
            "b) the dam is safe against sliding at various levels",
            "c) the load is divided between the arches and cantilevers and the deflections at the conjugal points being equal",
            "d) the deflections of the cantilevers are equal at different points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the trial load method, deflections for the arches are calculated at the points where the cantilevers cross it in each trial. If the deflection calculated at these points from cantilever elements is within reasonable limits and same, then the assumed distribution of load is correct. If not, then the calculations are repeated using a different set of load distribution until the condition is satisfied.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1020,
        "Question": "The load from the deck of a buttress dam is transmitted to the foundations through the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) corbels",
            "b) buttresses",
            "c) lateral braces",
            "d) sloping deck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Buttresses are solid walls of specified thickness and sections are constructed parallel to the flow at suitable intervals. They are used to support the vertical slab which holds the water. The stability of the dam against external forces is obtained by transferring the water pressure to the supporting buttresses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1021,
        "Question": "Multiple arch dams are generally used for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high heights",
            "b) low heights",
            "c) medium heights",
            "d) any height"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Free slab type dams are generally preferred for smaller heights and multiple arch dams are used for higher dam heights. Manicougan-5 dam in Canada is the highest multiple arch dam of the world having a height of 210 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1022,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam requires no reinforcement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed deck buttress dam",
            "b) Simple deck buttress dam",
            "c) Cantilever deck buttress dam",
            "d) Massive head buttress dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Massive head buttress dam does not use slabs or arches for the upstream face. The head of the buttresses are enlarged to meet each other to form a continuous water supporting surface. The bending, as well as diagonal tension in the upstream part of the dam,  is absent, so the deck is not reinforced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1023,
        "Question": "Which of the following dam is also known as the Amberson dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple arch buttress dam",
            "b) Mushroom head buttress dam",
            "c) Massive head buttress dam",
            "d) Free deck buttress dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Free deck slab type dam is generally preferred for smaller heights. Rodriguez dam in Mexico is the highest dam of such kind having a height of 73.2 m. They are virtually referred to as Amberson dams.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1024,
        "Question": "Which of the following component of a buttress dam is also called counterfort?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corbel",
            "b) Buttress",
            "c) Lateral brace",
            "d) Sloping deck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A counterfort or a buttress is a structure built against the wall to prevent overturning or to increase its bending strength. This term is synonymous with the buttress and is often used when referring to the dam, retaining walls and other structures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1025,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of dam requires very strong and stable foundations and is not in use as much as the other types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple dome-type dams",
            "b) Massive head type dam",
            "c) Columnar buttress type dam",
            "d) Deck slab type dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Columnar buttress type dam is a modification of the ordinary slab type and the deck is supported on columns. It requires a very durable base and more skill is required in constructing the buttresses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1026,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the earliest recorded multiple arch buttress dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meer Alam dam in India",
            "b) The Coolidge dam in Arizona",
            "c) Rodriguez dam in Mexico",
            "d) Idduki dam in Kerela, India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Coolidge dam on San Carlos River in Arizona is a multiple dome-type dam having a height of 76.2 m with buttresses @ 54.8 m apart. The Rodriguez dam in Mexico is the highest deck slab type dam having a height of 73.2 m. The Idduki dam is a concrete double curvature parabolic thin arch dam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1027,
        "Question": "The buttresses of a free deck buttress dam are provided at ‘x’ m clear spacing and buttress thickness is proposed to be ‘t’ m. The buttress section can then be designed like the section of a concrete gravity dam by considering the effective unit weight of water = Surcharge factor (S) x actual unit weight of water. The value of this surcharge factor is given as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) S = (x + t)/x",
            "b) S = (x + t)/t",
            "c) S = (x + t)/(x + 1)",
            "d) S = (x + t)/(t + 1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The economical spacing of buttresses is governed to a very large extent by the values of the upstream slope of the dam which is given by the master curve. The lower values of upstream slope lesser than 47° are not available on the master curve which shows that lower values will not prove economical for the project.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1028,
        "Question": "What is the suggested economic buttress spacing for a mean dam height of greater than 45 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.5",
            "b) 4.5 to 7.5",
            "c) 7.5 to 12",
            "d) 12 to 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surcharge factor (S) is the ratio of the dam length (x + t) to the buttress thickness (t).\nS = (x + t)/t\nThe resultant impact can be considered by increasing the unit weight of water by multiplying the actual value by a surcharge factor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1029,
        "Question": "What is the suggested slenderness ratio for simply supported RCC decks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.5 to 7.5",
            "b) 7.5 to 12",
            "c) 12 to 15",
            "d) 15 to 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The suggested economic buttress spacing in m for a normal Φ value of 40° to 50° for different dam heights –\n\n\nS.No\nMean Dam Height in m\nEconomic buttress spacing\n\n\n1.\nLess than 15\n4.5\n\n\n2.\n15 – 30\n4.5 to 7.5\n\n\n3.\n30 – 45\n7.5 to 12\n\n\n4.\nAbove 45\n12 to 15\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 1030,
        "Question": "What is suggested massiveness factor for simply supported RCC Decks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 to 3",
            "b) 3 to 4.5",
            "c) 4.5 to 7.5",
            "d) 7.5 to 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The height, thickness and spacing of buttresses can be controlled by Slenderness ratio. Slenderness ratio is the ratio of the height of the buttress to the thickness of the buttress. The value usually ranges from 12 to 15.\n"
    }
]